<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">NPJ Biofilms Microbiomes</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">NPJ Biofilms Microbiomes</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3133</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">npjbiofilms</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>NPJ Biofilms and Microbiomes</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2055-5008</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10318059</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10318059.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10318059</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10318059</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37400593</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41522-023-00409-0</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">409</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Brief Communication</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Ex vivo intestinal permeability assay (X-IPA) for tracking barrier function dynamics</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bootz-Maoz</surname><given-names initials="H">Hadar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names initials="A">Ariel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Del Mare-Roumani</surname><given-names initials="S">Sara</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bennet</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yifat</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Toister</surname><given-names initials="E">Einat</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Romano</surname><given-names initials="H">Hadar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names initials="D">Danping</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Amidror</surname><given-names initials="S">Sivan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5775-2110</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Elinav</surname><given-names initials="E">Eran</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-7647-9754</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Yissachar</surname><given-names initials="N">Nissan</given-names></name><address><email>nissan.yissachar@biu.ac.il</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.22098.31</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1937 0503</institution-id><institution>The Goodman Faculty of Life Sciences, </institution><institution>Bar-Ilan University, </institution></institution-wrap>Ramat-Gan, 5290002 Israel </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.22098.31</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1937 0503</institution-id><institution>Bar-Ilan Institute of Nanotechnology and Advanced Materials, </institution><institution>Bar-Ilan University, </institution></institution-wrap>Ramat-Gan, 5290002 Israel </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.13992.30</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0604 7563</institution-id><institution>Systems Immunology Department, </institution><institution>Weizmann Institute of Science, </institution></institution-wrap>234 Herzl Street, Rehovot, 7610001 Israel </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7497.d</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0492 0584</institution-id><institution>Microbiome &amp; Cancer Division, </institution><institution>Deutsches Krebsforschungszentrum (DKFZ), </institution></institution-wrap>Neuenheimer Feld 280, 69120 Heidelberg, Germany </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>3</day><month>7</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">425252</issue-id><elocation-id>44</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>11</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>9</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>03</day><month>07</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>05</day><month>07</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-07-05 02:25:10.273"><day>05</day><month>07</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2023</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="41522_2023_Article_409.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">The intestinal epithelial barrier facilitates homeostatic host–microbiota interactions and immunological tolerance. However, mechanistic dissections of barrier dynamics following luminal stimulation pose a substantial challenge. Here, we describe an ex vivo intestinal permeability assay, X-IPA, for quantitative analysis of gut permeability dynamics at the whole-tissue level. We demonstrate that specific gut microbes and metabolites induce rapid, dose-dependent increases to gut permeability, thus providing a powerful approach for precise investigation of barrier functions.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Biological techniques</kwd><kwd>Symbiosis</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>This work was supported by the Israel Science Foundation (grant No.1384/18), the Israel Science Foundation-Broad Institute Joint Program (grant No. 2615/18), and the Gassner Fund for Medical Research, Israel.</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© Springer Nature Limited 2023</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="Par2">The gut microbiota is confined to the lumen by a single layer of intestinal epithelial cells (IECs). Continuous replenishment of the IEC layer by Lgr5+ intestinal stem cells and physical reinforcement by inter-epithelial tight-junction (TJ) proteins are crucial to maintain barrier integrity and tissue homeostasis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. Interference with epithelial barrier integrity (e.g., by pathogenic microbes or drugs) leads to enhanced gut permeability and enables translocation of previously confined (and potentially harmful) microorganisms into the tissue and to distal locations including secondary lymph nodes and liver, where they trigger inflammatory responses<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. Indeed, disruptions to epithelial barrier functions and a ‘leaky gut’ are implicated in both intestinal and extraintestinal pathologies, including allergic and autoimmune conditions, inflammatory bowel diseases, irritable bowel syndrome and cancer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par3">Existing methods for evaluation of epithelial barrier functions and gut permeability include trans-epithelial electrical resistance (TEER) assay, measurement of ion transport in an Ussing chamber, and oral gavage of animal models with fluorescently labeled molecules followed by quantification of serum fluorescence<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. However, these approaches do not support real-time perturbations and readouts in an intact, whole-tissue setting, and thus do not provide temporal information of barrier dynamics.</p><p id="Par4">To finely dissect host-microbiota interactions, we developed a unique gut organ culture system that maintains the naïve intestinal tissue architecture and provides tight experimental control<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. We have demonstrated that this system is ideal for investigating rapid intestinal responses to specific bacterial strains<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>, whole human microbiota samples<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>, drugs and metabolites<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. The emerging realization that the gut microbiota and its associated metabolites regulate intestinal barrier functions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup> drove us to investigate whether the advantages of the gut organ culture system could be harnessed to uncover mechanisms underlying microbial regulation of gut permeability.</p><p id="Par5">Here, we aimed to measure rapid and subtle changes to gut permeability following luminal stimulation, in multiple gut tissues, under tightly controlled experimental conditions and in high temporal resolution. We developed and optimized an ex vivo intestinal permeability assay (X-IPA) in which fluorescein isothiocyanate (FITC)-dextran is infused directly into the lumen of the cultured gut tissues (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1A</xref>). Migration of luminal FITC-dextran to the extraintestinal culture medium depends on integrity of the epithelial barrier. Thus, fluorescence intensity of the extraintestinal medium corresponds with epithelial barrier integrity and permeability.<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Development of an ex vivo intestinal permeability assay (X-IPA).</title><p><bold>A</bold> Intact intestinal mice tissues are connected to the gut organ culture device and FITC-dextran is infused into the gut lumen. Diffusion over time is quantified by fluorescence intensity of the extra-intestinal medium (time-lapse imaging) and at the experiment end-point (fluorometer), as an indicator of gut permeability degree and temporal dynamics. <bold>B</bold>, <bold>C</bold> Normalized TEER values for Caco-2 cells supplemented with EGTA after 8 h (<bold>B</bold>) and versus time (<bold>C</bold>). <bold>D</bold>, <bold>E</bold> Confocal imaging of colon segments cultured for 8 h, immuno-stained for ZO-1 (white; DAPI nuclear stain in blue) (<bold>D</bold>) and quantification of ZO-1 MFI following EGTA infusion (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.03) (<bold>E</bold>). <bold>F</bold> Normalized extraintestinal medium fluorescence of colon cultures infused with 4kDa-FITC-dextran, with or without EGTA, at 2 h (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.02) and 8 h (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.04). <bold>G</bold> Normalized extraintestinal medium fluorescence in colon cultures infused with 70kDa-FITC-dextran, with or without EGTA at 4 h. <bold>H</bold> Filmstrips showing gut organ cultures infused with FITC-dextran only (Ctrl) or together with EGTA. The pseudo-color imaging illustrates MFI quantification of FITC-dextran concentrations in the extraintestinal medium. Frames are separated by 15 min. Tissue dimensions captured = ~2 cm <bold>I</bold> Single colon time traces showing normalized MFI of the extraintestinal medium in tissues infused with EGTA or sterile medium (Ctrl). Circles represent average permeability rates. <bold>J</bold> MFI and medium fluorescence intensity (O.D) are tightly correlated (<italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.9822). <bold>K</bold> Normalized extraintestinal medium fluorescence of small intestinal organ cultures infused with EGTA or sterile medium (Ctrl) at 4 h (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0001). <bold>L</bold> Normalized extraintestinal medium fluorescence of colon cultures infused with 5% EtOH or sterile medium (Ctrl) at 4 h (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0033). Statistical significance between two groups was determined by Student’s <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test, or by one-way ANOVA (for three or more independent groups), <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> values: ****&lt;0.0001; ***&lt;0.001; **&lt;0.01; ns not significant. For all panels, mean and standard deviation is shown.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e444" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41522_2023_409_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par6">In a set of proof-of-principle experiments, we measured gut permeability ex vivo in response to luminal introduction of EGTA, a calcium chelator that disrupts TJ integrity and paracellular barrier functions (confirmed using dynamic TEER assay (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1B, C</xref>) and ZO-1 staining (Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1A</xref>) in Caco-2 monolayers). Colon tissues were dissected from 14d-old mice reared under specific-pathogen-free (SPF) conditions, and connected to the gut culture device as previously described (six tissues per device; Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1A</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. Culture medium containing FITC-dextran (4 kDa) was infused directly into the cultured colons’ lumens either with or without EGTA (25 mM). Compared with controls, luminal EGTA infusion disrupted epithelial barrier integrity, as indicated by marked decreases in ZO-1 TJ protein expression (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1D, E</xref>). In agreement, luminal infusion of EGTA resulted in rapid and significant increase in extraintestinal FITC-dextran throughout the experiment (2 h, 8 h), compared with internal controls (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1F</xref>), supporting the utility of the X-IPA system in evaluating changes to gut permeability.</p><p id="Par7">We next asked whether EGTA-induced barrier loss observed in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1F</xref> is attributed to increased TJ-controlled paracellular permeability (leak pathway) or to non-specific epithelial damage (unrestricted pathway). To address this question, we used 70 kDa FITC-dextran, a larger molecule that can cross the barrier only in an unrestricted manner (in contrast to 4 kDa FITC-dextran which can pass via increased paracellular permeability<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>). Interestingly, luminal infusion of EGTA and 70 kDa FITC-dextran did not increase extraintestinal medium fluorescence (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1G</xref> and Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1D</xref>), suggesting that the X-IPA system maintains the viability and functional integrity of the epithelial barrier, and may be used to detect changes in TJ-controlled paracellular permeability.</p><p id="Par8">A major advantage of the gut organ culture system is the ability to track rapid intestinal responses to experimental perturbations, over time. To quantify barrier dynamics, we added three upright fluorescence digital microscopes (Dino-Lite) to the gut culture system setup, where each microscope tracks two cultured gut fragments (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1A</xref>). Using this set-up, we could efficiently detect subtle changes in medium concentrations of FITC-dextran by quantifying mean fluorescence intensity (MFI) measurements (dynamic range: 1–100 μg/mL; Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1B</xref>).</p><p id="Par9">We acquired time-lapse movies of gut organ cultures following luminal introduction of EGTA, at a temporal resolution of 5 min (for 2 h experiments) or 15 min (for 8 h experiments) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1H, I</xref> and Supplementary Video <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">1</xref>). For automated analysis and quantification, we developed a MATLAB-based image analysis tool and user-friendly interface (X-IPA analyzer; Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1C</xref> and extended data). This software allowed us to generate dozens of single-tissues time traces and quantify extraintestinal medium MFI, for accurate and comparable characterization of gut permeability dynamics in multiple tissues, over time (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1I</xref>). Automated analysis of time-lapse movies revealed a slow and continuous increase in extraintestinal MFI in non-stimulated tissues (average slope <italic toggle="yes">m</italic> = 0.17), which we interpret as steady-state gut permeability rate under culture conditions. In contrast, EGTA-infused tissues displayed a rapid increase in extraintestinal MFI (average slope <italic toggle="yes">m</italic> = 0.75), observed already at 2 h post-stimulation (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1I</xref> and Supplementary Video <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">1</xref>). We analyzed FITC-dextran spatial distribution along each intestinal fragment to validate tissue integrity and to exclude potential leaking of FITC-dextran from the input or output ports (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2A</xref>). Further, medium fluorescence at the experiment endpoint (measured by fluorometer) and corresponding image MFI (calculated by image analysis) were well correlated (<italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.9822), demonstrating that time-lapse imaging and analysis can reliably track and quantify gut permeability dynamics (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1J</xref>).</p><p id="Par10">We further utilized the X-IPA system to track gut permeability dynamics in EGTA-infused small intestinal organ cultures (ileum, Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1K</xref> and Supplementary Video <xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">2</xref>), and in response to barrier-disrupting ethanol<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup> (colon cultures, Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1L</xref>, Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1E</xref>, and Supplementary Video <xref rid="MOESM6" ref-type="media">3</xref>).</p><p id="Par11">Next, to explore whether the X-IPA system could detect changes to gut permeability induced by intestinal metabolites, gut organ cultures were infused with putrescine, a polyamine compound produced by the gut microbiota which we recently identified as a potent disruptor of the intestinal epithelial barrier<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. At 4 h post-stimulation, we observed a dose-dependent increase in gut permeability in putrescine-infused organ cultures (average slopes: 33 mM <italic toggle="yes">m</italic> ≈ 0; 66 mM <italic toggle="yes">m</italic> = 0.28; 100 mM <italic toggle="yes">m</italic> = 0.42), compares with controls (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2A</xref>). Automated image analysis revealed a gradual increase in the FITC-dextran diffusion rate (steeper linear slope) in response to increasing putrescine concentrations (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2B, C</xref> and Supplementary Video <xref rid="MOESM7" ref-type="media">4</xref>). These results could support a model in which TJ opening is a continuous process linearly tuned by luminal signal intensity (putrescine concentration) subsequently resulting in increased permeability.<fig id="Fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>Rapid modulation of gut permeability by metabolites and gut bacteria.</title><p><bold>A</bold>, <bold>D</bold> Normalized extraintestinal medium fluorescence of gut cultures infused with increasing putrescine concentrations (<bold>A</bold>) or equivalent load of <italic toggle="yes">B. adolescentis</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">B. fragilis</italic> cultures (<bold>D</bold>), at 4 h post-infusion (normalized to internal control). <bold>B</bold>, <bold>E</bold> Filmstrips showing gut organ cultures infused with FITC-dextran only (Ctrl) or with putrescine (<bold>B</bold>) or microbial cultures (<bold>E</bold>). The pseudo-color-imaging illustrates MFI quantification of FITC-dextran concentrations in the extraintestinal medium. Frames are separated by 10 min. <bold>C</bold>, <bold>F</bold> Single colon time traces showing normalized MFI of the extraintestinal medium in tissues infused with putrescine (<bold>C</bold>) or microbial cultures (<bold>F</bold>) and sterile medium (Ctrl). <bold>G</bold>, <bold>H</bold> Normalized TEER values of Caco-2 cells co-cultured with <italic toggle="yes">E. gallinarum</italic> (<bold>G</bold>) or <italic toggle="yes">B. acidifaciens</italic> (<bold>H</bold>), over time. <bold>I</bold> Normalized extraintestinal medium fluorescence of gut cultures infused with <italic toggle="yes">E. gallinarum</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001) or <italic toggle="yes">B. acidifaciens</italic>, for 4 h. Statistical significance was determined by one-way ANOVA, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> values: ****&lt;0.0001; ***&lt;0.001; **&lt;0.01; ns not significant.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d32e670" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="41522_2023_409_Fig2_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="Par12">Finally, we sought to examine changes to gut permeability induced by the gut microbiota. We analyzed colonic responses to the anaerobic human commensal <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium adolescentis</italic>, a Th17-inducing microbe<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup> which we recently identified as a diet-sensitive pathobiont that alters TJ integrity and disrupts gut barrier functions in vitro and in vivo<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. We infused medium containing FITC-dextran and equivalent amounts of <italic toggle="yes">B. adolescentis</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">B. fragilis</italic> (an anaerobic human symbiont that does not induce Th17 development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup> nor disrupt the epithelial barrier<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>) into the lumen of colonic organ cultures. We observed an increase in extraintestinal MFI in response to barrier-disrupting <italic toggle="yes">B. adolescentis</italic>, but not to <italic toggle="yes">B. fragilis</italic>, at 4 h post-stimulation (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2D</xref>). In agreement, time-lapse movies revealed that luminal introduction of <italic toggle="yes">B. adolescentis</italic> rapidly increased extraintestinal MFI (average slope <italic toggle="yes">m</italic> = 0.22), while tissues infused with <italic toggle="yes">B. fragilis</italic> were indistinguishable from controls (average slope <italic toggle="yes">m</italic> ≈ 0) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2E, F</xref> and Supplementary Video <xref rid="MOESM8" ref-type="media">5</xref>).</p><p id="Par13">Similar results were obtained in response to barrier-disrupting <italic toggle="yes">E. gallinarum</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>, compared with non-disrupting <italic toggle="yes">B. acidifaciens</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup> using in vitro TEER assay (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2G, H</xref>) and the X-IPA system (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2I</xref>).</p><p id="Par14">Taken together, we present a unique organ culture-based gut permeability assay. The X-IPA system provides quantitative insights into the effects of luminal perturbations on gut permeability at the whole-tissue level, thus bridging the gap between simplified in vitro assays and complex in vivo animal models. Moreover, this system allows to quantify dynamic behaviors of the intestinal barrier as they occur, over time, in high temporal resolution. We should acknowledge the current limitations of the X-IPA system. In its current setting, the system probably cannot detect transcellular epithelial passage, and is limited to short-term culture (up to 24 h) of tissues dissected from mice (not humans). Additional readouts (including next-generation sequencing, cell sorting, and imaging) applied to the cultured tissues will complement dynamic permeability measurements, thus providing a powerful approach for integrated investigations of host–microbiome interactions.</p><p id="Par15">Given the emerging therapeutic potential of barrier modulating agents, we anticipate that the ability to perturb multiple intestinal tissues and to track subsequent gut barrier functions will further advance mechanistic insights and translational discoveries.</p><sec id="Sec1"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec2"><title>Mice</title><p id="Par16">Small and large intestinal tissues used in the ex vivo organ culture system were dissected from sacrificed C57BL/6J (B6) mice. Mice were obtained from Envigo RMS (Israel) and reared in the specific-pathogen-free (SPF) facility at Bar-Ilan University (Israel). For gut organ culture permeability assays, gut tissues were dissected from 14-day-old littermates. All experiments were performed following animal protocol approved by the Bar-Ilan University ethics committee (ethics approval number BIU-BIU-IL-2203-131-1).</p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title>Gut organ culture system and X-IPA permeability assay</title><p id="Par17">Fabrication of the gut organ culture device and gut organ culture experiments (Yissachar et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>) were performed with the addition of carbon black (Holland-Moran Cas#1333-86-4) into the PDMS (184 ®SYLGARD#761036) mixture, for fabrication of black, opaque gut culture devices. Briefly, intact whole colons were dissected sterilely from 14-day-old C57BL/6 mouse littermates reared under SPF conditions. The solid lumen content was gently flushed, and the gut fragment was threaded and fixed over the luminal input and output ports of the gut organ culture device, using sterile surgical thread. The culture device was placed in a custom-made incubator that maintains a temperature of 37 °C, and tissue was maintained half-soaked in sterile, serum-free culture medium (Iscove’s Modified Dulbecco’s Medium without phenol-red (IMDM, GIBCO) supplemented with 20% KnockOut serum replacement (GIBCO), 2% B-27 and 1% of N-2 supplements (GIBCO), 1% L-glutamine, 1% non-essential amino acids, 1% HEPES) using a syringe pump. FITC-dextran (4kD) (0.5 mg/mL; Sigma-Aldrich Cas#60842-46-8) was resuspended in sterile culture medium without phenol-red and infused into the gut lumen using a syringe pump, with or without EGTA (25 mM) (Sigma-Aldrich Cas#13368-13-3), 5% EtOH, purified bacterial cultures (<italic toggle="yes">B. adolescentis</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">B. fragilis, E. gallinarum</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">B. acidifaciens</italic> at 10<sup>7-9</sup> CFU/mL) or putrescine (Sigma, diluted to final concentrations of 33/66/100 mM). Gas outlet in the device lid enabled the flow of a humidified and filtered, medical grade 95% O<sub>2</sub>/5% CO<sub>2</sub> gas mixture into the device. Experiments were terminated at 2–8h post-stimulation. A fluorescence video microscope (Dino-Lite, Iner Tech Dino-Capture 2.0 AM4115T-GRFBY) acquired time-lapse movies of the cultured tissues and their surrounding culture medium for downstream image analysis and fluorescence quantification. At the experiment end point, the FITC-dextran concentration in the extraintestinal medium was determined by quantifying the fluorescence intensity using a fluorometer (excitation 485 nm, emission 520 nm). After culture, tissues were subjected to further analysis (including immunofluorescence staining and imaging).</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Image analysis of time‐lapse imaging</title><sec id="Sec5"><title>Software development</title><p id="Par18">Automated computerized image analysis of time‐lapse movies was performed with the X-IPA Analyzer, a custom written MATLAB software (created in the MathWorks 2020 platform). The main functions in the software are image pre-processing, tissue segmentation and quantification of the green fluorescence intensity of the extraintestinal medium in each chamber, over time (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Experimental design</title><p id="Par19">The experiments were carried out within an organ culture device that contains six chambers, each containing an intact colon tissue and external medium. Three Dino-Lite microscope cameras were placed over the device, such that each one could capture two chambers. The images were taken at regular intervals of 5 min (for 2 h experiments), 10 min (for 4 h experiments) or 15 min (for 8 h experiments). A series of images per chamber was analyzed.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Analysis algorithm</title><p id="Par20">The algorithm works as follows: The tissue-images are loaded and manually cropped to select pixel-coordinates that represent the measurement area. This area includes the colon-tissue itself and the external tissue-medium. After user-confirmation, the green channel of the RGB model is chosen and the images denoised using a Gaussian filter with a standard deviation of two. The denoised images are segmented by an automated threshold using Otsu’s method from Gray-Level Histograms (Binarization), and the tissue segmentation is expanded by an additional 8 pixels in each direction. Per image, the medium pixels (area outside of the segmentation) are measured, and their mean value is calculated. These mean values are shown in a plot, demonstrating MFI (mean fluorescence intensity) changes over time.</p><p id="Par21">The O.D ratio was calculated by dividing the final concentration of the FITC-dextran (µg/mL) by the final concentration of the sterile medium (Ctrl). The MFI ratio was calculated by dividing the value of the FITC-dextran normalized-MFI final value by the sterile medium (Ctrl) normalized-MFI final value.</p><p id="Par22">All steps of analysis can be easily performed with a user-friendly interface (detailed user manual is provided in the online extended data).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Bacterial cultures</title><p id="Par23"><italic toggle="yes">B. adolescentis, B. fragilis</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">B. acidifaciens</italic> were obtained from DSMZ (Germany). <italic toggle="yes">E. gallinarum</italic> was kindly provided by Prof. Martin Kriegel (Muenster University, Germany). Bacterial classification was further validated by Sanger sequencing of the 16 S gene. Microbes were incubated overnight in rich liquid medium (2% proteose peptone (Thermo Fisher Cat#LP0085), 0.5% NaCl (Mercury Cat#1064041) and 0.5% yeast extract (Merck Cas#8013-01-2)) supplemented with 250 mg/mL glucose (Mercury Cas#50-99-7), 250 mg/mL K<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub> (Holland Moran Cas#7758-11-4), 50 mg/mL L-cysteine (Merck Cas#52-90-4), 5 mg/mL Hemin (Mercury Cat#3741) and 5 μL/mL vitamin <italic toggle="yes">K</italic><sub>1</sub> (Merck Cas#84-80-0) under anaerobic conditions. <italic toggle="yes">B. acidifaciens</italic> was first incubated in chopped meat medium and then transferred to rich liquid medium.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Cell line</title><p id="Par24">Caco-2 cell line was kindly provided by Professor Ohad Gal Mor (Sheba Medical Center, Israel). Cells were cultured at 37 °C with 5% CO<sub>2</sub> until 80% confluence. For co-culture experiments, Caco-2 cells were cultured with growth media without antibiotics and were seeded on a 24-well plate (at 2 × 10<sup>5</sup> cells per well). The cells were grown for 4 days and then incubated with 2 mM EGTA, or with purified bacterial cultures resuspended in Caco-2 growth media.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Dynamics trans-epithelial electrical resistance (TEER) measurements</title><p id="Par25">Caco-2 cells were seeded on a CytoView Z, 96-well impedance plate (5 × 10<sup>5</sup> cells per well) (Axion BioSystems; cat: Z96-IMP-96B-25) and monitored by Maestro Edge platform (Axion BioSystems) until reaching full confluence (800–1200 ohm, usually within 4 days). The barrier index (which represents barrier integrity) was calculated by the Axion “Impedance” module as the ratio between cellular resistance at low frequency (1 kHz) vs. high frequency (41 kHz). For co-culture experiments, microbes were centrifuged at 4200 × <italic toggle="yes">g</italic> for 10 min and resuspended in 1.5 mL cell culture media without antibiotics. Following serial dilutions, a final volume of 200 μL was added in each well. Microbial load (CFU/mL) was calculated in each experiment. The barrier index was measured at high temporal resolution of 1 min for 24 h and was normalized to the reference time (<italic toggle="yes">t</italic> = 0). An additional correction was performed by normalizing to the barrier index of unstimulated cells.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Immunofluorescence staining of tissue sections, and confocal imaging</title><p id="Par26">For tissue section staining, intestinal tissues were embedded in OCT and stored at −80 °C. The fresh-frozen tissues were sliced using a cryostat (CM1950) into 7 μm sections. The sections were fixed with cold acetone (100%) for 20 min, washed twice in PBS and blocked (10% donkey serum, 0.1% triton in PBS) for 1 h at room temperature. Tissue sections were then stained for ZO-1, diluted 1:100 (Invitrogen Cat 40-2200) overnight at 4 °C. Excess antibody was washed three times and incubated with secondary antibody (Cy3 anti rabbit Jackson-immuno Cat#711-165-152; diluted 1:250) for 1 h at room temperature. After washing, the sections were stained with DAPI (Merck Cat#1246530100). and mounted (fluoroshield) using an antifade reagent (Sigma F6182).</p><p id="Par27">Tissue sections were visualized using a confocal fluorescence microscope (Leica) and processed and analyzed using ImageJ software. To measure the ZO-1 intensity only in the periphery of the intestinal epithelium, an ImageJ macro was employed, using the following workflow: The images were first Gaussian smoothed (sigma = 2), and then segmented by the percentile auto threshold algorithm using the E-cadherin staining. Binary holes were filled to obtain a uniform layer. Next, an ROI (region of interest) band, representing the edge of the intestinal crypt, enclosing the ZO-1 staining, was created as follows: First, the segmented tissue was duplicated and eroded to get a thinner segment. Second, the segmented tissue image was duplicated and dilated to get a wider segment. Finally, the eroded image was subtracted from the dilated image to yield a band, representing the tissue edge. Note, that while the macro allows adjustment of the number of pixels to erode and dilate, once optimal numbers were determined for our images to cover ZO-1, these factors were kept constant for all treatments and for each experiment type. Finally, Analyze Particles was employed to measure the intensity of the total ZO-1 (Cy3) in the ROI.</p><p id="Par28">The intensity of ZO-1 in cultured cells was measured as follows: Smoothing on the ZO-1 image (channel 3 Cy3) using Gaussian blur (sigma = 1) was applied. Next, the background was subtracted (rolling ball = 10). The cells were then segmented using the automatic Otsu algorithm. Finally, the intensity of the ZO-1 marker was calculated according to the binary segmented image.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Immunofluorescence staining of cultured cells</title><p id="Par29">Cells were seeded 4 days pre-treatment on 13 mm coverslips cleaned with 70% EtOH and treated with PDL (0.08 μg/mL) in 24-well plate. Caco-2 cells were then washed with PBS and co-cultured with EGTA (2 mM) for 1 h. Caco-2 cells were fixed and permeabilized (0.5% triton in 3% PFA) for 3 min and then washed with PBS. Then, cells were further fixed (3% PFA) for 30 min, and washed twice with PBS for 10 min. Cells were incubated with blocking solution (10% donkey serum) for 1 h. The cells were then labeled with primary antibody against ZO-1, diluted 1:200 (BD cat:610967) overnight at 4 °C. Excess antibody was washed three times with blocking solution and the cells were incubated with secondary antibody (Cy3 anti mouse, diluted 1:500, Jackson cat: 715-165-151) for 1 h at room temperature. Cells were washed and mounted using fluoro-mount-G. Cells were visualized using a confocal fluorescence microscope (Leica).</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Reporting summary</title><p id="Par30">Further information on research design is available in the <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">Nature Research Reporting Summary</xref> linked to this article.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><sec id="Sec14"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41522_2023_409_MOESM1_ESM.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary Information</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41522_2023_409_MOESM2_ESM.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Reporting Summary</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41522_2023_409_MOESM3_ESM.zip" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>user manual of X-IPA analyser and its source data</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41522_2023_409_MOESM4_ESM.mp4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary video 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41522_2023_409_MOESM5_ESM.mp4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary video 2</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41522_2023_409_MOESM6_ESM.mp4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary video 3</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM7" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41522_2023_409_MOESM7_ESM.mp4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary video 4</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM8" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="41522_2023_409_MOESM8_ESM.mp4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary video 5</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher’s note</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1038/s41522-023-00409-0.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work is dedicated to the loving memory of Professor Nir Friedman z”l—a dear friend, a mentor, and a source of inspiration. We thank Sondra Turjeman for critical editing of the manuscript; Gitali Naim, Hagar Morad, Shir Ben-Aaron, and Nadav Vernia for computational image analysis; and members of the Yissachar lab for insightful discussions. This work was supported by the Israel Science Foundation (grant No. 1384/18), the Israel Science Foundation-Broad Institute Joint Program (grant No. 2615/18), the Israel Science Foundation-Israel Precision Medicine Partnership (grant No. 3061/22), and the Gassner Fund for Medical Research, Israel.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>Conceptualization, S.D.M.-R., H.B.-M., S.A., E.E., and N.Y.; investigation, H.B.-M., A.S., S.D.M.-R., Y.B., D.Z., and S.A; writing, H.B.-M., A.S., and N.Y.; funding acquisition, N.Y.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All data generated and analyzed in this study are available within the main text and/or the Supplementary Materials. Code and scripts generated in this study are available in the Supplementary Materials. Any additional information that may be required to support the findings of this study are available upon reasonable request from the corresponding author.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par31">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intestinal mucosal barrier function in health and disease</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Immunol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>799</fpage><lpage>809</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nri2653</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19855405</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Within-host evolution of a gut pathobiont facilitates liver translocation</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2022</year><volume>607</volume><fpage>563</fpage><lpage>570</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-022-04949-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35831502</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9308686</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Manfredo Vieira</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Translocation of a gut pathobiont drives autoimmunity in mice and humans</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2018</year><volume>359</volume><fpage>1156</fpage><lpage>1161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aar7201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29590047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5959731</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruff</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Greiling</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kriegel</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Host-microbiota interactions in immune-mediated diseases</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Microbiol.</source><year>2020</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>521</fpage><lpage>538</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41579-020-0367-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32457482</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Akdis</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Does the epithelial barrier hypothesis explain the increase in allergy, autoimmunity and other chronic conditions?</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Immunol.</source><year>2021</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>739</fpage><lpage>751</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41577-021-00538-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33846604</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schoultz</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keita</surname><given-names>ÅV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The intestinal barrier and current techniques for the assessment of gut permeability</article-title><source>Cells</source><year>2020</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1909</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/cells9081909</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32824536</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7463717</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yissachar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An intestinal organ culture system uncovers a role for the nervous system in microbe-immune crosstalk</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2017</year><volume>168</volume><fpage>1135.e12</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2017.02.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28262351</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5396461</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duscha</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Propionic acid shapes the multiple sclerosis disease course by an immunomodulatory mechanism</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2020</year><volume>180</volume><fpage>1067.e16</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2020.02.035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32160527</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bootz-Maoz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Diet-induced modifications to human microbiome reshape colonic homeostasis in irritable bowel syndrome</article-title><source>Cell Rep.</source><year>2022</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>111657</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2022.111657</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36384106</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grosheva</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>High-throughput screen identifies host and microbiota regulators of intestinal barrier function</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><year>2020</year><volume>159</volume><fpage>1807</fpage><lpage>1823</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2020.07.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32653496</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heppert</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcriptional programmes underlying cellular identity and microbial responsiveness in the intestinal epithelium</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Gastroenterol. Hepatol.</source><year>2021</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41575-020-00357-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33024279</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7997278</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tilg</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zmora</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adolph</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elinav</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The intestinal microbiota fuelling metabolic inflammation</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Immunol.</source><year>2019</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>40</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41577-019-0198-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31388093</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Azriel, S., Bootz, H., Shemesh, A., Amidror, S. &amp; Yissachar, N. An intestinal gut organ culture system for analyzing host-microbiota interactions. <italic toggle="yes">J. Vis. Exp</italic>. 10.3791/62779 (2021).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3791/62779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34279494</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>P-Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>IL-22 upregulates epithelial Claudin-2 to drive diarrhea and enteric pathogen clearance</article-title><source>Cell Host Microbe</source><year>2017</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>671.e4</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chom.2017.05.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28618266</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5541253</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elamin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ethanol impairs intestinal barrier function in humans through mitogen activated protein kinase signaling: a combined in vivo and in vitro approach</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e107421</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0107421</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25226407</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4165763</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identifying species of symbiont bacteria from the human gut that, alone, can induce intestinal Th17 cells in mice</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2016</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>E8141</fpage><lpage>E8150</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1617460113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27911839</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5167147</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mazmanian</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Round</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kasper</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A microbial symbiosis factor prevents intestinal inflammatory disease</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2008</year><volume>453</volume><fpage>620</fpage><lpage>625</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature07008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18509436</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Bacteroides acidifaciens in the gut plays a protective role against CD95-mediated liver injury</article-title><source>Gut Microbes</source><year>2022</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>2027853</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/19490976.2022.2027853</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35129072</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8820816</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J-Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gut commensal Bacteroides acidifaciens prevents obesity and improves insulin sensitivity in mice</article-title><source>Mucosal Immunol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>104</fpage><lpage>116</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mi.2016.42</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27118489</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ginsenosides Rb3 and Rd reduce polyps formation while reinstate the dysbiotic gut microbiota and the intestinal microenvironment in ApcMin/+ mice</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>12552</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-12644-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28970547</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5624945</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>