<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cell Mol Gastroenterol Hepatol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cell Mol Gastroenterol Hepatol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3079</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">cmgh</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cellular and Molecular Gastroenterology and Hepatology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2352-345X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8020481</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC8020481.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">8020481</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">8020481</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33482393</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcmgh.2021.01.004</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2352-345X(21)00010-2</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Exposure to p40 in Early Life Prevents Intestinal Inflammation in Adulthood Through Inducing a Long-Lasting Epigenetic Imprint on TGFβ</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yilin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name name-style="western"><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names initials="OG">Oliver G.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="aff7" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">4</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name name-style="western"><surname>Means</surname><given-names initials="AL">Anna L.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff7" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peek</surname><given-names initials="RM">Richard M.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name name-style="western"><surname>Washington</surname><given-names initials="MK">M. Kay</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6"><name name-style="western"><surname>Acra</surname><given-names initials="SA">Sari A.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au7"><name name-style="western"><surname>Polk</surname><given-names initials="DB">D. Brent</given-names></name><xref rid="aff8" ref-type="aff">8</xref><xref rid="aff9" ref-type="aff">9</xref><xref rid="aff10" ref-type="aff">10</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au8"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names initials="F">Fang</given-names></name><email>fang.yan@vumc.org</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">∗</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Pediatrics, Vanderbilt University Medical Center, Nashville, Tennessee</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Pathology, Microbiology and Immunology, Vanderbilt University Medical Center, Nashville, Tennessee</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>4</label>Epithelial Biology Center, Vanderbilt University Medical Center, Nashville, Tennessee</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>5</label>Vanderbilt-Ingram Cancer Center, Vanderbilt University Medical Center, Nashville, Tennessee</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>6</label>Department of Surgery, Vanderbilt University Medical Center, Nashville, Tennessee</aff><aff id="aff6"><label>7</label>Department of Medicine, Vanderbilt University Medical Center, Nashville, Tennessee</aff><aff id="aff7"><label>3</label>Department of Cell and Developmental Biology, Vanderbilt University, Nashville, Tennessee</aff><aff id="aff8"><label>8</label>Department of Pediatrics, Keck School of Medicine of University of Southern California, Los Angeles, California</aff><aff id="aff9"><label>9</label>Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Medicine, Keck School of Medicine of University of Southern California, Los Angeles, California</aff><aff id="aff10"><label>10</label>Division of Gastroenterology, Hepatology and Nutrition, Children’s Hospital Los Angeles, Los Angeles, California</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>∗</label><bold>Correspondence</bold> Address correspondence to: Fang Yan, MD, PhD, Department of Pediatrics, Vanderbilt University Medical Center, 2215 Garland Avenue, MRB IV, Room 1035, Nashville, Tennessee 37232-0696. fax: (615) 343-5323. <email>fang.yan@vumc.org</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>1</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue>5</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">378487</issue-id><fpage>1327</fpage><lpage>1345</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>3</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>1</month><year>2021</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>19</day><month>01</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>08</day><month>04</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2021-04-09 00:16:28.233"><day>09</day><month>04</month><year>2021</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2021 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><abstract id="abs0010"><sec><title>Background &amp; Aims</title><p>Colonization by gut microbiota in early life confers beneficial effects on immunity throughout the host’s lifespan. We sought to elucidate the mechanisms whereby neonatal supplementation with p40, a probiotic functional factor, reprograms intestinal epithelial cells for protection against adult-onset intestinal inflammation.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>p40 was used to treat young adult mouse colonic (YAMC) epithelial cells with and without deletion of a methyltransferase, su(var)3-9, enhancer-of-zeste and trithorax domain–containing 1β (Setd1β), and mice in early life or in adulthood. Anti–transforming growth factor β (TGFβ)-neutralizing antibodies were administered to adult mice with and without colitis induced by 2,4,6-trinitrobenzenesulfonic acid or dextran sulfate sodium. We examined <italic toggle="yes">Setd1b</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Tgfb</italic> gene expression, TGFβ production, monomethylation and trimethylation of histone H3 on the lysine 4 residue (H3K4me1/3), H3K4me3 enrichment in <italic toggle="yes">Tgfb</italic> promoter, differentiation of regulatory T cells (Tregs), and the inflammatory status.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>p40 up-regulated expression of <italic toggle="yes">Setd1b</italic> in YAMC cells. Accordingly, p40 enhanced H3K4me1/3 in YAMC cells in a Setd1β-dependent manner. p40-regulated Setd1β mediated programming the TGFβ locus into a transcriptionally permissive chromatin state and promoting TGFβ production in YAMC. Furthermore, transient exposure to p40 during the neonatal period and in adulthood resulted in the immediate increase in <italic toggle="yes">Tgfb</italic> gene expression. However, only neonatal p40 supplementation induced the sustained H3K4me1/3 and <italic toggle="yes">Tgfb</italic> gene expression that persisted into adulthood. Interfering with TGFβ function by neutralizing antibodies diminished the long-lasting effects of neonatal p40 supplementation on differentiation of Tregs and protection against colitis in adult mice.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Exposure to p40 in early life enables an epigenetic imprint on TGFβ, leading to long-lasting production of TGFβ by intestinal epithelial cells to expand Tregs and protect the gut against inflammation.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="abs0015"><title>Graphical abstract</title><fig id="undfig1" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fx1.jpg"/></fig></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Histone Methyltransferase</kwd><kwd>Intestinal Epithelial Cell</kwd><kwd>Probiotic Function Factor</kwd><kwd>Regulatory T Cell</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group id="kwrds0015"><title>Abbreviations used in this paper</title><kwd>ChIP, chromatin immunoprecipitation</kwd><kwd>DSS, dextran sulfate sodium</kwd><kwd>EGFR, epidermal growth factor receptor</kwd><kwd>ELISA, enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay</kwd><kwd>FBS, fetal bovine serum</kwd><kwd>H3K4me, histone H3 on the lysine 4 methylation</kwd><kwd>IBD, inflammatory bowel disease</kwd><kwd>IEC, intestinal epithelial cell</kwd><kwd>IFN-γ, interferon-γ</kwd><kwd>IL, interleukin</kwd><kwd>LGG, <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus rhamnosus</italic> GG</kwd><kwd>mRNA, messenger RNA</kwd><kwd>MSIE, mouse small intestinal epithelial</kwd><kwd>RT-PCR, reverse- transcription polymerase chain reaction</kwd><kwd>Setd1β, su(var)3-9, enhancer-of-zeste and trithorax domain–containing 1β</kwd><kwd>shRNA, short hairpin RNA</kwd><kwd>SV40, simian virus 40</kwd><kwd>Treg, regulatory T cell</kwd><kwd>TNBS, 2,4,6-trinitrobenzenesulfonic acid</kwd><kwd>TGFβ, transforming growth factor β</kwd><kwd>TNF, tumor necrosis factor</kwd><kwd>WT, wild-type</kwd><kwd>YAMC, young adult mouse colonic</kwd><kwd>ZO-1, zonula occludens-1</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="p0010"><boxed-text id="dtbox1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Summary</title></caption><p id="p0015">A functional factor of probiotics, p40, stimulates long-lasting epigenetic imprint on transforming growth factor β through up-regulating a methyltransferase, su(var)3-9, enhancer-of-zeste and trithorax domain–containing 1β, in intestinal epithelial cells. This novel mechanism is involved in colitis prevention in adulthood by p40 supplementation in early life–induced sustained transforming growth factor β production in mice.</p></boxed-text></p><p id="p0020">Probiotics, which originally were defined as “living microorganisms with low or no pathogenicity that exert beneficial effects on the health of the host,”<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> are among a broad range of beneficial microbes naturally living in the human body. Evidence from current research using animal models and in vitro approaches has identified distinct cellular and molecular mechanisms through which probiotics exert health-promoting effects on the host. The beneficial effects of probiotics include regulating immunity, in terms of inhibiting proinflammatory and enhancing anti-inflammatory responses, maintaining intestinal epithelial integrity, such as preservation of barrier function and blockade of apoptosis in intestinal epithelial cells (IECs), balancing the gut microbiota profile, and blocking pathogenic bacteria.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> However, probiotics in clinical trials yielded inconclusive results, thus, there is no strong evidence to support the clinical efficacy of probiotics.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> The uncertain bioavailability and biopharmacology of probiotics in the gastrointestinal tract has posed challenges in assessing the beneficial effects of probiotics in prior clinical trials.</p><p id="p0025">Increasing evidence suggests that components of probiotics, including probiotic-derived products and metabolites by probiotics, serve as functional factors for probiotic action. Application of these previously unrecognized functional factors could serve as therapeutic targets, bypassing clinical limitations of direct probiotic use. p40, which is a secretory protein originally isolated and cloned from culture supernatant of a probiotic bacterium, <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus rhamnosus</italic> GG (LGG),<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> represents one such probiotic-derived functional product. Phylogenic analysis showed that p40 is present mainly in <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus casei</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus paracasei</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">L rhamnosus</italic> phylogenomic groups.<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> Studies to functionally assess p40 showed that this protein transactivates epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) in IECs, which is required for inhibiting cytokine-induced apoptosis in IECs, preserving barrier function, up-regulating mucin production, and stimulating IgA production in the prevention and treatment of colitis in mice.<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> Because IECs provide the frontline response to the gut microbiota in maintaining intestinal homeostasis,<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> p40 has the potential to promote intestinal health.</p><p id="p0030">Colonization of the gut microbiota during a critical window of early life confers life-long health outcomes in human beings and animals.<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> Dysbiosis in infants and children is associated with increased susceptibility to inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) in adults.<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref> Therefore, elucidating the mechanisms underlying gut microbiota-regulated long-term health outcomes could provide opportunities to develop early life interventions to prevent IBD throughout a patient’s lifespan. Both neonatal LGG colonization<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> and transient exposure to p40 in the neonatal period<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> in mice promoted intestinal functional maturation. Furthermore, p40 supplementation in early life was sufficient to induce sustained expansion of regulatory T cells (Tregs) in the intestinal lamina propria and durable protection against colitis that extends into adulthood.<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> Therefore, this work was focused on elucidating the mechanisms whereby exposure to p40 in early life reprograms IECs for protection against adult-onset intestinal inflammation.</p><p id="p0035">Epigenetic programming serves as one of the mechanisms though which host cells recognize and translate microbial signals into long-term specific cellular responses. Epigenetic modifications have been shown to allow the gut microbiota to regulate gene expression and control cellular responses in IECs<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref> and immune cells.<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref> Su(var)3-9, enhancer-of-zeste and trithorax domain containing 1 (Setd1)β is a class 2 lysine methyltransferase that operates alongside other adaptor subunits within the complex proteins associated with Set1 (COMPASS) to catalyze monomethylation and trimethylation of histone H3 lysine 4 residue (H3K4me1/3) at enhancer and promoter sites to activate target gene expression.<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> Here, we show that p40 stimulates Setd1β expression, leading to the increase in H3K4me3 within the <italic toggle="yes">Tgfb1</italic> locus for up-regulating expression of transforming growth factor β (TGFβ) in IECs. Notably, p40 supplementation in early life induces sustained increase in TGFβ production in adult mice, which contributes to promoting differentiation of Tregs and protecting against colitis in adult mice. These findings support early life administration of oral p40 as a novel strategy to prevent intestinal inflammation in adulthood.</p><sec id="sec1"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec1.1"><title>p40 Up-regulates TGFβ Production in IECs, Leading to Protective Cellular Responses</title><p id="p0040">The up-regulation of TGFβ by IECs for the induction of intestinal Tregs represents one of the mechanisms through which the gut microbiota contributes to maintaining intestinal homeostasis.<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref> Our previous studies implied that p40 potentially may stimulate TGFβ production, leading to induction of Tregs, based on the evidence that conditioned medium from p40-treated IECs stimulated differentiation of Tregs, which was blocked by TGFβ-neutralizing antibodies.<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> We therefore tested whether and how p40 stimulates TGFβ production in IECs.</p><p id="p0045">We have reported that p40 promotes growth of enteroids.<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> The effects of p40 on stimulating <italic toggle="yes">Tgfb1</italic> gene expression in IECs was first examined in the colonoid (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref><italic toggle="yes">A</italic>) and enteroid models from wild-type (WT) mice in this study. Compared with untreated controls, p40 treatments significantly up-regulated <italic toggle="yes">Tgfb1</italic> gene expression in both models (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref><italic toggle="yes">B</italic>). The effects of p40 on <italic toggle="yes">Tgfb1</italic> gene expression and protein production were examined further in the young adult mouse colonic (YAMC) epithelial cells.<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref> p40 up-regulated <italic toggle="yes">Tgfb1</italic> gene expression in YAMC cells in a time-dependent manner (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref><italic toggle="yes">C</italic>). The TGFβ protein levels in cell culture supernatants were examined by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) analysis. Cell culture supernatants were collected from cells treated with p40 for different times with treatment ending at the same time. Compared with the TGFβ levels in control YAMC cell culture supernatants, p40 treatment stimulated secretion of TGFβ by YAMC cells (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref><italic toggle="yes">D</italic>). Interestingly, the levels of TGFβ in the culture supernatants did not persist over time with p40 treatment. The TGFβ levels in cell culture supernatants from cells with 2-hour p40 treatment were significantly higher than those from cells with 4- or 6-hour p40 treatment (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref><italic toggle="yes">D</italic>). This evidence presumably is owing to the ligand consumption induced by TGFβ binding TGFβ-receptor I and II on the cell surface. Therefore, accumulated levels of TGFβ in culture supernatants from cells with longer p40 treatment are lower than those from cells with shorter p40 treatment.<fig id="fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>p40 stimulates TGFβ production in IECs.</bold> (<italic toggle="yes">A</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B</italic>) Enteroids and colonoids from WT mice were cultured in IntestiCult organoid growth medium in the presence and absence of p40 (100 ng/mL). (<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>) Representative images of colonoids at the indicated days after culture are shown. Images were taken using a light microscope at a magnification of 10×. (<italic toggle="yes">C</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">D</italic>) YAMC cells were treated with p40 at 10 ng/mL for the indicated times. RNA was isolated from (<italic toggle="yes">B</italic>) enteroids and colonoids cultured for 9 days, and (<italic toggle="yes">C</italic>) YAMC cells for RT-PCR analysis of the expression levels of <italic toggle="yes">Tgfb</italic> mRNA. The <italic toggle="yes">Tgfb</italic> mRNA expression levels in the control groups were set as 1. The mRNA expression levels in treated groups were compared with the control group. (<italic toggle="yes">D</italic>) Supernatants from YAMC cell culture with and without p40 treatment were collected for assessing the amount of TGFβ release using enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay. The TGFβ concentration is presented as picograms per 10<sup>6</sup> cells. (<italic toggle="yes">B–D</italic>) Data are quantified from 3 independent experiments. (<italic toggle="yes">B</italic>) For each experiment, data represent the average of at least 5 enteroids or colonoids in each group. ∗<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .05 compared with the control group. <sup>#</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .05 compared with the 2-hour p40 treatment group.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr1.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0050">TGFβ binding to the TGFβ-receptor complex activates intrinsic kinase activity leading to phosphorylation of downstream targets, including SMAD2/3, which interact with SMAD4 for the regulatory effects.<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> We next examined if p40 might activate downstream TGFβ signaling in IECs. YAMC cells were treated with p40 for various times and the SMAD2 and 3 phosphorylation states were examined using Western blot analysis. SMAD2 and 3 phosphorylation was increased by p40 treatment for 1–4 hours (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref><italic toggle="yes">A</italic>).<fig id="fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>p40-stimulated TGFβ production in IECs contributes to protective epithelial cellular responses.</bold> (<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>) YAMC cells were treated with p40 (10 ng/mL) for the indicated times. Total cellular proteins were prepared for Western blot analysis. β-actin blot was used as the protein loading control. (<italic toggle="yes">B</italic>) Caco<sub>2</sub> cells were treated with H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (20 μmol/L) for 4 hours with or without 1-hour pretreatment of p40 (10 ng/mL) and TGFβ-neutralizing antibody (1 μg/mL). (<italic toggle="yes">C</italic>) Total cellular proteins from <italic toggle="yes">IMC</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">S4fl/fl</italic></sup> and <italic toggle="yes">IMC</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">S4null</italic></sup> cells were prepared for Western blot analysis. (<italic toggle="yes">D</italic>) <italic toggle="yes">IMC</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">S4fl/fl</italic></sup> and <italic toggle="yes">IMC</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">S4null</italic></sup> cells were treated with H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (20 μmol/L) for 4 hours with or without 1-hour pretreatment of p40 (10 ng/mL). The cells were fixed and immunostained to localize ZO-1 using an anti–ZO-1 antibody and a Cy3-conjugated secondary antibody (red). Nuclei were stained with 4′,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (blue). Membrane (<italic toggle="yes">white arrows</italic>) and intracellular (<italic toggle="yes">yellow arrows</italic>) ZO-1 distribution are shown. Images were taken using a fluorescent microscope at a magnification of 40×. (<italic toggle="yes">E</italic>) Cells were treated with lipopolysaccharide (LPS) (1 μg/mL) with and without p40 (10 ng/mL) for 24 hours. RNA was isolated for RT-PCR analysis of the expression levels of indicated genes. The mRNA expression levels in the control groups were set as 1. The mRNA expression levels in treated groups were compared with the control group of the same cell line. (<italic toggle="yes">A</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">C</italic>) The fold changes of band density are shown under the blot. (<italic toggle="yes">E</italic>) ∗<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .05 compared with the control group of the same cell line. Data in this figure are representative of at least 3 independent experiments. Ab, antibody; CCL, CC chemokine ligands; KC, keratinocytes-derived chemokine; P-SMAD3, phosphorylated-SMAD3; T-SMAD3, total-SMAD3.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr2.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0055">Activation of TGFβ signaling plays roles in preserving the intestinal barrier function<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> and inhibiting proinflammatory cytokines and chemokine production in IECs.<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref> Therefore, the roles of p40-stimulated increase in TGFβ production in promoting protective cellular responses in IECs was tested. To this end, 2 complementary TGFβ loss-of-function approaches were used: blocking the activity of secreted TGFβ with neutralizing antibodies and interference of downstream TGFβ signaling through deletion of floxed <italic toggle="yes">Smad4</italic> alleles in IECs. H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> induced disruption of the barrier function in Caco2 cells by redistribution of a tight junctional protein, zonula occludens-1 (ZO-1), from the apical tight junctional complex to the cytoplasmic compartment observed by immunostaining, which was inhibited by p40 treatment (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref><italic toggle="yes">B</italic>), an effect that was abolished by co-treatment with TGFβ-neutralizing antibodies (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref><italic toggle="yes">B</italic>). Immortalized mouse colonocytes with floxed <italic toggle="yes">Smad4</italic> alleles (<italic toggle="yes">IMC</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">S4fl/fl</italic></sup>) were generated from mice on the Immortomouse background.<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref>
<italic toggle="yes">IMC</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">S4fl/fl</italic></sup> cells were transduced with adenoviral-Cre to delete <italic toggle="yes">Smad4</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">IMC</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">S4null</italic></sup>)<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref> (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref><italic toggle="yes">C</italic>). p40 inhibited the H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced disruption of tight junctions in <italic toggle="yes">IMC</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">S4fl/fl</italic></sup> cells, but not in <italic toggle="yes">IMC</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">S4null</italic></sup> cells (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref><italic toggle="yes">D</italic>). In addition, p40 was able to block lipopolysaccharide-induced expression of proinflammatory chemokines, C-C motif chemokine ligand 20, and keratinocyte chemoattractant in <italic toggle="yes">IMC</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">S4fl/fl</italic></sup> cells. p40 failed to exert these effects in <italic toggle="yes">IMC</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">S4null</italic></sup> cells (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref><italic toggle="yes">E</italic>). Collectively, these data suggest that a p40-stimulated increase in TGFβ production supports intestinal barrier function and attenuates inflammatory cytokine release from IECs.</p></sec><sec id="sec1.2"><title>Sustained Increase in <italic toggle="yes">Tgfb</italic> Gene Expression Is Induced by p40 Supplementation in Early Life in Mice</title><p id="p0060">To investigate the in vivo effects of p40 on <italic toggle="yes">Tgfb1</italic> gene expression, we used an oral encapsulation and microbial enzyme-driven release system using a food-grade pectin and zein mixture to specifically deliver p40 to the small intestine and the colon.<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> These hydrogels can protect proteins, such as p40, from damage by proteases, acid, and other intestinal contents in the intestinal tract.<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> The short-term effects of p40 supplementation on stimulating <italic toggle="yes">Tgfb1</italic> gene expression in mice were tested in the early stage of life and in adulthood. Neonatal p40 supplementation was performed from postnatal day 2 to day 13 (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref><italic toggle="yes">A</italic>). For adult p40 supplementation, 6-week-old mice received p40 hydrogels at 20 μg/d for 2 weeks (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>A). Mice were killed at the end of the p40 supplementation for testing <italic toggle="yes">Tgfb1</italic> gene expression in the colonic mucosa. Hydrogels without p40 were used as a control. <italic toggle="yes">Tgfb1</italic> messenger RNA (mRNA) levels were up-regulated significantly in colonic tissues of both neonatal and adult mice at the point immediately after p40 treatment, compared with levels in mice receiving control hydrogel treatment alone (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref><italic toggle="yes">A</italic>).<fig id="fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>p40 supplementation in early stage has a long-term effect on the increase in Tgfb gene expression in mice.</bold> (<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>) For testing the short-term effects of p40 in neonate and adult mice, WT mice were supplemented with p40 from postnatal day 2 to day 14 or from week 6 to week 8. Mice were killed at the end of treatment. (<italic toggle="yes">B</italic>) For testing the long-term effects of p40 supplementation in neonatal stage and in adulthood, WT mice were supplemented with p40 from postnatal day 2 to day 21 (neo-p40) and from week 6 to week 8 (adult-p40). Mice supplemented with hydrogels without p40 were used as controls. Mice were killed 4 weeks after the end of p40 supplementation. Each symbol represents one mouse in <italic toggle="yes">A</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B</italic>. (<italic toggle="yes">C</italic>) For testing the sustained effects of p40 on <italic toggle="yes">Tgfb</italic> gene expression in mouse enteroids, enteroids from WT mice were treated with p40 (100 ng/mL) and passaged as indicated. RNA was isolated from colonic tissues and enteroids for RT-PCR analysis of <italic toggle="yes">Tgfb1</italic> gene expression. The <italic toggle="yes">Tgfb1</italic> mRNA expression levels in the control groups were set as 1. The mRNA expression levels in treated groups were compared with the control group. (<italic toggle="yes">C</italic>) Data are quantified from 3 independent cultures.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr3.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0065">The long-term effects of p40 supplementation on stimulating <italic toggle="yes">Tgfb1</italic> gene expression were examined in mice receiving p40 treatment in either the neonatal period (days 1–21) or in adulthood (weeks 6–8). For these experiments, <italic toggle="yes">Tgfb1</italic> expression was measured 4 weeks after the final treatment (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref><italic toggle="yes">B</italic>). Remarkably, neonatal p40 supplementation induced long-lasting effects on increased TGFβ gene expression in the colonic tissues of mice at least 4 weeks after p40 exposure ended, an effect not seen in adult mice treated with p40 (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref><italic toggle="yes">B</italic>). We further found that <italic toggle="yes">Tgfb</italic> gene expression was up-regulated in the first and second passages of enteroids without p40 treatment from the original culture treated with p40 (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref><italic toggle="yes">C</italic>), which indicates the direct effects of p40 on the intestinal epithelium. These results not only provide evidence that p40 stimulates TGFβ production in IECs, but show an important novel finding that supplementation with p40 in neonates, but not in adult mice, induces a sustained increase in mucosal <italic toggle="yes">Tgfb1</italic> mRNA expression.</p></sec><sec id="sec1.3"><title>Epigenetic Regulation by p40 Promotes TGFβ Production in IECs</title><p id="p0070">The long-lasting effects by neonatal p40 supplementation raise the possibility that p40 exposure imprints the neonatal intestine with a stable epigenetic program that protects against inflammatory conditions. Increasing evidence indicates a significant relationship between the epigenetic modification induced by maternal and neonatal factors, including microbiota composition in early life, and health and diseases in adulthood.<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref> In particular, the gut microbiota can regulate epigenetic modifications in the intestine, including H3K4me3, which is permissive for gene activation.<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref> We therefore asked if p40 might regulate TGFβ production through H3K4 methyltransferase, <italic toggle="yes">Setd1b</italic>. We found that p40 significantly up-regulated <italic toggle="yes">Setd1b</italic> gene expression (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref><italic toggle="yes">A</italic>) and protein production (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref><italic toggle="yes">B</italic>) in YAMC cells. The increase in <italic toggle="yes">Setd1b</italic> gene expression was observed in enteroids and colonoids with p40 treatment (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref><italic toggle="yes">C</italic>). Furthermore, up-regulation of Setd1β protein also was coupled to a global increase in H3K4me1 and H3K4me3 in YAMC cells (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref><italic toggle="yes">D</italic>). We did not find significant effects of p40 on the regulation of other methyltransferases, such as Setd1α, mixed lineage leukemia (MLL)1, or MLL2 in YAMC (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref><italic toggle="yes">E</italic>). It should be noted that p40 was shown to up-regulate the level of WD repeat-containing protein (Wdr)82 in YAMC cells, an adaptor subunit within the COMPASS complex (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref><italic toggle="yes">E</italic>). Our future study will investigate whether p40–up-regulated Wdr82 mediates recruitment of methyltransferases to the TGFβ locus.<fig id="fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>p40 up-regulates <italic toggle="yes">Setd1β</italic> expression in IECs.</bold> (<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">B</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">D</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">E</italic>) YAMC cells were treated with p40 at 10 ng/mL for the indicated times. (<italic toggle="yes">C</italic>) Enteroids and colonoids were generated and cultured as described in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>, in the presence or absence of p40 (100 ng/mL). (<italic toggle="yes">A</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">C</italic>) RNA was isolated from (<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>) YAMC cells and (<italic toggle="yes">C</italic>) enteroids and colonoids for RT-PCR analysis of the levels of <italic toggle="yes">Setd1b</italic> mRNA. <italic toggle="yes">Setd1b</italic> mRNA expression levels in the control groups were set as 1. The mRNA expression levels in treated groups were compared with the control group. Data are quantified from 3 independent experiments. (<italic toggle="yes">C</italic>) For each experiment, data represent the average of at least 5 enteroids or colonoids in each group. (<italic toggle="yes">B</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">D</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">E</italic>) Total cellular proteins were prepared from YAMC cells for Western blot analysis. β-actin blot was used as the protein loading control. The fold changes of band density are shown under the blot. Data are representative of at least 3 independent experiments. ∗<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .05 compared with the control group.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr4.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0075">We next examined whether p40 might regulate <italic toggle="yes">Setd1b</italic> gene expression and global H3K4 methylation levels in vivo. p40 supplementation to neonatal and adult mice showed short-term effects on stimulating <italic toggle="yes">Setd1b</italic> gene expression in colonic tissues (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref><italic toggle="yes">A</italic>). However, neither neonatal nor adult p40 supplementation induced long-term consequences on <italic toggle="yes">Setd1b</italic> gene expression (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref><italic toggle="yes">B</italic>). Furthermore, H3K4me1 levels in colonic epithelial cells in mice were examined by double immunostaining of H3K4me1 and E-cadherin, a marker of epithelial cells. A sustained increase in H3k4me1 in colonic epithelia cells was observed in adult mice receiving p40 supplementation in the early stage, but not in adulthood (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref><italic toggle="yes">C</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">D</italic>). Thus, p40 exposure during the neonatal period transiently up-regulates <italic toggle="yes">Setd1b</italic> expression yet stably imprints H3K4 methylation in IECs that persists into adulthood.<fig id="fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>p40 supplementation in early life stimulates short-term up-regulation of <italic toggle="yes">Setd1b</italic> gene expression, but sustained increase in epigenetic marks in mice.</bold> The treatment plans for detecting the short-term (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref><italic toggle="yes">A</italic>) and long-term effects (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref><italic toggle="yes">B</italic>) are described. (<italic toggle="yes">A</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B</italic>) RNA was isolated from colonic tissues for RT-PCR analysis of <italic toggle="yes">Setd1b</italic> gene expression. Each symbol represents one mouse in <italic toggle="yes">A</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B</italic>. (<italic toggle="yes">C</italic>) Paraffin-embedded tissue sections were prepared for immunohistochemistry using anti-H3K4me1 antibody and fluorescein isothiocyanate–conjugated secondary antibody (green), an epithelial cell marker using anti–E-cadherin antibody and Cy3-conjugated secondary antibody (red), and nuclei using 4′,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI) staining (blue). Images were taken using a fluorescent microscope at 40×. (<italic toggle="yes">D</italic>) The numbers of H3K4me1 and E-cadherin double-positive cells per crypt are shown. N = 5 in each group.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr5.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0080">We further investigated more directly whether Setd1β was responsible for p40-driven production of TGFβ. A stable cell line with <italic toggle="yes">Setd1b</italic> knocked down by transducing lentiviral <italic toggle="yes">Setd1b</italic> short hairpin RNA (shRNA) into YAMC cells was generated. <italic toggle="yes">Setd1b</italic> gene expression and protein production, which were detected by reverse-transcription polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) analysis and Western blot analysis, respectively, were suppressed in cells transduced with a set of 3 lentiviral <italic toggle="yes">Setd1b</italic> shRNAs, but not in cells transduced with nontargeting shRNA (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref><italic toggle="yes">A</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B</italic>). As expected, p40 treatment increased H3K4me3 levels in YAMC cells transduced with nontarget shRNA, but not in Setd1β-deficient cells (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref><italic toggle="yes">C</italic>). Importantly, chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP)–quantitative PCR experiments showed that p40 stimulated H3K4me3 enrichments at the TGFβ promoter, and this effect was partially reversed by knockdown of <italic toggle="yes">Setd1b</italic> (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref><italic toggle="yes">D</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">E</italic>). p40 failed to stimulate TGFβ gene expression (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref><italic toggle="yes">F</italic>) and protein production (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref><italic toggle="yes">G</italic>) in cells with knockdown of <italic toggle="yes">Setd1b</italic> expression. Collectively, these data indicate that p40 stimulates durable TGFβ production by up-regulating <italic toggle="yes">Setd1b</italic> expression, which then programs a stable H3K4 methylation imprint into IECs that is targeted to the TGFβ locus.<fig id="fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><bold>Increase of <italic toggle="yes">Setd1b</italic> expression in IECs mediates p40-promoted TGFβ production.</bold> (<italic toggle="yes">A</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B</italic>) YAMC cells were transduced with lentiviral <italic toggle="yes">Setd1b</italic> shRNAs to generate a stable cell line with reduced expression of Setd1β. Nontargeting shRNA was used as a control. Knockdown efficiency of <italic toggle="yes">Setd1β</italic> was determined by assessing (<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>) mRNA expression and (<italic toggle="yes">B</italic>) protein levels using RT-PCR and Western blot analysis, respectively. The <italic toggle="yes">Setd1b</italic> mRNA expression level in the nontarget shRNA transduced cells was set as 1. (<italic toggle="yes">C</italic>) Total cellular lysates were prepared to detect p40-regulated histone methylation in the indicated cell lines. (<italic toggle="yes">D</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">E</italic>) H3K4me3 region within the <italic toggle="yes">TGFβ</italic> locus in mouse intestinal cells is shown. The enrichment of H3K4me3 in the <italic toggle="yes">Tgfb1</italic> promoter was analyzed by ChIP quantitative PCR. The percentage of relative enrichment (H3K4me3/Input) in the control group is set as 1. (<italic toggle="yes">F</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">G</italic>) Cells were treated with p40 (10 ng/mL) for the indicated times. (<italic toggle="yes">F</italic>) RNA was isolated for RT-PCR analysis of the <italic toggle="yes">Tgfb1</italic> mRNA level. The <italic toggle="yes">Tgfb1</italic> mRNA expression level in the control group with nontarget transduction was set as 1. (<italic toggle="yes">G</italic>) Supernatants from cell culture were collected for analysis of the amount of TGFβ release using enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay, as described in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>. ∗<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .05 compared with the control group in each cell line. <sup>#</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .05 compared with the p40 treatment group in nontargeting shRNA-transduced cell line. (<italic toggle="yes">B</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">C</italic>) The fold changes of band density are shown under the blot. Images shown are representative of 3 independent experiments. (<italic toggle="yes">A</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">E–G</italic>) Data are quantified from 3 independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr6.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec1.4"><title>Sustained Increase in TGFβ Production Induced by Supplementation With p40 in Early Life Contributes to Prevention of Colitis in Adulthood in Mice</title><p id="p0085">We have previously reported on the long-lasting effects of neonatal supplementation with p40 on stimulating expansion of Tregs and prevention of colitis in adulthood in mice.<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> Therefore, we examined if a sustained increase in TGFβ production induced by p40 supplementation in early life contributes to these protective effects in adult mice. To this end, adult forkhead box P (Foxp)3-green fluorescent protein (GFP) mice previously exposed to p40 in early life were treated with either neutralizing antibodies against TGFβ or matched IgG isotype negative control antibodies (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref><italic toggle="yes">A</italic>). Differentiation of Tregs was evaluated by flow cytometry analysis of populations of CD4<sup>+</sup>Foxp3<sup>+</sup> cells in the colonic lamina propria of Foxp3-GFP mice. Adult mice receiving p40 supplementation during the first 3 weeks of life showed a significant increase in the percentage of CD4<sup>+</sup>Foxp3<sup>+</sup> in total CD4<sup>+</sup> cells of the colon lamina propria, which was inhibited by treatment of adult mice with the TGFβ-neutralizing antibody, but not by the isotype control antibody (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref><italic toggle="yes">B</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">C</italic>).<fig id="fig7" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><bold>Neonatal p40 supplementation-promoted Treg expansion in the lamina propria of the colon in adult mice requires sustained increase in TGFβ production.</bold> (<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>) The treatment plan is shown. Foxp3-GFP mice were supplemented with p40 from postnatal day 2 to day 21 and received anti–TGFβ-neutralizing antibodies or isotype-negative control antibodies (IgG) at 50 μg/d at the indicated time points. Lymphocytes were isolated from the lamina propria of the colon. CD4- and Foxp3-expressing cells were assessed using flow cytometry analysis. (<italic toggle="yes">B</italic>) Representative contour plots of Foxp3 and CD4 are shown. Numbers in quarter 2 of contour plots represent the percentages of CD4<sup>+</sup>Foxp3<sup>+</sup> in total lamina propria cells. (<italic toggle="yes">C</italic>) The percentages of CD4<sup>+</sup>Foxp3<sup>+</sup> cells in total lamina propria cells are shown. N = 3 samples. Each sample contains cells from 2 to 3 mice. ∗<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .05 compared with the counterpart in the no-p40 group. <sup>#</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .05 compared with the Neo-p40 group with TGFβ antibody co-treatment. Ab, anti-TGFβ antibody.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr7.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0090">We then asked if the sustained increase in TGFβ production by neonatal p40 supplementation prevents colitis in adult mice (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Figure 8</xref><italic toggle="yes">A</italic>). Eight-week old mice were treated with 2,4,6-trinitrobenzenesulfonic acid (TNBS), which induces colitis by stimulating interleukin (IL)12-driven T-helper 1 immune responses, leads to disruption of the epithelial monolayer and increased inflammatory cell infiltration, with an increase in production of tumor necrosis factor (TNF) and interferon-γ (IFN-γ).<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref> TNBS-induced inflammation in adult mice with neonatal p40 supplementation (inflammation score, 2.0 ± 1.22) was significantly lower than the inflammation in mice without neonatal p40 supplementation (inflammation score, 4.0 ± 0.93; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .0169) (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Figure 8</xref><italic toggle="yes">B</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">C</italic>). The significantly attenuated inflammation in adult mice receiving neonatal p40 supplementation was abolished by treatment of adult mice with the neutralizing transforming growth factor-β (TGFβ) antibody (inflammation score, 4.4 ± 1.14; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .013), but not by the isotype control IgG treatment (inflammation score, 1.8 ± 1.10; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; .05) (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Figure 8</xref><italic toggle="yes">B</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">C</italic>).<fig id="fig8" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p><bold>Sustained TGFβ production by neonatal p40 supplementation mediates prevention of colitis in adult mice.</bold> (<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>) The treatment plan is shown. Mice were supplemented with p40 from postnatal day 2 to day 21 and received TGFβ-neutralizing antibodies or isotype control antibodies (IgG) at 50 μg/d, at the indicated time points. Colitis was induced by TNBS in ethanol intrarectally. Mice receiving ethanol were used as controls for TNBS treatment. Mice were killed 4 days after TNBS treatment. (<italic toggle="yes">B</italic>) Colon sections were stained with H&amp;E for assessment of inflammation. (<italic toggle="yes">C</italic>) The inflammation scores are shown. (<italic toggle="yes">D</italic>) RNA was isolated from the colonic tissues for RT-PCR analysis of the indicated cytokine mRNA expression levels. The average cytokine mRNA expression level in the control mice of the no-p40 group was set as 1, and the mRNA expression level of each mouse was compared with this average. ∗<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .05 compared with the control mice in the no-p40 group. <sup>#</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .05 compared with the p40 group with TNBS or TNBS and IgG co-treatment. (<italic toggle="yes">E</italic>) Paraffin-embedded colon tissues were used to determine ZO-1 distribution by immunohistochemistry using an anti–ZO-1 antibody and a Cy3-labeled secondary antibody (red). Nuclei were stained with 4′,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI) (blue). Slides with H&amp;E staining and immunostaining were scanned and images were exported at 10X magnification. Membrane (<italic toggle="yes">white arrowheads</italic>) and intracellular (<italic toggle="yes">yellow arrowheads</italic>) ZO-1 distributions are shown. Ab, antibody; Sac, sacrifice.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr8.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0095">Next, 2 characteristics of TNBS-induced colitis were evaluated. TNBS up-regulated levels of TNF and IFN-γ expression in the colonic mucosa were decreased significantly in mice with neonatal p40 supplementation, compared with mice without neonatal p40 supplementation (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .05) (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Figure 8</xref><italic toggle="yes">D</italic>). These effects were inhibited by the treatment of TGFβ-neutralizing antibody (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .05), but not IgG treatment (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; .05) (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Figure 8</xref><italic toggle="yes">D</italic>). A TNBS-induced colitis model also showed disruption of the intestinal epithelial integrity. The distribution of a tight junctional protein, ZO-1, was detected by immunostaining. Neonatal p40 supplementation prevented TNBS-induced redistribution of ZO-1 from apical tight junctional complexes to the cytoplasmic compartment of colon epithelial cells in adult mice with the treatment of IgG, but not TGFβ-neutralizing antibody (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Figure 8</xref><italic toggle="yes">E</italic>).</p><p id="p0100">The effects of the increase in TGFβ production by neonatal p40 supplementation on adult mice were examined further in the dextran sulfate sodium (DSS) mouse model of injury and acute colitis (<xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Figure 9</xref><italic toggle="yes">A</italic>), which is well characterized by increased intestinal epithelial injury and production of inflammatory cytokines.<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref> Consistent with the previous report,<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> adult mice receiving neonatal p40 supplementation showed lower levels of injury and acute colitis and TNF production upon DSS treatment (<xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Figure 9</xref><italic toggle="yes">B–D</italic>). Similar to TNBS colitis, these effects were inhibited by TGFβ-neutralizing antibody but not isotype IgG control treatment in adult mice (<xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Figure 9</xref><italic toggle="yes">B–D</italic>)<fig id="fig9" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p><bold>Sustained TGFβ production by neonatal p40 supplementation mediates. prevention of colitis in adult mice.</bold> (<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>) The treatment plan is shown. Mice were supplemented with p40 from postnatal day 2 to day 21 and received TGFβ-neutralizing antibodies or isotype control antibodies (IgG) at 50 g/d, at the indicated time points. Colitis was induced by 3% DSS in drinking water for 4 days. Mice receiving water were used as controls for DSS treatment. Mice were killed at the end of DSS treatment. (<italic toggle="yes">B</italic>) Colon sections were stained with H&amp;E for assessment of inflammation. Slides were scanned and images were exported at 10X magnification. (<italic toggle="yes">C</italic>) The inflammation/injury scores are shown. (<italic toggle="yes">D</italic>) RNA was isolated from the colonic tissues for RT-PCR analysis of the indicated cytokine mRNA expression levels. The average cytokine mRNA expression level in the control mice of the no-p40 group was set as 1, and the mRNA expression level of each mouse was compared with this average. ∗<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .05 compared with the control mice in the no-p40 group. <sup>#</sup><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .05 compared with the p40 group with DSS or DSS and IgG co-treatment. Ab, antibody; Sac, sacrifice.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr9.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0105">These data suggest that neonatal p40 supplementation stimulates a sustained increase in TGFβ production that supports protective immune responses and reduces intestinal inflammation in adult colitis models.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0110">Colonization by the microbiota in the neonatal gut has been recognized as an important early life event that exerts durable beneficial impact on immunity and health throughout the lifespan.<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> To advance this knowledge to clinical application, a next step forward is to elucidate the mechanisms through which the gut microbiome in early life transmits health-promoting signals and imprints them onto intestinal ecosystems in adulthood. This study showed that supplementation with probiotic-derived functional factor p40 in early life confers long-lasting effects on TGFβ production in the colon, leading to durable expansion of Tregs and prevention of colitis in adulthood. Furthermore, we identified the epigenetic effects of p40 on mouse small intestinal epithelial (MSIE) cells in vitro and the long-lasting effects on TGFβ production in the small intestine by neonatal p40 supplementation (<xref rid="fig10" ref-type="fig">Figure 10</xref>). Increasing evidence indicates a significant correlation among the epigenetic changes induced by maternal and neonatal factors, including microbiota composition in early life, and influencing health and disease susceptibility in adulthood.<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref> This work contributes to further understanding this relationship by discovering an epigenetic program modulated by p40-stimulated Setd1β function in the colonic epithelial cells, which mediates the increase in TGFβ production. Our novel finding provides a key mechanistic understanding of the capacity of factors produced by bacterial colonization of the gut in newborns for imprinting health in adults.<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref><fig id="fig10" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p><bold>p40 stimulates <italic toggle="yes">Tgfb</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Setd1b</italic> expression and histone modification in small intestinal epithelial cells in vitro and in vivo.</bold> (<italic toggle="yes">A–C</italic>) MSIE cells were treated with p40 at 10 ng/mL for the indicated times. RNA was isolated for RT-PCR analysis of the mRNA expression levels of (<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>) <italic toggle="yes">Setd1b</italic> and (<italic toggle="yes">C</italic>) <italic toggle="yes">Tgfb</italic>. The mRNA expression level in the control group was set as 1. The mRNA expression level in the treated group was compared with the control group. (<italic toggle="yes">B</italic>) Total cellular proteins were prepared from MSIE cells for Western blot analysis. β-actin blot was used as the protein loading control. The band density fold changes are shown under the bands. (<italic toggle="yes">A</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">C</italic>) Data are quantified from 3 independent experiments. (<italic toggle="yes">B</italic>) Images represent results in at least 3 independent experiments. (<italic toggle="yes">D</italic>) The treatment plan. WT mice were supplemented with p40 for testing the short-term and the long-term effects, as shown in <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>. Mice supplemented with hydrogels without p40 were used as controls. (<italic toggle="yes">E</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">F</italic>) RNA was isolated from small intestinal tissues for RT-PCR analysis of <italic toggle="yes">Tgfb1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Sedt1b</italic> gene expression. The mRNA expression level in the control groups was set as 1. The mRNA expression level in treated groups was compared with the control group. Sac, sacrifice.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr10.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0115">Numerous studies have identified evidence that there is a limited window of opportunity for inducing stable effects by the gut microbiota on imprinting the immune system. For example, the microbial colonization in the neonatal period, not in adulthood, in germ-free mice shapes the function of natural killer T cells in adulthood.<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref> Consistent with these published results, one significant finding from this study is to define the neonatal period as the time window for p40 supplementation to induce a sustained increase in TGFβ production and induction of Tregs. Previous studies have suggested that immune cells in early life could obtain memory of the microbiota influence during the development of the immune system.<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref> This study identified a novel heritable mechanism: sustained induction of Tregs is through a durable increase in TGFβ production by IECs after neonatal p40 supplementation.</p><p id="p0120">It should be noted that IECs must retain the memory of p40 regulation during cell division to extend the effects of early p40 exposure into adulthood. However, IECs are constantly shed into the lumen, undergoing essentially complete replacement every 5 days with continuous renewal from intestinal stem cells.<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr"><sup>34</sup></xref> The long-lived characteristics of intestinal stem cells makes them potential target cells in the intestine for conferring stable cellular responses. We have found that p40 up-regulates H3K4me1 in Lgr5<sup>+</sup> cells in neonatal leucine-rich repeat-containing G-protein coupled receptor (Lgr)5-<italic toggle="yes">iSuRe</italic> (IRE)s-Cre enhancer trap (ERT)2 mice (data not shown). This result supports our future studies to elucidate whether p40-regulated epigenetic reprogramming in intestinal stem cells in early life is inherited by IECs in adult mice. In addition, intestinal stem cells have been found to have different developmental programs at different development stages.<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref> The immature human intestinal epithelium has the intrinsic capability of establishing stable host–microbe symbiosis.<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr"><sup>36</sup></xref> Therefore, it is possible that in addition to Setd1β, other factors involved in developmental programs in intestinal stem cells in early life may contribute to the persistent effects of p40. Future studies will be focused on studying p40 regulation of epigenetic memory in intestinal stem cells in early life that extends into adulthood, thus programming IECs with the ability to maintain intestinal homeostasis.</p><p id="p0125">Current therapies for IBD induce sustained remission in less than half of patients; thus, new therapies are needed.<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref> TGFβ signaling has multiple roles in suppressing inflammation, such as controlling immune responses through Treg induction and inducing protective cellular responses.<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr"><sup>38</sup></xref> Clinical studies have shown that the locus encoding SMAD3, an effector of TGFβ signaling, is associated with IBD susceptibility,<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39</sup></xref> and enhancing TGFβ signaling benefits in patients with Crohn’s disease.<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr"><sup>40</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr"><sup>41</sup></xref> Therefore, any strategies that potentiate the function of TGFβ signaling could benefit IBD prevention and treatment. The identification of the effects of p40 on TGFβ production and its consequences for stimulating TGFβ signal targets in IECs and Treg expansion supports the significant clinical potential of p40 for IBD. In addition, although there is no strong evidence to support the clinical efficacy of supplementation with probiotics,<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> application of defined probiotic-derived factors, such as p40, could bypass the limitations of clinical application of probiotics, such as uncertain bioavailability and biopharmacology of probiotics in the human gastrointestinal tract. Therefore, results from this work provide a mechanistic rationale for early p40 intervention as a strategy for individuals at high risk of developing intestinal inflammation, such as IBD.</p><p id="p0130">p40 has been shown to transactivate the EGFR in IECs, which induces protective cellular responses.<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> We have now shown that p40 up-regulates <italic toggle="yes">Setd1b</italic> gene expression and H3K4me3 in IECs in the absence of EGFR expression (<xref rid="fig11" ref-type="fig">Figure 11</xref><italic toggle="yes">A</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B</italic>). Furthermore, p40 was able to stimulate transactivation of the EGFR in IECs without <italic toggle="yes">Setd1b</italic> gene expression (<xref rid="fig11" ref-type="fig">Figure 11</xref><italic toggle="yes">C</italic>). These results suggest that the epigenetic effect of p40 on TGFβ production is not associated with p40-regulated EGFR transactivation in IECs. There is evidence to support p40 regulates several signaling pathways to prevent and treat colitis. p40 ameliorated DSS-induced colitis in WT mice. This effect was diminished in <italic toggle="yes">Egfr</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">fl/fl</italic></sup>-Villin (Vil)-Cre mice with the EGFR specifically deleted in IECs.<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> However, the inhibitory effects of p40 on proinflammatory cytokine production in mice with DSS-induced colitis, such as increasing IL10 and decreasing IL6 and IL17, are similar in WT and <italic toggle="yes">Egfr</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">fl/fl</italic></sup>-Vil-Cre mice. These results suggest that p40 inhibits intestinal inflammation through at least 2 independent pathways.<fig id="fig11" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 11</label><caption><p><bold>p40-stimulated EGFR transactivation and <italic toggle="yes">Setd1b</italic> gene expression in IECs are 2 independent functions.</bold> YAMC, <italic toggle="yes">Egfr</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> mouse colonic epithelial (MCE), and YAMC transduced with lentiviral <italic toggle="yes">Setd1b</italic> shRNAs or nontargeting shRNA as used in <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref> were treated with p40 at 10 ng/mL for the indicated times. (<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>) RNA was isolated for RT-PCR analysis of the levels of <italic toggle="yes">Setd1b</italic> mRNA. The <italic toggle="yes">Setd1b</italic> mRNA expression level in the control group was set as 1. The mRNA expression levels in treated groups were compared with the control group. (<italic toggle="yes">B</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">C</italic>) Western blot analysis of cellular lysates was performed to detect levels of H3K4me3, total H3, phospho-Tyr1068-EGFR (P-EGFR), and total EGFR. β-actin blot was used as a loading control. (<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>) Data are quantified from 3 independent experiments. (<italic toggle="yes">B</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">C</italic>) Images are representative of at least 3 independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr11.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0135">In summary, studies from this work further elucidate the impact of neonatal supplementation with p40 on long-term intestinal inflammation in the adult. In addition to previously reported EGFR-dependent protection from neonatal colonization with LGG or p40 treatment,<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> here we show an EGFR-independent increase in TGFβ production in IECs, also leading to protection from colitis. These results also uncover a novel epigenetic mechanism underlying the priming of IECs by p40 to enable long-lasting effects. Notably, this knowledge should provide mechanistic insights to support early intervention with p40 as a novel strategy for maintaining intestinal health in adulthood.</p></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec3.1"><title>Purification and Encapsulation of p40</title><p id="p0140">p40 was purified from LGG (53103; American Type Culture Collection, Manassas, VA) culture supernatant and saved at -80°C, as previously reported.<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> A BCA protein assay kit (23225; Pierce Thermo Scientific, Waltham, MA) was used to examine the concentration of p40 isolates. The level of endotoxin in p40 isolates was &lt;0.03 EU/μg p40 protein examined by the Pierce LAL Chromogenic Endotoxin Quantitation Kit (88282; Pierce Thermo Scientific). p40 was encapsulated in the pectin/zein hydrogels and stored at 4°C, using methods reported previously.<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> Briefly, p40 was encapsulated at 0.5 and 1 μg of p40/hydrogel in pectin solution in water (2.0% w/v) for supplementation to mice at the early stage. For adult mice supplementation, p40 was encapsulated in hydrogel in pectin solution in water (6.0% w/v). Each hydrogel contained 5 μg of p40. All hydrogels were coated with zein solution (1.0% w/v) and CaCl<sub>2</sub> (0.5% w/v) in 75% ethanol solution. Hydrogels without p40 were prepared as negative controls.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><title>Mice and Treatment</title><p id="p0145">All animal experiments were performed according to protocols approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee at Vanderbilt University Medical Center. This study used wild-type C57BL/6J (000664; Jackson Laboratory, Bar Harbor, ME) and Balb/cJ (000651; Jackson Laboratory) mice, and Foxp3-GFP transgenic mice on a Balb/c background (006769; Jackson Laboratory). For each experiment, two 8-week-old female mice from the same litter in the same cage were mated with 1 adult male mouse and were housed until female mice were close to deliver. Mice in 1 litter were supplemented with p40-containing hydrogels. As control, mice in the other litter received hydrogels without p40. For p40 supplementation in the neonatal period, pups were supplemented with p40-containing hydrogels at 0.5 μg/d (postnatal days 2–6), 1 μg/d (postnatal days 7–13), and 1.5 μg/d (postnatal days 14–21). For p40 supplementation in adulthood, 10 μg/d of p40 was supplemented to 6-week-old mice for 3 weeks. Mice received hydrogels through oral administration. Experiments were repeated by using mice from at least 3 pairs of pregnant female mice for each treatment.</p><p id="p0150">Mice with and without neonatal p40 supplementation received a monoclonal anti–TGFβ-neutralizing antibody (MA5-23795; ThermoFisher Scientific, Waltham, MA) or IgG isotype control (02-6100; ThermoFisher Scientific) at 50 μg in 100 μL of phosphate-buffered saline for each injection. This treatment was give to mice every the other day through peritoneal cavity injection. The time lines of anti-TGFβ antibody and IgG treatment are shown in <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figures 7</xref><italic toggle="yes">A</italic> and <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref><italic toggle="yes">A</italic>.</p><p id="p0155">Colitis was induced by TNBS in Balb/c mice with and without neonatal p40 supplementation and TGFβ antibody treatment. Mice were treated with 100 μL of 70 mmol/L TNBS in 50% ethanol intrarectally. Control mice received 100 μL of 50% ethanol intrarectally. Mice were killed 4 days after TNBS treatment.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><title>Analysis of Colitis</title><p id="p0160">Paraffin-embedded colonic tissue sections were prepared for H&amp;E staining. Slides were scanned using the Leica SCN400 Slide Scanner (Leica, Wetzlar, Germany. Samples from the entire colon were examined by a pathologist blinded to treatment conditions for assessing inflammation. The scoring system used to assess TNBS-induced colitis was modified from a previous scoring system<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr"><sup>42</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr"><sup>43</sup></xref>: lamina propria mononuclear cell and polymorphonuclear cell infiltration, enterocyte loss, crypt inflammation, and epithelial hyperplasia were scored from 0 to 3, yielding an additive score between 0 (no colitis) and 15 (maximal colitis).</p></sec><sec id="sec3.4"><title>Isolation of Lymphocytes From Colonic Lamina Propria for Flow Cytometry Analysis</title><p id="p0165">Lymphocytes were isolated from lamina propria of the colon of Foxp3-GFP mice with and without neonatal p40 supplementation and TGFβ antibody treatment, as described previously.<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr"><sup>44</sup></xref> Cells were labeled with R-phycoerythrin (PE)–Cyanine (Cy)5–anti-cluster of differentiation (CD)4 (100410; BioLegend, San Diego, CA) by incubation for 0.5 hours at room temperature. Then, cells were analyzed using multicolor flow cytometry to determine the percentage of GFP (Foxp3 expression) and PE-Cy5.5 (CD4 expression) double-positive cells using a BD LSRII system (BD Biosciences, Franklin Lakes, NJ). Each sample contained lymphocytes from 3 to 4 mice with the same treatment.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.5"><title>Enteroid and Colonoid Culture</title><p id="p0170">The ileum and colonic tissues were isolated from WT C57BL/6 mice for culture of enteroids and colonoids, as described previously.<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> Enteroids and colonoids were cultured in Matrigel (Cornng, Bedford, MA) and overlaid with IntestiCult Organoid Growth Medium (06005; STEMCELL Technologies, Vancouver, Canada) in the absence or presence of p40 (100 ng/mL) in Matrigel and in medium.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.6"><title>Cell Culture, shRNA Transduction, and Treatment</title><p id="p0175">The YAMC and MSIE cell lines were generated from immortalized mice (Immortomouse) harboring thermolabile simian virus 40 (SV40) large tumor antigen (TAg) from a SV40 strain, tsA58.<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref> Cell proliferation requires the expression of SV40 TAg, which is induced by an IFN-γ-inducible H-2Kb promoter at the permissive temperature (33°C). Cells die in medium without IFN-γ at the nonpermissive temperature (37°C) for 3 passages. An EGFR knock out (EGFR<sup>-/-</sup>) mouse colonic epithelial cell line was generated from the colonic epithelium of EGFR-null mice crossed to the Immortomouse.<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr"><sup>45</sup></xref> Immortalized mouse colonocytes with floxed <italic toggle="yes">Smad4</italic> alleles (<italic toggle="yes">IMC</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">S4fl/fl</italic></sup>) were generated from <italic toggle="yes">Smad4</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">fl/fl</italic></sup> mice on the Immortomouse background. <italic toggle="yes">IMC</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">S4null</italic></sup> cells were generated by transducing <italic toggle="yes">IMC</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">S4fl/fl</italic></sup> cells with adenoviral-Cre to delete <italic toggle="yes">Smad4</italic>.<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref></p><p id="p0180">YAMC, MSIE, <italic toggle="yes">Egfr</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">-/-</italic></sup> MEC (mouse epithelial cell), <italic toggle="yes">IMC</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">S4fl/fl</italic></sup>, and <italic toggle="yes">IMC</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">S4null</italic></sup> cells were maintained in RPMI 1640 medium supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS), 5 U/mL of murine IFN-γ, 100 U/mL penicillin and streptomycin, 5 μg/mL insulin, 5 μg/mL transferrin, and 5 ng/mL selenous acid at 33°C with 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. Cells were cultured in RPMI 1640 medium containing 1% FBS and 100 U/mL penicillin and streptomycin for 18 hours at 37°C before experiments.</p><p id="p0185">To generate a stable cell line with <italic toggle="yes">Setd1b</italic> deletion, YAMC cells were stably transduced with 3 sets of lentiviral <italic toggle="yes">Setd1b</italic> shRNAs using the Dharmacon SMARTvector lentiviral shRNA kit, following the manufacturer’s instructions (Waterbeach, UK). SMARTvector nontargeting murine cytomegalovirus (mCMV)-TurboGFP shRNA was used as a control. Transduced cells were selected by puromycin for 7–10 days.</p><p id="p0190">YAMC and <italic toggle="yes">shRNA</italic>-transduced cells were treated with p40 (10 ng/mL) for Western blot analysis of activation of the TGFβ/SMAD signaling pathway. <italic toggle="yes">IMC</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">S4fl/fl</italic></sup> and <italic toggle="yes">IMC</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">S4null</italic></sup> cells were treated with H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (20 μmol/L) for 4 hours and lipopolysaccharide (1 μg/mL; Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO) for 24 hours in the presence or absence of p40 (10 ng/mL) co-treatment with 1-hour pretreatment for immunostaining of ZO-1 and examining proinflammatory cytokine production by RT-PCR, respectively.</p><p id="p0195">The human colonic adenocarcinoma cell line, Caco-2 cells (86010202; American Type Culture Collection, Manassas, VA), were grown in Dulbecco’s modified Eagle medium supplemented with 10% FBS and 100 U/mL penicillin and streptomycin at 37°C with 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. Cells were serum-starved in Dulbecco’s modified Eagle medium containing 1% FBS for 16–18 hours before experiments. For immunostaining of ZO-1, cells were treated with H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (20 μmol/L) for 4 hours in the presence or absence of 1-hour p40 (10 ng/mL) and anti–TGFβ-neutralizing antibody (1 μg/mL) pretreatment.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.7"><title>ChIP Assay</title><p id="p0200">Binding of H3K4me3 to the TGFβ promoter was examined using the SimpleCHIP Plus Enzymatic Chromatin IP Kit (Magnetic Beads) (9005; Cell Signaling), according to the manufacturer’s instruction. Briefly, cells were treated with 37% formaldehyde to cross-link protein and DNA. Nuclei were isolated and digested using micrococcal nuclease, and nuclear lysates were sonicated to fragment chromatin to 150–900 bp, which was verified by analyzing purified DNA using electrophoresis on 1% agarose gel. Digested chromatin was diluted in ChIP dilution buffer and immunoprecipitated using a rabbit anti-H3K4me3 antibody (9751; Cell Signaling) overnight at 4°C. The rabbit anti–histone 3 (4620; Cell Signaling, Danvers, MA) antibody and normal rabbit IgG (2729; Cell Signaling) were used as positive and negative controls, respectively. The immune complexes were captured by protein G magnetic beads and cross-linked protein and DNA was reversed by NaCl (5 mol/L) and proteinase K at 65°C for 2 hours. DNA was purified for quantification by quantitative PCR in triplicate using the TGFβ promoter specific primers: forward: 5’-GCACTGCGCTGTCTCGCAAGG-3’ and reverse: 5’-GGGATGCGAGGGACTCAAGAGG-3'. Results were expressed as a percentage of control. Relative enrichment was calculated as the amount of immunoprecipitated DNA by anti-H3K4me3 antibody relative to the total amount of input (H3K4me3/Input). Relative enrichment in the control group is set as 1, for comparison by data in other groups.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.8"><title>ELISA of TGFβ1 Production</title><p id="p0205">The level of TGFβ in supernatants of cultured YAMC cells was measured using the mouse TGFβ1 DuoSet ELISA development system (DY1679; R&amp;D System, Minneapolis, MN), according to the manufacturer’s instruction. Purified TGFβ was used to generate the standard concentration curve. Cell numbers were counted at the end of experiments. The TGFβ concentration was representative as of ng/10<sup>6</sup> cells.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.9"><title>RT-PCR Assay</title><p id="p0210">Total RNA was isolated from cultured cells and enteroids and colonoids, and homogenized colon tissues, using an RNA isolation kit (Qiagen, Valencia, CA) and was treated with RNase-free DNase. Reverse transcription was performed using the High Capacity cDNA Reverse Transcription kit and the 7300 RT-PCR System (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA). The data were analyzed using Sequence Detection System V1.4.0 software. Primers, <italic toggle="yes">Setd1b</italic> (Mm00616971), <italic toggle="yes">Tgfb1</italic> (Mm01178820), TNF (Mm00443259), and <italic toggle="yes">Ifng</italic> (Mm99999071) were purchased from Applied Biosystems. The relative abundance of β-actin mRNA was used to normalize levels of the mRNAs of interest. All complementary DNA samples were analyzed in triplicate.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.10"><title>Immunofluorescence Staining</title><p id="p0215">Cultured cells were fixed and permeabilized with 2% Triton X-100 in phosphate-buffered saline for 5 minutes at room temperature. Paraffin-embedded tissue sections were deparaffinized followed by antigen unmasking by boiling in sodium citrate buffer (10 mmol/L sodium citrate, 0.05% Tween 20, pH 6.0). Colonic sections and cells were blocked using 10% goat serum for 1 hour at room temperature. For ZO-1 staining, slides were incubated with a rabbit anti-mouse ZO-1 (61-7300; Invitrogen Life Technologies, Carlsbad, CA) antibody overnight at 4°C and a Cy3-labeled goat anti-rabbit IgG (111-165-003; Jackson ImmunoResearch) antibody at room temperature for 1 hour. H3K4me1 and E-cadherin double staining was performed by incubating slides with a rabbit polyclonal anti-H3K4me1 antibody (5326; Cell Signaling) overnight followed by a mouse monoclonal anti–E-cadherin antibody (610181; BD Biosciences) for 1 hour at 4°C. Then, sections were incubated sequentially with fluorescein isothiocyanate–labeled anti-rabbit (111-095-003; Jackson ImmunoResearch) for 1 hour followed by Cy3-labeled anti-mouse (115-165-003; Jackson ImmunoResearch) antibodies for 1 hour at room temperature. Sections then were mounted using Mounting Medium containing 4′,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole for nuclear counterstaining. Slides were scanned using the Apiro Versa 200 platform (Leica) or observed using a Leica DM IRB inverted microscope, and images were recorded using a Nikon DXM1200C camera (Nikon, Tokyo, Japan)</p></sec><sec id="sec3.11"><title>Western Blot Analysis</title><p id="p0220">Cell pellets were solubilized in cell lysis buffer containing 1% Triton X-100 (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO) 50 mmol/L Tris (pH 7.4), 1 mmol/L EDTA, 150 mmol/L NaCl, and a protease and phosphatase inhibitor mixture (Sigma-Aldrich) to obtain total cellular lysates. Protein concentrations of lysates were determined using a protein assay kit. The lysates were mixed with Laemmli sample buffer and equal amounts of protein were loaded for sodium dodecyl sulfate–polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis. Western blot analysis was performed using anti-total SMAD3 (9523; Cell Signaling Technology), anti–phospho-SMAD3 (9520; Cell Signaling Technology), anti–total SMAD2 (5339; Cell Signaling Technology), anti–phospho-SMAD2 (3108; Cell Signaling Technology), anti-SMAD4 (38454; Cell Signaling Technology), anti–histone 3 (Cell Signaling Technology), anti-H3K4me1 (Cell Signaling Technology), anti-H3K4me3 (Cell Signaling Technology), anti-Setd1β (44922; Cell Signaling Technology), anti-Setd1α (61702; Cell Signaling Technology), anti-MML1 (14689; Cell Signaling Technology), anti-MML2 (63735; Cell Signaling Technology), anti-WDR5 (13105; Cell Signaling Technology), anti-WDR82 (99715; Cell Signaling Technology), anti–β-actin (A2228; Sigma-Aldrich), and anti–β-tubulin (2146; Cell Signaling Technology) antibodies.</p><p id="p0225">The band density was measured using the ImageJ (National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD) processing program. The relative band density by a specific antibody was calculated by comparing it with the β-actin band from the same sample. The relative band density in the control group was set as 1. The density fold change was obtained by comparing the relative band density in the treatment group with that in the control group.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.12"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p id="p0230">Statistical significance was determined by 1-way analysis of variance for multiple comparisons and the <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> test for comparing data from 2 samples using Prism 6.0 (GraphPad Software, Inc, San Diego, CA). A <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value less than .05 was defined as statistically significant. All data are presented as means ± SEM.</p><p id="p0235">Results from in vitro studies shown in this manuscript represent data from at least 3 independent experiments. Data from all mice in this study were included in the analysis. All authors had access to the study data and have reviewed and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lilly</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stillwell</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Probiotics: growth-promoting factors produced by microorganisms</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>147</volume><year>1965</year><fpage>747</fpage><lpage>748</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14242024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.147.3659.747</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guarner</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>G.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Merenstein</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pot</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morelli</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Canani</surname><given-names>R.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flint</surname><given-names>H.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salminen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Calder</surname><given-names>P.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The International Scientific Association for Probiotics and Prebiotics consensus statement on the scope and appropriate use of the term probiotic</article-title><source>Nat Rev Gastroenterol Hepatol</source><volume>11</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>506</fpage><lpage>514</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24912386</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nrgastro.2014.66</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Versalovic</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Probiotics-host communication: modulation of signaling pathways in the intestine</article-title><source>Gut Microbes</source><volume>1</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>148</fpage><lpage>163</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20672012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4161/gmic.1.3.11712</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2909492</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vanderpool</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Polk</surname><given-names>D.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms of probiotic action: implications for therapeutic applications in inflammatory bowel diseases</article-title><source>Inflamm Bowel Dis</source><volume>14</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>1585</fpage><lpage>1596</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18623173</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/ibd.20525</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lichtenstein</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Avni-Biron</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ben-Bassat</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Probiotics and prebiotics in Crohn's disease therapies</article-title><source>Best Pract Res Clin Gastroenterol</source><volume>30</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27048899</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bpg.2016.02.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cover</surname><given-names>T.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitehead</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Washington</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Polk</surname><given-names>D.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Soluble proteins produced by probiotic bacteria regulate intestinal epithelial cell survival and growth</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><volume>132</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>562</fpage><lpage>575</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17258729</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1053/j.gastro.2006.11.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3036990</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bauerl</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abitayeva</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sosa-Carrillo</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mencher-Beltran</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Navarro-Lleo</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coll-Marques</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zuniga-Cabrera</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaikhin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perez-Martinez</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>P40 and P75 are singular functional muramidases present in the <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus casei/paracasei/rhamnosus</italic> taxon</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><volume>10</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>1420</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31297099</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fmicb.2019.01420</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6607858</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>W.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Acra</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activation of epidermal growth factor receptor mediates mucin production stimulated by p40, a <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus rhamnosus GG-</italic>derived protein</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>289</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>20234</fpage><lpage>20244</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24895124</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M114.553800</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4106339</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peek</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Acra</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Polk</surname><given-names>D.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An LGG-derived protein promotes IgA production through upregulation of APRIL expression in intestinal epithelial cells</article-title><source>Mucosal Immunol</source><volume>10</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>384</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27353252</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/mi.2016.57</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5199635</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cover</surname><given-names>T.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Washington</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaturvedi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peek</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>K.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Polk</surname><given-names>D.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Colon-specific delivery of a probiotic-derived soluble protein ameliorates intestinal inflammation in mice through an EGFR-dependent mechanism</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><volume>121</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>2242</fpage><lpage>2253</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21606592</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1172/JCI44031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3104743</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dempsey</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>Y.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raines</surname><given-names>E.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>C.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Polk</surname><given-names>D.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus rhamnosus</italic> GG-derived soluble protein, p40, stimulates ligand release from intestinal epithelial cells to transactivate epidermal growth factor receptor</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>288</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>30742</fpage><lpage>30751</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24043629</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M113.492397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3798544</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Allaire</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crowley</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Law</surname><given-names>H.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>S.Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>H.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vallance</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The intestinal epithelium: central coordinator of mucosal immunity</article-title><source>Trends Immunol</source><volume>39</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>677</fpage><lpage>696</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29716793</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.it.2018.04.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tamburini</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clemente</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The microbiome in early life: implications for health outcomes</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><volume>22</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>713</fpage><lpage>722</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27387886</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nm.4142</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jostins</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ripke</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weersma</surname><given-names>R.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duerr</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McGovern</surname><given-names>D.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hui</surname><given-names>K.Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schumm</surname><given-names>L.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Essers</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitrovic</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ning</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cleynen</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Theatre</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spain</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raychaudhuri</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goyette</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Achkar</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amininejad</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ananthakrishnan</surname><given-names>A.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baidoo</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Balschun</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bampton</surname><given-names>P.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bitton</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boucher</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brand</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buning</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cohain</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cichon</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>D'Amato</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Jong</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Devaney</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dubinsky</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ellinghaus</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>L.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Franchimont</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fransen</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gearry</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Georges</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gieger</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Glas</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haritunians</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hawkey</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hedl</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karlsen</surname><given-names>T.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kupcinskas</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kugathasan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Latiano</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laukens</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lawrance</surname><given-names>I.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lees</surname><given-names>C.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Louis</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahy</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mansfield</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mowat</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palmieri</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ponsioen</surname><given-names>C.Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Potocnik</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prescott</surname><given-names>N.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Regueiro</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rotter</surname><given-names>J.I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>R.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanderson</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sans</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Satsangi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schreiber</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simms</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sventoraityte</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Targan</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>K.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tremelling</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Verspaget</surname><given-names>H.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Vos</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wijmenga</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>D.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Winkelmann</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xavier</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeissig</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>International</surname><given-names>I.B.D.G.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silverberg</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Annese</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hakonarson</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brant</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Radford-Smith</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mathew</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rioux</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schadt</surname><given-names>E.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daly</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Franke</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parkes</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vermeire</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Host-microbe interactions have shaped the genetic architecture of inflammatory bowel disease</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>491</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>124</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23128233</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nature11582</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3491803</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Washington</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peek</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Acra</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Polk</surname><given-names>D.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neonatal colonization of mice with LGG promotes intestinal development and decreases susceptibility to colitis in adulthood</article-title><source>Mucosal Immunol</source><volume>10</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27095077</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/mi.2016.43</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5073052</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peek</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Acra</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>K.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Polk</surname><given-names>D.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Supplementation of p40, a <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus rhamnosus</italic> GG-derived protein, in early life promotes epidermal growth factor receptor-dependent intestinal development and long-term health outcomes</article-title><source>Mucosal Immunol</source><volume>11</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>1316</fpage><lpage>1328</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29875401</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41385-018-0034-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6162144</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sugi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakano</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsuda</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurihara</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hosono</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaminogawa</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epigenetic control of the host gene by commensal bacteria in large intestinal epithelial cells</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>286</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>35755</fpage><lpage>35762</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21862578</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M111.271007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3195625</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ganal</surname><given-names>S.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanos</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kallfass</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oberle</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johner</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirschning</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lienenklaus</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Staeheli</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aichele</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diefenbach</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Priming of natural killer cells by nonmucosal mononuclear phagocytes requires instructive signals from commensal microbiota</article-title><source>Immunity</source><volume>37</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>186</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22749822</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.immuni.2012.05.020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shilatifard</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The COMPASS family of histone H3K4 methylases: mechanisms of regulation in development and disease pathogenesis</article-title><source>Annu Rev Biochem</source><volume>81</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22663077</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1146/annurev-biochem-051710-134100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4010150</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanoue</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Atarashi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Honda</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development and maintenance of intestinal regulatory T cells</article-title><source>Nat Rev Immunol</source><volume>16</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>295</fpage><lpage>309</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27087661</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nri.2016.36</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitehead</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>VanEeden</surname><given-names>P.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Noble</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ataliotis</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jat</surname><given-names>P.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Establishment of conditionally immortalized epithelial cell lines from both colon and small intestine of adult H-2Kb-tsA58 transgenic mice</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>90</volume><year>1993</year><fpage>587</fpage><lpage>591</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7678459</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.90.2.587</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC45708</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Derynck</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Smad-dependent and Smad-independent pathways in TGF-beta family signalling</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>425</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>577</fpage><lpage>584</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14534577</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nature02006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>P.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Derynck</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sumoylation of Smad4, the common Smad mediator of transforming growth factor-beta family signaling</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>278</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>27853</fpage><lpage>27863</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12740389</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1074/jbc.M301755200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ten Dijke</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immunoregulation by members of the TGFbeta superfamily</article-title><source>Nat Rev Immunol</source><volume>16</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>723</fpage><lpage>740</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27885276</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nri.2016.112</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gorelik</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flavell</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transforming growth factor-beta in T-cell biology</article-title><source>Nat Rev Immunol</source><volume>2</volume><year>2002</year><fpage>46</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11905837</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nri704</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ihara</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirata</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koike</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TGF-beta in inflammatory bowel disease: a key regulator of immune cells, epithelium, and the intestinal microbiota</article-title><source>J Gastroenterol</source><volume>52</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>777</fpage><lpage>787</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28534191</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00535-017-1350-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Means</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woodbury</surname><given-names>L.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marincola-Smith</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Padmanabhan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>An</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wessinger</surname><given-names>B.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaturvedi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>T.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deane</surname><given-names>N.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coffey</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>K.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sawyers</surname><given-names>C.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldenring</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Novitskiy</surname><given-names>S.V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Washington</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beauchamp</surname><given-names>R.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epithelial Smad4 deletion up-regulates inflammation and promotes inflammation-associated cancer</article-title><source>Cell Mol Gastroenterol Hepatol</source><volume>6</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>257</fpage><lpage>276</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30109253</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jcmgh.2018.05.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6083016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Washington</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roland</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Means</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eschrich</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yeatman</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deane</surname><given-names>N.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beauchamp</surname><given-names>R.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Smad4-mediated signaling inhibits intestinal neoplasia by inhibiting expression of beta-catenin</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><volume>142</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>562</fpage><lpage>571</lpage><comment>e562</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22115830</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1053/j.gastro.2011.11.026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3343368</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillycrop</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burdge</surname><given-names>G.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epigenetic mechanisms linking early nutrition to long term health</article-title><source>Best Pract Res Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><volume>26</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>667</fpage><lpage>676</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22980048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.beem.2012.03.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Strober</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fuss</surname><given-names>I.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blumberg</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The immunology of mucosal models of inflammation</article-title><source>Annu Rev Immunol</source><volume>20</volume><year>2002</year><fpage>495</fpage><lpage>549</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11861611</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1146/annurev.immunol.20.100301.064816</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Okayasu</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hatakeyama</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohkusa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Inagaki</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakaya</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A novel method in the induction of reliable experimental acute and chronic ulcerative colitis in mice</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><volume>98</volume><year>1990</year><fpage>694</fpage><lpage>702</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1688816</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0016-5085(90)90290-h</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Olszak</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>An</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeissig</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vera</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Franke</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Glickman</surname><given-names>J.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Siebert</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baron</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kasper</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blumberg</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbial exposure during early life has persistent effects on natural killer T cell function</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>336</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>489</fpage><lpage>493</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22442383</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.1219328</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3437652</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gensollen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iyer</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kasper</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blumberg</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How colonization by microbiota in early life shapes the immune system</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>352</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>539</fpage><lpage>544</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27126036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.aad9378</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5050524</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clevers</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The intestinal crypt, a prototype stem cell compartment</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>154</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>274</fpage><lpage>284</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23870119</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cell.2013.07.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kabiri</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Greicius</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaribafzadeh</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hemmerich</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Counter</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Virshup</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Wnt signaling suppresses MAPK-driven proliferation of intestinal stem cells</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><volume>128</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>3806</fpage><lpage>3812</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30059017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1172/JCI99325</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6118584</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>D.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yadagiri</surname><given-names>V.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fields</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>Bons B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dedhia</surname><given-names>P.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>Y.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thodla</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>T.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walk</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>V.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spence</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacterial colonization stimulates a complex physiological response in the immature human intestinal epithelium</article-title><source>Elife</source><volume>6</volume><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.7554/eLife.29132</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5711377</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29110754</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colombel</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feagan</surname><given-names>B.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fedorak</surname><given-names>R.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanauer</surname><given-names>S.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kamm</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Regueiro</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rutgeerts</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sandborn</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sands</surname><given-names>B.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schreiber</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Targan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Travis</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vermeire</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>American gastroenterological association consensus development conference on the use of biologics in the treatment of inflammatory bowel disease</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><volume>133</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>312</fpage><lpage>339</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17631151</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1053/j.gastro.2007.05.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sedda</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marafini</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dinallo</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Fusco</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Monteleone</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The TGF-beta/Smad system in IBD pathogenesis</article-title><source>Inflamm Bowel Dis</source><volume>21</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>2921</fpage><lpage>2925</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26230862</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/MIB.0000000000000542</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lees</surname><given-names>C.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parkes</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Satsangi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New IBD genetics: common pathways with other diseases</article-title><source>Gut</source><volume>60</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>1739</fpage><lpage>1753</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21300624</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/gut.2009.199679</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feagan</surname><given-names>B.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sands</surname><given-names>B.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rossiter</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Usiskin</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colombel</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of Mongersen (GED-0301) on endoscopic and clinical outcomes in patients with active Crohn's disease</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><volume>154</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><comment>e66</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28847751</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1053/j.gastro.2017.08.035</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref41"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Monteleone</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumberova</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Croft</surname><given-names>N.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McKenzie</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steer</surname><given-names>H.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>T.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Blocking Smad7 restores TGF-beta1 signaling in chronic inflammatory bowel disease</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><volume>108</volume><year>2001</year><fpage>601</fpage><lpage>609</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11518734</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1172/JCI12821</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC209401</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref42"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fuss</surname><given-names>I.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marth</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neurath</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pearlstein</surname><given-names>G.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strober</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-interleukin 12 treatment regulates apoptosis of Th1 T cells in experimental colitis in mice</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><volume>117</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>1078</fpage><lpage>1088</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10535870</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0016-5085(99)70392-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref43"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neurath</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weigmann</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Finotto</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Glickman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nieuwenhuis</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iijima</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mizoguchi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mizoguchi</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mudter</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galle</surname><given-names>P.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Autschbach</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>B.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szabo</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Glimcher</surname><given-names>L.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blumberg</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The transcription factor T-bet regulates mucosal T cell activation in experimental colitis and Crohn's disease</article-title><source>J Exp Med</source><volume>195</volume><year>2002</year><fpage>1129</fpage><lpage>1143</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11994418</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1084/jem.20011956</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2193714</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref44"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Kaer</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Washington</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dube</surname><given-names>P.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>K.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Polk</surname><given-names>D.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activation of the epidermal growth factor receptor in macrophages regulates cytokine production and experimental colitis</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><volume>192</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>1013</fpage><lpage>1023</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24391216</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4049/jimmunol.1300133</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4006992</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref45"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dise</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frey</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitehead</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Polk</surname><given-names>D.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidermal growth factor stimulates Rac activation through Src and phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase to promote colonic epithelial cell migration</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Gastrointest Liver Physiol</source><volume>294</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>G276</fpage><lpage>G285</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17991704</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1152/ajpgi.00340.2007</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ack id="ack0010"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p id="p0280">The authors thank Mrs Liping Liu for technical help and the Digital Histology Shared Resource at Vanderbilt University Medical Center (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mc.vanderbilt.edu/dhsr" id="intref0010">www.mc.vanderbilt.edu/dhsr</ext-link>) for whole slide imaging.</p><sec id="sec4"><title>CRediT Authorship Contributions</title><p id="p0240">Yilin Deng (Conceptualization: Lead; Data curation: Lead; Formal analysis: Lead; Investigation: Equal; Methodology: Equal; Writing – original draft: Equal; Writing – review &amp; editing: Equal)</p><p id="p0245">Oliver G Mcdonald, MD, PhD (Conceptualization: Equal; Formal analysis: Equal; Investigation: Equal; Methodology: Equal; Validation: Equal; Writing – review &amp; editing: Equal)</p><p id="p0250">Anna Means (Conceptualization: Equal; Data curation: Supporting; Formal analysis: Supporting; Investigation: Supporting; Methodology: Supporting; Writing – review &amp; editing: Equal)</p><p id="p0255">Richard M Peek Jr, MD (Conceptualization: Supporting; Formal analysis: Supporting; Funding acquisition: Supporting; Investigation: Supporting; Methodology: Supporting; Project administration: Supporting; Resources: Supporting; Validation: Equal; Writing – original draft: Supporting; Writing – review &amp; editing: Supporting)</p><p id="p0260">M. Kay Washington, MD, PhD (Data curation: Supporting; Formal analysis: Supporting; Investigation: Supporting; Methodology: Supporting; Writing – review &amp; editing: Supporting)</p><p id="p0265">Sari A Acra, MD (Conceptualization: Supporting; Formal analysis: Supporting; Funding acquisition: Supporting; Project administration: Supporting; Resources: Supporting; Validation: Supporting; Writing – original draft: Supporting; Writing – review &amp; editing: Supporting)</p><p id="p0270">D. Brent Polk, MD (Conceptualization: Equal; Formal analysis: Supporting; Funding acquisition: Supporting; Investigation: Equal; Methodology: Equal; Project administration: Supporting; Resources: Supporting; Validation: Equal; Writing – original draft: Equal; Writing – review &amp; editing: Equal)</p><p id="p0275">Fang Yan, MD, PhD (Conceptualization: Lead; Data curation: Supporting; Formal analysis: Lead; Funding acquisition: Lead; Investigation: Equal; Methodology: Lead; Project administration: Lead; Resources: Equal; Supervision: Lead; Validation: Lead; Writing – original draft: Lead; Writing – review &amp; editing: Lead)</p></sec></ack><fn-group><fn id="d34e616"><p id="ntpara0010"><bold>Conflicts of interest</bold> The authors disclose no conflicts.</p></fn><fn id="d34e621"><p id="ntpara0015"><bold>Funding</bold> This work was supported by <funding-source id="gs1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100000002</institution-id><institution>National Institutes of Health</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> grants R01DK081134 (F.Y.), R01DK56008, R01DK54993 (D.B.P.), and R01DK58587, R01CA77955, and P01CA116087 (R.M.P.); the <funding-source id="gs2"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100011684</institution-id><institution>Crohn's and Colitis Foundation</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> Senior Research Award (F.Y. and D.B.P.); and core services performed through Vanderbilt University Medical Center's Digestive Disease Research Center, which was supported by <funding-source id="gs3"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100000002</institution-id><institution>National Institutes of Health</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> grant P30DK058404.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article></pmc-articleset>