<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Rev Assoc Med Bras (1992)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Rev Assoc Med Bras (1992)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">4296</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">ramb</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ramb</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Revista da Associação Médica Brasileira</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0104-4230</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1806-9282</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Associação Médica Brasileira</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10890203</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10890203.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10890203</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10890203</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38422245</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/1806-9282.20230636</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">00621</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Analysis of <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium animalis</italic> subsp. <italic toggle="yes">lactis</italic> BB-12 <sup>®</sup> and <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus rhamnosus</italic> GG on underweight and malabsorption in premature infants</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3287-0954</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Xing</surname><given-names initials="M">Meng</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/">Conceptualization</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/">Data curation</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/formal-analysis/">Formal Analysis</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/">Investigation</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/">Methodology</role><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/resources/">Resources</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/software/">Software</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/validation/">Validation</role><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/visualization/">Visualization</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/">Writing - original draft</role></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9199-0489</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="X">Xuran</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/">Data curation</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/formal-analysis/">Formal Analysis</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/">Investigation</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/">Methodology</role><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/resources/">Resources</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/software/">Software</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/validation/">Validation</role><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/visualization/">Visualization</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/">Writing - original draft</role></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0414-9796</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yinzhu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/">Conceptualization</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/">Data curation</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/formal-analysis/">Formal Analysis</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/">Investigation</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/">Methodology</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/project-administration/">Project administration</role><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/resources/">Resources</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/software/">Software</role><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/supervision/">Supervision</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/">Writing - review &amp; editing</role></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>Beijing United Family Hospital, Department of Pediatrics - Beijing, China.</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>Beijing United Family Jingbei Women and Children’s Hospital, Department of Pediatrics - Beijing, China.</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1">
<label>*</label>Corresponding author: <email>zhangyinzhu@yeah.net</email>
</corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="fn1"><p><bold>Conflicts of interest:</bold> the authors declare there is no conflicts of interest</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>23</day><month>2</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>70</volume><issue>2</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">452644</issue-id><elocation-id>e20230636</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>06</day><month>9</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>9</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>23</day><month>02</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>23</day><month>02</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2026-02-04 20:25:13.707"><day>04</day><month>02</month><year>2026</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="1806-9282-ramb-70-02-e20230636.pdf"/><abstract><title>SUMMARY</title><sec><title>OBJECTIVE:</title><p> This study aimed to explore and analyze the therapeutic effect of the combination of <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium animalis</italic> subsp. <italic toggle="yes">lactis</italic> BB-12<sup>®</sup> and <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus rhamnosus</italic> GG on underweight and malabsorption in premature infants.</p></sec><sec><title>METHODS:</title><p> This is a retrospective study. The clinical data of 68 premature infants admitted to Beijing United Family Hospital (Private Secondary Comprehensive Hospital, Chaoyang District, Beijing, China) from January 2016 to January 2022 were analyzed retrospectively. Preterm infants less than 37 weeks of gestational age admitted to the neonatal intensive care unit were included in the study. Patients with intestinal malformations, necrotizing enterocolitis, etc., who require long-term fasting were excluded. A telephone follow-up was performed 3-6 months after discharge. They were classified as treatment groups A and B according to the treatment plan. The treatment group A included parenteral nutrition, enteral nutrition, etc. In treatment group B, based on treatment group A, the premature infants were treated with <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium animalis</italic> subsp. <italic toggle="yes">lactis</italic> BB-12<sup>®</sup> and <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus rhamnosus</italic> GG. The time to regain birthweight and the weight on day 30 were compared between the two groups, as was the duration of transition from parenteral nutrition to total enteral nutrition.</p></sec><sec><title>RESULTS:</title><p> The time of weight regain birthweight in group B was shorter than that in group A (t=-2.560; t=-4.287; p&lt;0.05). The increase of weight on day 30 in group B was significantly higher than that in group A (t=2.591; t=2.651; p&lt;0.05). The time from parenteral nutrition to total enteral nutrition in group B was shorter than that in group A (z=-2.145; z=-2.236; p&lt;0.05).</p></sec><sec><title>CONCLUSION:</title><p> In the treatment of premature infants, the combination of <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium animalis</italic> subsp. <italic toggle="yes">lactis</italic> BB-12<sup>®</sup> and <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus rhamnosus</italic> GG can have a better therapeutic effect on the underweight and malabsorption of premature infants, and this treatment method can be popularized in clinics.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><title>KEYWORDS:</title><kwd>Bifidobacterium</kwd><kwd>Lactobacillus rhamnosus</kwd><kwd>Preterm</kwd><kwd>Infants</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="1"/><table-count count="3"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="24"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Premature infants, born at less than 37 weeks of gestation, have underdeveloped immune systems and face challenges in gastrointestinal feeding due to slow gastrointestinal tract development. Additionally, related diseases and antibiotic treatment can further delay the establishment of healthy intestinal flora. This negatively impacts nutrient absorption and immune system development, potentially leading to complications like necrotizing enterocolitis (NEC). Probiotics have shown promise in improving feeding tolerance, reducing inflammation, altering intestinal flora, and influencing metabolic mechanisms<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>. However, the mechanism of action, efficacy, and safety of probiotic treatment in premature infants are still under investigation<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>.</p><p>Intestinal microflora, an essential component of the intestinal system, plays a crucial role in the intestinal barrier, digestion and absorption, nutrient metabolism, and immune function<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>. Oral probiotics have been found to enhance gastrointestinal function and lower the incidence of NEC and sepsis in premature infants<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref>. Nevertheless, the exact mechanisms of action, effectiveness, and safety of probiotic treatment remain uncertain, and there is a lack of clinical studies focusing on premature infants. <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium animalis</italic> subsp. <italic toggle="yes">lactis</italic> BB-12<sup>®</sup> is involved in host digestion, nutrition, metabolism, absorption, immunity, and anti-infection processes. It helps prevent the invasion of pathogenic bacteria or viruses in the intestinal mucosa, promotes intestinal cell maturation, and facilitates newborn development. <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus rhamnosus</italic> GG, a commonly used probiotic, exhibits tolerance to bile and gastric acid, reduces NEC, and improves outcomes in premature infants<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref>. However, its impact on intestinal flora and immunity in premature infants is not well understood. In this study, we aimed to investigate the therapeutic efficacy of a combination of <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium animalis</italic> subsp. <italic toggle="yes">lactis</italic> BB-12<sup>®</sup> and <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus rhamnosus</italic> GG in the treatment of underweight and malabsorption in premature infants. The detailed findings are provided below.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>METHODS</title><sec><title>Subjects</title><p>This is a retrospective study. Participants in the study were 68 preterm infants with gestational age less than 37 weeks admitted to Beijing United Family Hospital (Private Secondary Comprehensive Hospital, Chaoyang District, Beijing, China) between January 2016 and January 2022. Preterm infants less than 37 weeks of gestational age admitted to the neonatal intensive care unit (NICU) were included in the study. The patients were classified as treatment groups A and B according to different treatment methods. Exclusion criteria were as follows: severe asphyxia and infection at birth, congenital malformation of the digestive tract, congenital immunodeficiency, and various inherited metabolic diseases; inability to tolerate gastrointestinal administration; giving up treatment during hospitalization for various reasons; poor compliance, not having follow-up time; use of antibiotics during the study; after discharge without permission stop taking or take other probiotics; and could not complete the study for various reasons. Due to the small NICU scale in our hospital, no patients requiring long-term fasting such as intestinal malformations and NEC, and the one-to-one nursing between nurses and patients in our hospital, nosocomial infections rarely occur, so no patients have been excluded. The specific process is shown in <xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>.</p><p>
<fig position="float" id="f1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><title>Flow chart.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="1806-9282-ramb-70-02-e20230636-gf1.jpg"/></fig>
</p><p>This study was approved by the Ethics Committee of our hospital (2023-03-006-k06) and obtained the written informed consent of all patients’ legal guardians.</p></sec><sec><title>Data collection</title><p>Preterm infants were classified according to gestational age: (1) very preterm infants: preterm infants with gestational age less than 28 weeks; (2) very preterm infants: preterm infants with a gestational age of 28-32 weeks; and (3) premature infants: premature infants with a gestational age of 32-37 weeks. Preterm infants with a gestational age of less than 28 weeks are more immature than preterm infants of other gestational ages. Feeding intolerance (FI) and even NEC are more likely to occur during the feeding process. Before the implementation of enteral nutrition for premature infants, it is necessary to comprehensively evaluate their general condition (gestational age and birth weight: normal range is determined based on gestational age; heart rate: 120-160 beats per minute; respiratory rate: 30-60 breaths per minute; body temperature: 36.5-37.5°C; whether there are obvious breathing difficulties, cardiovascular problems, etc.), physical examination (skin condition, whether jaundice, skin lesions, etc., abdominal distension, tenderness, etc.), laboratory monitoring (hemoglobin level: between 13 and 20 g/dL; white blood cell count: 5,000-15,000/µL; blood sodium level: 135-145 mmol/L; blood potassium level: 3.5-5.0 mmol/L; blood calcium level: 8.5-10.5 mg/dL; blood phosphorus level: 2.5-4.5 mg/dL; indicators of liver and kidney function; inflammatory markers such as C-reactive proteins and cytokines), imaging examination (chest X-ray: lung condition and whether there are any pulmonary issues based on the imaging results), medical history complications (whether preterm infants have other underlying health problems, such as heart disease and neurological problems, whether there are complications such as infection, intestinal necrosis, and intestinal obstruction), and pipeline placement (insertion of an enteral nutrition tube: checking whether the cannula is correctly placed without displacement or air leakage), and whether there are serious contraindications according to the evaluation results should be observed. If so, it is necessary to suspend or stop the enteral nutrition treatment plan<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>Grouping and treatment methods</title><p>In group A, premature infants with gestational age less than 28 weeks or weight less than 2 kg were put into the neonatal incubator in time, and the other premature infants were put into the neonatal radiation heater for close observation<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>9</sup>
</xref>. For preterm infants without contraindications to enteral feeding, feeding was performed within 12-48 h, with intermittent feeding every 2-3 h. Depending on the condition of premature infants, enteral feeding was increased gradually, combined with the infant’s tolerance, if the daily intake of calories should be insufficient by parenteral nutrition. Premature infants need to be given adequate energy supply after birth, through enteral nutrition, parenteral nutrition, or enteral and parenteral combined energy support, from the first day of 50 kcal/kg/day to the third day of 80 kcal/kg/day, gradually increasing to 110-150 kcal/kg/day energy intake<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>10</sup>
</xref>.</p><p>Based on group A, group B was treated with Nemans, 1 g, once a day. For premature infants without feeding contraindications, Nemans was mixed with breast milk or milk powder to feed premature infants once a day. For newborns using antibiotics, the interval with antibiotics is more than 2 h before feeding.</p><p>The manufacturer of Nemans is PharmTech (HongKong) Ltd. It is produced in Hong Kong, China, and is sold normally in mainland China. The main ingredients are <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium animalis</italic> BB-12 and <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus rhamnosus</italic> LGG. The product is packaged in 1 g/bag, and each bag (1 g) contains at least 4.5 billion viable probiotics.</p></sec><sec><title>Observation indicators</title><p>The observational indexes in this study were the time when the weight returned to the birth weight, the weight on day 30, and the duration from parenteral nutrition to total enteral nutrition. The time when the weight returned to the birth weight is defined as the period it takes for the infant’s weight to reach the same weight as at the time of birth. The weight on day 30 is defined as the infant’s weight on the 30th day after birth. The duration from parenteral nutrition to total enteral nutrition is defined as the length of time it takes for the infant’s nutrition to transition from being received intravenously to being fully obtained through the digestive tract.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical methods</title><p>The SPSS 26.0 software was used to analyze the data. Comparisons between two groups with continuous data conforming to the homogeneity of variance of normal distribution were performed using a parametric test (independent-samples t-test), presented as mean±standard deviation, and comparisons between two groups with non-normal distribution data were performed using a Mann-Whitney U test - median and quartile [m (QR)] were used, and categorical data were counted using the chi-square test and frequency (rate). A two-sided test showed a significant difference (p&lt;0.05).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>General data analysis</title><p>A total of 66 patients (33 in each group) were enrolled in this study. In group A, the ratio of males to females was 21:12, the average gestational age was 31.77 weeks, and the average birth weight was 1671.36 g. In group B, the ratio of males to females was 17:16, the average gestational age was 32.85 weeks, and the average birth weight was 1831.06 g. There were no significant differences in sex, gestational age, birth weight, or mode of delivery between the two groups (p&gt;0.05), as shown in <xref rid="t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p><p>
<table-wrap position="float" id="t1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title>General data analysis (case).</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indicators</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group A (n=33)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group B (n=33)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">t/X<sup>2</sup> value</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.992</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.319</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (63.6%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (51.5%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (36.4%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (48.5%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weeks of gestation</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.77</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.85</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.455</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.151</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight (g)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1671.36</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1831.06</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.271</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.208</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TFN1"><p>The treatment group A included parenteral nutrition, enteral nutrition, etc., treatment group B based on treatment group A, the premature infants were treated with <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium animalis</italic> subsp. <italic toggle="yes">lactis</italic> BB-12<sup>®</sup> and <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus rhamnosus</italic> GG.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec><title>Comparative analysis of each index in different gestational age</title><p>This study compared the two groups of premature infants over 28 weeks of each index analysis. The time to return to birth weight in group B was significantly shorter than that in group A (t=-2.560, p=0.013), and the difference in weight on day 30 in group B was significantly higher than that in group A (t=2.591, p=0.012). The duration of conversion from parenteral nutrition to total enteral nutrition in group B was significantly shorter than that in group A (z=-2.145, p=0.032), as shown in <xref rid="t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>.</p><p>
<table-wrap position="float" id="t2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><title>Comparison and analysis of the indexes of premature infants above 28 weeks.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indicators</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group A (n=30)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group B (n=30)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">t/z value</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time required to return to birth weight (days)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.79</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.93</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.560</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of conversion from parenteral nutrition to total enteral nutrition (days)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.50</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.145</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight difference (g)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">696.96</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">895.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.591</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TFN2"><p>The treatment group A included parenteral nutrition, enteral nutrition, etc., treatment group B based on treatment group A, the premature infants were treated with <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium animalis</italic> subsp. <italic toggle="yes">lactis</italic> BB-12<sup>®</sup> and <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus rhamnosus</italic> GG.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p>In addition, this study compared the two groups of premature infants under 28 weeks of gestational age for each index analysis. The time to return to birth weight in group B was significantly shorter than that in group A (t=-4.287, p=0.005), and the difference of birth weight in group B was significantly higher than that in group A (t=2.651, p=0.038). The duration of conversion from parenteral nutrition to total enteral nutrition in group B was significantly shorter than that in group A (z=-2.236, p=0.036), as shown in <xref rid="t3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>.</p><p>
<table-wrap position="float" id="t3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><title>Comparison and analysis of the indexes of premature infants below week 28.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="2"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Indicators</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Whether or not to add probiotics</th><th align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">t/z-value</th><th align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">p-value</th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes (3 cases)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No (3 cases)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time required to return to birth weight (days)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.80</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-4.287</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of conversion from parenteral nutrition to total parenteral nutrition (days)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2.236</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.036</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight difference (g)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">728.33</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">443.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.651</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.038</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TFN3"><p>The treatment group A included parenteral nutrition, enteral nutrition, etc., treatment group B based on treatment group A, the premature infants were treated with <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium animalis</italic> subsp. <italic toggle="yes">lactis</italic> BB-12<sup>®</sup> and <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus rhamnosus</italic> GG.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>In this study, we examined the effect of supplementation with <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus rhamnosus</italic> GG and <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium animalis</italic> subsp. <italic toggle="yes">lactis</italic> BB-12<sup>®</sup> on the return of premature weight to birth weight and the weight on day 30, and the effect of the duration of conversion from parenteral nutrition to total parenteral nutrition.</p><p>More than 10,000 premature infants worldwide have been randomized controlled trials for probiotics, suggesting that probiotics can generally reduce NEC, sepsis, and mortality<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>11</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>12</sup>
</xref>. However, the answers to clinical questions about which strain to use, the dose, and the timing of supplementation are not clear<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>13</sup>
</xref>. On the contrary, a growing number of commercial products containing probiotics are sometimes of poor quality<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>14</sup>
</xref>.</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium</italic> is a common component of the inherent microbiota in the human gut. <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium animalis</italic> subsp<italic toggle="yes">. lactis</italic> BB-12<sup>®</sup> (BB-12<sup>®</sup>), which is the world’s most documented probiotic <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium</italic>, originates from Chr. Hansen’s collection of dairy cultures, has high stability in foods, and is available as freeze-dried powders. Studies have shown that BB-12 supplementation in preterm infants can effectively promote the proliferation of bifidobacteria in the intestine and inhibit the harmful bacteria <italic toggle="yes">Enterobacter</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium</italic>, thus effectively promoting the balance of intestinal flora<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>15</sup>
</xref>. BB-12 has a great effect on human health; it can regulate intestinal flora, improve immune function, reduce infection, and improve resistance, so it is often used in infant formula milk powder, food additives, and yogurt<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>16</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>17</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>18</sup>
</xref>. Studies have shown that BB-12 has significant clinical efficacy against FI in neonates and diarrhea in infants<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>19</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>20</sup>
</xref>. The survival of BB-12 in the gastrointestinal tract has been demonstrated, and BB-2 has been shown to support a healthy gastrointestinal microbiota<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>21</sup>
</xref>. In addition, BB-12 has been shown to improve intestinal function, protect against diarrhea, and reduce the side effects of antibiotic therapy. In terms of immune function, clinical studies have shown that BB-12 enhances the body’s resistance to common respiratory infections and reduces the incidence of acute respiratory infections<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>22</sup>
</xref>.</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">In vivo</italic> studies show that LGG has good adhesion and colonization ability in the human gastrointestinal tract<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>23</sup>
</xref>. The possible mechanisms involved in its protective effects on the gastrointestinal tract include enhancement of intestinal barrier function and adhesion to the intestinal mucosa, inhibition of pathogen adhesion, competitive rejection of pathogenic microorganisms, production of antibiotic-like substances, and regulation of the body’s immunity and system. NEC is the most common severe acquired disease in premature infants, characterized by intestinal wall necrosis of different lengths and depths. Intestinal perforation occurs in one-third of affected infants<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>. The European Society of Pediatric Gastroenterology, Liver Disease and Nutrition (ESPGHAN) probiotics, Prebiotics and Nutrition Committee Working Group published a systematic review and network meta-analysis of the randomized controlled trials in 2018. The report analyzed data on the use of probiotics in preterm infants, outcomes regarding mortality, NEC, delayed sepsis (LOS), or time to complete enteral feeding. There were 51 randomized controlled trials, including 11,231 premature births. Seven treatments reduced the incidence of NEC, two treatments reduced the incidence of NEC and LOS, and three treatments reduced the time to complete enteral feeding. LGG was used in seven trials<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>24</sup>
</xref>.</p><p>Due to the low number of premature infants under 28 weeks (six cases), in future studies we will include more premature infants. The small sample size and the geographical limitations of the subjects will cause some bias in the conclusion of this study. In addition, when we analyzed the NICU data in our hospital, we found that there were two cases of neonatal sepsis in these two groups; the incidence was lower than that reported in the previous literature, and the infection rate is low. We will do further analysis to include more samples.</p><p>In conclusion, the treatment of premature infants with the combination of <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium animalis</italic> subsp<italic toggle="yes">. lactis</italic> BB-12<sup>®</sup> and <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus rhamnosus</italic> GG can obtain a better therapeutic effect on underweight and malabsorption. This study provides a new idea for the clinical treatment and nursing of premature infants, as well as the relevant database.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn2"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> none</p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="data-availability" specific-use="data-available-upon-request"><title>AVAILABILITY OF DATA AND MATERIALS</title><p>The datasets used or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></sec><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pammi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cope</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tarr</surname><given-names>PI</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Warner</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Morrow</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mai</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Intestinal dysbiosis in preterm infants preceding necrotizing enterocolitis: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Microbiome</source><year>2017</year><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40168-017-0248-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28274256</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5343300</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mitha</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kruth</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bjurman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rakow</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Neonatal Morbidities and Feeding Tolerance Outcomes in Very Preterm Infants, before and after Introduction of Probiotic Supplementation</article-title><source>Nutrients</source><year>2022</year><volume>14</volume><issue>17</issue><fpage>3646</fpage><lpage>3646</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nu14173646</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36079903</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9460632</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Halloran</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Underwood</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Probiotic mechanisms of action</article-title><source>Early Hum Dev</source><year>2019</year><volume>135</volume><fpage>58</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.earlhumdev.2019.05.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31174927</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hickey</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Donath</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Opie</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Garland</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Probiotics, prematurity and neurodevelopment: follow-up of a randomised trial</article-title><source>BMJ Paediatr Open</source><year>2017</year><volume>1</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>e000176</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjpo-2017-000176</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5862156</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29637171</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tobin</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Opie</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Donath</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tabrizi</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pirotta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Probiotic effects on late-onset sepsis in very preterm infants: a randomized controlled trial</article-title><source>Pediatrics</source><year>2013</year><volume>132</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1055</fpage><lpage>1062</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2013-1339</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24249817</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Athalye-Jape</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Deshpande</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Simmer</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Patole</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Probiotic supplementation and late-onset sepsis in preterm infants: a meta-analysis</article-title><source>Pediatrics</source><year>2016</year><volume>137</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>e20153684</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2015-3684</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26908700</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Reduction in necrotizing enterocolitis and improved outcomes in preterm infants following routine supplementation with Lactobacillus GG in combination with bovine lactoferrin</article-title><source>J Neonatal Perinatal Med</source><year>2017</year><volume>10</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>255</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3233/NPM-16130</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28854514</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>SQ</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Interpretation of China guidelines for clinical application of neonatal nutrition support (2013 update)</article-title><source>J Clin Pediatr</source><year>2014</year><volume>32</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>801</fpage><lpage>803</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>DQ</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Management guidelines for preterm infants</article-title><source>Chin J Pediatr</source><year>2006</year><issue>3</issue><fpage>188</fpage><lpage>191</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hay</surname><given-names>WW</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hei</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Nutrition optimization of premature infants [J/OL]</article-title><source>China J Contemp Pediatr</source><year>2017</year><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>21</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rolnitsky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Asztalos</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Karol</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Findlater</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>A quality improvement intervention to reduce necrotizing enterocolitis in premature infants with probiotic supplementation</article-title><source>Pediatr Qual Saf</source><year>2019</year><volume>4</volume><issue>5</issue><elocation-id>e201</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/pq9.0000000000000201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31745505</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6805101</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Samuels</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Graaf</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Been</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jonge</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hanff</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wijnen</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Necrotising enterocolitis and mortality in preterm infants after introduction of probiotics: a quasi-experimental study</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>31643</fpage><lpage>31643</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep31643</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27545195</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4992873</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Athalye-Jape</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Patole</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Probiotics for preterm infants - time to end all controversies</article-title><source>Microb Biotechnol</source><year>2019</year><volume>12</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>253</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1751-7915.13357</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30637944</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6389843</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Akker</surname><given-names>CHP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Goudoever</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shamir</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Domellöf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Embleton</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hojsak</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Probiotics and preterm infants: a position paper by the European society for paediatric gastroenterology hepatology and nutrition committee on nutrition and the European society for paediatric gastroenterology hepatology and nutrition working group for probiotics and prebiotics</article-title><source>J Pediatr Gastroenterol Nutr</source><year>2020</year><volume>70</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>664</fpage><lpage>680</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MPG.0000000000002655</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32332478</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mohan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Koebnick</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schildt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Possner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Effects of Bifidobacterium lactis Bb12 supplementation on intestinal microbiota of preterm infants: a double-blind, placebo-controlled, randomized study</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>44</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>4025</fpage><lpage>4031</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.00767-06</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16971641</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1698302</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>LQ</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Research progress of Bifidobacterium BB-12 and its immunomodulatory function</article-title><source>Shanghai Preventive Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>32</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>600</fpage><lpage>605</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Nocerino</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Filippis</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cecere</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Marino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Micillo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Scala</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>The therapeutic efficacy of Bifidobacterium animalis subsp. lactis BB-12® in infant colic: a randomised, double blind, placebo-controlled trial</article-title><source>Aliment Pharmacol Ther</source><year>2020</year><volume>51</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>110</fpage><lpage>120</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/apt.15561</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31797399</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6973258</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Verruck</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Barretta</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Miotto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Canella</surname><given-names>MHM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liz</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Maran</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the interaction between microencapsulated Bifidobacterium BB-12 added in goat’s milk Frozen Yogurt and Escherichia coli in the large intestine</article-title><source>Food Res Int</source><year>2020</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>108690</fpage><lpage>108690</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2019.108690</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31882106</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sui</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Therapeutic effect of Bifidobacterium BB-12 on neonatal feeding intolerance</article-title><source>Modern Chinese Doctor</source><year>2018</year><volume>56</volume><issue>31</issue><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>46</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZX</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>TX</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>A controlled study of Bifidobacterium BB-12 in the treatment of infantile diarrhea</article-title><source>Chinese J Pract Pediatr</source><year>2017</year><volume>32</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>539</fpage><lpage>542</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Plummer</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bulach</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Tabrizi</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Garland</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Gut microbiota of preterm infants supplemented with probiotics: sub-study of the ProPrems trial</article-title><source>BMC Microbiol</source><year>2018</year><volume>18</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>184</fpage><lpage>184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12866-018-1326-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30424728</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6234596</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jungersen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Wind</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Johansen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Stuer-Lauridsen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Eskesen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The science behind the probiotic strain Bifidobacterium animalis subsp. lactis BB-12(®)</article-title><source>Microorganisms</source><year>2014</year><volume>2</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>92</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/microorganisms2020092</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27682233</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5029483</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pagnini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Corleto</surname><given-names>VD</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Martorelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lanini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>D’Ambra</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Giulio</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Mucosal adhesion and anti-inflammatory effects of Lactobacillus rhamnosus GG in the human colonic mucosa: a proof-of-concept study</article-title><source>World J Gastroenterol</source><year>2018</year><volume>24</volume><issue>41</issue><fpage>4652</fpage><lpage>4662</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3748/wjg.v24.i41.4652</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30416313</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6224475</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Akker</surname><given-names>CHP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Goudoever</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Szajewska</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Embleton</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hojsak</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><article-title>Probiotics for preterm infants: a strain-specific systematic review and network meta-analysis</article-title><source>J Pediatr Gastroenterol Nutr</source><year>2018</year><volume>67</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>122</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MPG.0000000000001897</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29384838</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>