<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Neuroinflammation</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Neuroinflammation</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">249</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jneuro</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Neuroinflammation</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1742-2094</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12607168</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12607168.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12607168</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12607168</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41219746</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12974-025-03590-5</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3590</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic>-derived cytolysin exacerbates ischemic stroke by disrupting the blood–brain barrier via NLRP3 activation</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names initials="JN">Jia-ni</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names initials="WH">Wei-hao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names initials="YS">Yi-si</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names initials="JX">Jia-xue</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="YL">Yan-lei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="J">Jia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names initials="M">Meng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names initials="CL">Cheng-long</given-names></name><address><email>xiechenglong1987@126.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names initials="RT">Ruo-ting</given-names></name><address><email>331523317@qq.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03cyvdv85</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.414906.e</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1808 0918</institution-id><institution>Department of Neurology, </institution><institution>The First Affiliated Hospital of Wenzhou Medical University, </institution></institution-wrap>Wenzhou, Zhejiang Province China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/011b9vp56</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.452885.6</institution-id><institution>Department of Neurology, </institution><institution>The Third Affiliated Hospital of Wenzhou Medical University, </institution></institution-wrap>Wenzhou, Zhejiang Province China </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/00rd5t069</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.268099.c</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0348 3990</institution-id><institution>The First School of Clinical Medicine, </institution><institution>Wenzhou Medical University, </institution></institution-wrap>Wenzhou, Zhejiang Province China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>22</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">478515</issue-id><elocation-id>266</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>7</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>11</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>13</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-11-14 10:25:13.187"><day>14</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="12974_2025_Article_3590.pdf"/><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Ischemic stroke remains a major global health burden. <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic>, which is enriched in the gut of stroke patients, produces cytolysin—a pore-forming toxin that disrupts cell membranes. Gut barrier damage may allow such toxins to enter circulation and impair the blood–brain barrier (BBB). In this study, cytolysin-induced BBB disruption via NLRP3 inflammasome activation was investigated with the aim of identifying new therapeutic targets for stroke.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">Ischemic stroke patients were enrolled within 48 h of onset at the First Affiliated Hospital of Wenzhou Medical University. Rectal swabs were collected for 16 S rRNA sequencing and analyzed via QIIME. To investigate the effects of cytolysin-positive <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> on BBB integrity and NLRP3 activation, a photothrombotic stroke model in C57BL/6J mice and in vitro studies with bEnd.3 cells were performed. Cerebral blood flow, BBB permeability, and intestinal barrier function were assessed using established physiological and molecular assays. NLRP3 pathway activation was evaluated by RNA sequencing, qPCR, Western blotting, and ELISA, and its functional role was further confirmed by administration of the selective NLRP3 inhibitor MCC950. Statistical significance was defined as <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">In a cohort of 100 stroke patients, rectal swabs were collected for 16 S rRNA sequencing and qPCR analysis, and the results identified elevated <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">cylA</italic> gene levels as potential prognostic biomarkers for 360-day mortality. In a photothrombotic stroke mouse model, cytolysin-positive <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> exacerbated stroke severity by increasing BBB permeability. Mechanistically, cytolysin activated nucleotide-binding oligomerization domain-like receptor family pyrin domain containing 3 (NLRP3) inflammasome-mediated pyroptosis, further compromising BBB integrity. Additionally, cytolysin disrupted the intestinal barrier, increased permeability, and may facilitate its entry into the circulation, potentially contributing to BBB damage. Notably, NLRP3 inhibition with MCC950 mitigated neurological deficits and restored BBB integrity.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">Cytolysin aggravates ischemic stroke by compromising the BBB via NLRP3 activation and disrupting the intestinal barrier. Targeting cytolysin and NLRP3 holds promise as a therapeutic strategy for neuroprotection during ischemic stroke.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s12974-025-03590-5.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Ischemic stroke</kwd><kwd>Cytolysin</kwd><kwd>Blood–brain barrier (BBB)</kwd><kwd>NLRP3 inflammasome</kwd><kwd>Neuroprotection</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/501100007194</institution-id><institution>Wenzhou Municipal Science and Technology Bureau</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>Y20210170</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Ruo-ting</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/501100004731</institution-id><institution>Natural Science Foundation of Zhejiang Province</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>LQ23H090005</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Ruo-ting</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Basic Research Funds of Wenzhou Medical University</institution></funding-source><award-id>KYYW202325</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Ruo-ting</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par5">Ischemic stroke (IS) remains a significant global health challenge and a leading cause of death and disability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. As of 2019, there were over 77 million prevalent cases worldwide, with 7.6 million new cases, 3.3 million deaths, and more than 63 million ischemic stroke-related disability-adjusted life-years (DALYs) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Currently, ultra-early intravenous thrombolysis and mechanical thrombectomy are the only proven reperfusion therapies for acute ischemic stroke (AIS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>], but their effectiveness is limited by strict time windows, contraindications, bleeding risks, and suboptimal recanalization rates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Given the substantial health burden of AIS, elucidating the underlying mechanisms of IS-related brain injury remains a critical priority for the development of more effective and reliable neuroprotective interventions.</p><p id="Par6">Building on the importance of understanding stroke pathophysiology, recent studies have focused on the gut–brain axis as a critical regulator of stroke outcomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>], revealing the influence of the gut microbiota and its metabolites on prognosis through neural, endocrine, metabolic, and immune pathways [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>], particularly in relation to epithelial barrier integrity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Studies have shown that the abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> is significantly greater in patients with IS than in healthy individuals and is closely associated with disease severity and prognosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> secretes a pore-forming toxin known as cytolysin, which consists of two bioactive, post-translationally modified peptides, CylL<sub>L</sub>’’ and CylL<sub>S</sub>’’ [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Cytolysin induces persistent pore formation in target cell membranes, leading to excessive potassium ion efflux and the subsequent activation of the nucleotide-binding oligomerization domain-like receptor family pyrin domain containing 3 (NLRP3) inflammasome signaling pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>].</p><p id="Par7">The NLRP3 inflammasome is a key intracellular complex involved in immune responses to infections and cellular damage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Upon activation, the NLRP3 inflammasome recruits ASC, facilitating the activation of caspase-1, which in turn processes the proinflammatory cytokines IL-1β and IL-18 into their active forms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Caspase-1 also cleaves gasdermin D (GSDMD), forming membrane pores that trigger pyroptosis and amplify inflammation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. This highly pro-inflammatory microenvironment accelerates neuronal cell death [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. In IS, during which cerebral blood flow cessation leads to neurovascular injury, the subsequent inflammatory response plays a crucial role in secondary damage and prognosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Thus, targeting the NLRP3 inflammasome may be a promising therapeutic approach for treating ischemic stroke.</p><p id="Par8">On the basis of previous studies and our preliminary experiments, we hypothesize that following ischemic stroke, <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic>-derived cytolysin compromises intestinal epithelial integrity, increasing gut barrier permeability and enabling its entry into systemic circulation. This process may subsequently induce pyroptosis in cerebrovascular endothelial cells, thereby exacerbating brain injury. The aim of this study was to investigate how cytolysin disrupts the blood–brain barrier via NLRP3 inflammasome activation, using a photothrombotic stroke mouse model gavaged with cytolysin-positive <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> and in vitro experiments stimulated with cytolysin-containing supernatant. The study revealed that cytolysin worsened ischemic stroke by damaging both the blood–brain barrier and intestinal barrier via NLRP3 activation. By elucidating the potential pathogenic role of <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> in ischemic stroke, this study provides novel therapeutic insights.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Patient cohort</title><p id="Par9">Patients who were diagnosed with ischemic stroke at the First Affiliated Hospital of Wenzhou Medical University were enrolled. The inclusion criteria were a diagnosis of ischemic stroke; age greater than 18 years; onset time less than 48 h; and willingness to participate in research and provide specimens. The exclusion criteria were the use of oral or intravenous antibiotics 3 months before sampling; failure to obtain rectal swabs; other surgeries or invasive examinations three months before sample collection; thrombolysis or thrombectomy after the onset of the disease; epilepsy that affects the National Institutes of Health Stroke Scale (NIHSS) score or neurological deficit symptom assessment; a combined history of intracranial tumors or active malignant tumors; and pregnancy or lactation.</p><p id="Par10">A total of 100 patients were enrolled in our study. Rectal swabs were obtained within 48 h of onset and stored in a −80 °C freezer. The prognosis of each patient was recorded at 30, 90, 180 and 360 days. Our study was approved by the Ethics Committee in Clinical Research (ECCR) of the First Affiliated Hospital of Wenzhou Medical University (number: KY2023-090) and was conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki and the STROBE (Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology) guidelines. Written informed consent was obtained from all participants or their authorized representatives.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Identification of bacteria by gel electrophoresis</title><p id="Par11">The standard strains of <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus faecalis</italic> (#29212 and #700802, ATCC) were thawed, resuspended, stored in a −80 °C freezer, and streaked onto BHI agar medium (110704026, BKMAMLAB). If single-colony formation was insufficient, the bacteria were collected using a filtered pipette tip and resuspended in PBS for bacterial DNA extraction and PCR (Beijing Genes and Biotechnch Co., Ltd.). Finally, agarose gel electrophoresis (Gel Red, D0139, Beyotime) was performed, and the results were visualized using a UV transilluminator (Bio-Techne).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Experimental animals</title><p id="Par12">Healthy male 8-week-old C57BL/6J mice weighing 22–24 g (Charles River, Beijing, China) were used for the experiments. All the mice, which were maintained at the Laboratory Animal Resources Center of Wenzhou Medical University, had free access to water and food, were housed at a comfortable temperature (23–25 °C) and were exposed to 12-hour:12-hour light‒dark cycle. To investigate the effects of cytolysin in vivo, mice were orally gavaged once daily for 14 consecutive days with 5 × 10⁸ colony-forming units (CFU) of either a cytolysin-positive <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus faecalis</italic> strain (CylPE.f, ATCC#29212), a cytolysin-negative <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus faecalis</italic> strain (CylNE.f, ATCC#700802), or PBS as a vehicle control, as described in previous research [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. All animal procedures were approved by the Laboratory Animal Resources Center of Wenzhou Medical University (number: wydw2025-0020). The preparation of this manuscript followed the ARRIVE guidelines for reporting animal research.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Photothrombotic (PT) ischemia model</title><p id="Par13">One hundred microliters of Bengal Rose dye was intraperitoneally injected into the mice, and after 30 min, the mice were anesthetized with 1% sodium pentobarbital (50 mg/kg, i.p.). After the fur was removed, the mice were disinfected with iodine solution. An incision was made along the sagittal line of the scalp, the skull was exposed, and the mouse was fixed on a stereotaxic frame. A hole was drilled in the skull using a drill bit with a diameter of 0.5 mm at coordinates (−1.0 mm, −1.0 mm), with the bregma as the zero point. The exposed brain tissue of the mice was exposed to 473 nm blue excitation light emitted by a 40 W laser emitter for 15 min. Then, the incision was sutured, and the mice were placed on a heating pad to maintain body temperature until they were fully awake. The scalp of the mice in the Sham group was cut open, and the skull was drilled before the scalp was sutured. Then, neurological deficits were assessed using two behavioral tests: the balance beam test and the Longa neurological scoring system (Supplementary Table 1).</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>16 S rRNA analysis</title><p id="Par14">Total genomic DNA was extracted from rectal swabs or mouse stool using an OMEGA Soil DNA Kit (M5635-02) (Omega Bio-Tek, Norcross, GA, USA) following the manufacturer’s instructions and then stored at −20 °C until further analysis. PCR amplification of the bacterial 16 S rRNA gene V3–V4 region was performed using the forward primer 338 F (5’-ACTCCTACGGGAGGCAGCA-3’) and the reverse primer 806R (5’-GGACTACHVGGGTWTCTAAT-3’). The PCR amplicons were purified with Vazyme VAHTSTM DNA Clean Beads (Vazyme, Nanjing, China) and quantified using a Quant-iT PicoGreen dsDNA Assay Kit (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA). After the individual quantification step, amplicons were pooled in equal amounts, and pair-end 2*250 bp sequencing was performed using the Illumina platform at Shanghai Personal Biotechnology Co., Ltd. (Shanghai, China).</p><p id="Par15">Microbiome bioinformatics was performed with QIIME2 2022.11 using default parameters, with slight modifications based on the official tutorials. Briefly, raw sequence data were demultiplexed using the demux plugin, followed by primer cutting via the cutadapt plugin. Using the DADA2 plugin, the sequences were then quality filtered, denoised, and merged, and chimera were removed. Nonsingleton amplicon sequence variants (ASVs) were aligned with MAFFT and used to construct a phylogenetic tree with fasttree2. Alpha diversity was assessed using indices including Pielou’s evenness and Shannon diversity, while beta diversity was evaluated based on Jaccard distances and visualized via principal coordinate analysis (PCoA). Taxonomy was assigned to ASVs using the classify-sklearn naïve Bayes taxonomy classifier in the feature-classifier plugin against the SILVA Release 138 Database. Differential microbial taxa were identified using linear discriminant analysis (LDA) effect size (LEfSe) and the Wilcoxon rank-sum test (with LDA score &gt; 3.7 and Wilcoxon <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Laser speckle contrast imaging of cerebral blood flow (CBF)</title><p id="Par16">CBF was evaluated using a laser speckle flow analyzer (RFLSI III, RWD Life Sciences). After each mouse was anesthetized with 1% sodium pentobarbital (50 mg/kg, i.p.), the skin along the midline of the scalp was cut open to expose the skull, which was then placed under a laser speckle flowmeter. The surgical area at the same location as the contralateral hemisphere was selected to evaluate changes in CBF, and LSCI_V 1.0.0 software (RWD, China) was used for data analysis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>2,3,5-triphenyl tetrazolium chloride (TTC) staining</title><p id="Par17">TTC staining was performed on whole brains to evaluate infarcted areas on day 3 after PI. Mice were anesthetized with 1% sodium pentobarbital (50 mg/kg, i.p.). Brains were incubated in 2% TTC solution (in saline) at 37 °C for 20 min, followed by fixation in 4% paraformaldehyde for 24 h. Images were acquired using a digital camera, and infarct areas were quantified using FIJI software (NIH, Bethesda, MD, USA).</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Immunofluorescence staining</title><p id="Par18">After anesthesia with 1% sodium pentobarbital (50 mg/kg, i.p.), the mice were perfused with physiological saline and 4% paraformaldehyde (PFA), and the brain and jejunum were collected. After soaking in PFA at 4 °C for 24 h, the samples were soaked in 10% and 30% sucrose solutions for one day until the tissue settled to the bottom of the solution. The samples were embedded in optimal cutting temperature (OCT) compound (4583, Sakura Finetek USA, Inc.), and 10 μm- and 5 μm-thick frozen sections of brain tissue and jejunal tissue were prepared using a cryostat. Immunostaining blocking solution (P0260, Beyotime) was used to block and permeabilize the tissue for 15 min, after which the samples were incubated overnight at 4 °C with the appropriate primary antibodies. The sections were incubated with fluorescently labeled secondary antibodies at 37℃ for 1 h and then with DAPI (C1005, Beyotime) at 37℃ for 5 min, after which they were sealed with Antifade Mounting Medium (Beyotime) and fixed with neutral balsam (C0173, Beyotime). Then, imaging was performed using a fluorescence microscope (Leica, magnification: 20x). Fluorescence intensity and area were measured, and Pearson’s correlation coefficient for co-localization was calculated using FIJI software (NIH, Bethesda, MD, USA).</p><p id="Par19">The primary antibodies used were as follows: anti-human/mouse/rat CD31/PECAM-1 antibody (1:500, AF3628, Invitrogen); anti-ZO-1 polyclonal antibody (1:500, 61–7300, Invitrogen); anti-claudin 5 monoclonal antibody (4C3C2) (1:500, &gt;35–2500, Invitrogen); recombinant anti-occludin antibody (1:500, ab216327, Abcam); anti-albumin polyclonal antibody (1:200, 16475-1-AP, Proteintech); anti-IBA1 antibody (1:250, sc-32725, Santa Cruz Biotechnology); and anti-GFAP antibody (1:500, ab68428, Abcam). The secondary antibodies used were as follows: donkey anti-rabbit IgG (H + L) highly cross-adsorbed secondary antibody, Alexa FluorT 488 (1:1000, A-21206, Invitrogen) and donkey anti-goat IgG (H + L) cross-adsorbed secondary antibody, Alexa FluorT (1:1000, A-21447, Invitrogen).</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>TUNEL staining</title><p id="Par20">A TUNEL Apoptosis Detection Kit (40307ES60, Yeasen) was used for TUNEL staining. Fixed frozen tissue sections were incubated with Proteinase K solution at room temperature for 10 min, equilibrated with equilibration buffer at 37℃ for 5 min, and then incubated with TdT incubation buffer containing YSFluor 488-12-dUTP labeling mix at 37 °C for 1 h. The sections were stained with DAPI (C1005, Beyotime) at 37℃ for 5 min and sealed with Antifade Mounting Medium and fixed with neutral resin. Then, imaging was performed using a fluorescence microscope (Leica, magnification: 20x). Fluorescence intensity and area were measured using FIJI software (NIH, Bethesda, MD, USA).</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Measurement of brain water content (BWC)</title><p id="Par21">The mice were anesthetized with 1% sodium pentobarbital and euthanized by cervical dislocation, and the entire brain was removed and weighed (wet weight). After being placed in a 60 °C oven for 24 h, the brains were removed and weighed again (dry weight). BWC = (wet weight - dry weight)/wet weight.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Evan’s blue staining</title><p id="Par22">As previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], 2% Evans blue dye solution (10 µl/g body weight; E6135, Macklin) dissolved in PBS was injected into the tail vein of each mouse. After 30 min to allow for the dye to circulate, the mice were perfused with PBS through the heart. The surgical hemispheres were separated, weighed, soaked in 500 µL formamide (HY-Y0842, MCE), and ground into a homogenate. The mixture was incubated in a 55 °C water bath for 48 h, centrifuged at 6000 × g at 4 °C for 15 min, and the optical density (OD) was measured at 610 nm.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Cell culture</title><p id="Par23">The mouse brain microvascular endothelial cell line bEnd.3 (iCell Bioscience) was cultured in high-glucose DMEM (iCell-128-0001, iCell Bioscience) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (10099141 C, Gibco) and 0.5% penicillin‒streptomycin solution (15140122, Gibco). The cells were cultured in a 37 °C incubator, and 5% CO<sub>2</sub> was added.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Measurement of endothelial permeability in vitro</title><p id="Par24">The method was performed in accordance with a previously reported method and the manufacturer’s instructions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Five thousand cells were resuspended in 200 µl of culture medium and added to the upper chamber of a Transwell (3470, 6.5 mm Transwell with 0.4 μm pore polyester membrane insert, Corning). A total of 500 µl of culture medium was added to the lower chamber until it had just passed through the membrane. After the cells were incubated for 5 days, the culture medium in the upper and lower chambers were removed. Two hundred microliters of FITC-dextran (MW 4000, GC18871, GLPBIO, diluted to 1 mg/ml with PBS) was added to the upper chamber, and 500 µl of PBS was added to the lower chamber. The Transwells were incubated in an incubator for 45 min. One hundred microliters of medium was removed from the upper chamber, and the absorbance was measured (Ex = 495 nm; Em = 525 nm).</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>RNA sequencing and data processing</title><p id="Par25">Total RNA was isolated using TRIzol Reagent (Invitrogen Life Technologies), after which RNA concentration, quality and integrity were determined using a NanoDrop spectrophotometer (Thermo Scientific). Three micrograms of RNA were used as input material for the RNA sample preparation, and then, sequencing libraries were generated. Products were purified (AMPure XP system) and quantified using the Agilent high-sensitivity DNA assay on a Bioanalyzer 2100 system (Agilent). The sequencing library was then sequenced on the NovaSeq 6000 platform (Illumina) at Shanghai Personal Biotechnology Co. Ltd.</p><p id="Par26">Differences in the expression of genes were analyzed using DESeq (v1.38.3, default parameters). The R language Pheatmap (v1.0.12, default parameters) software package was used to perform bi-directional clustering analysis of all the different genes in the samples. A heatmap was generated according to the expression level of the same gene in different samples and the expression patterns of different genes in the same sample via the Euclidean method to calculate the distance and complete linkage method for clustering. TopGO (v2.50.0, default parameters) was used to perform GO enrichment analysis of the DEGs (all DEGs/upregulated DEGs/downregulated DEGs). ClusterProfiler (v4.6.0, default parameters) software was used to carry out enrichment analysis of the KEGG pathways of the DEGs. The data were analyzed by using the free online platform Personalbio GenesCloud (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.genescloud.cn">https://www.genescloud.cn</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>ELISAs</title><p id="Par27">IL-18, IL-1β, CXCL1, CCL2, CCL5 and CXCL10 concentrations were measured using commercially available ELISA kits (Mouse IL-1β ELISA kit, JL18442, J&amp;L Biological; Mouse IL-18 ELISA kit, JL20253, J&amp;L Biological; Mouse CXCL1 ELISA kit, JL20150, J&amp;L Biological; Mouse CCL2 ELISA kit, JL20304, J&amp;L Biological; Mouse CCL5 ELISA kit, JL17335, J&amp;L Biological; Mouse CXCL10 ELISA kit, JL13372, J&amp;L Biological). All reagents were provided with each kit, and ELISAs were performed in accordance with the manufacturer’s manual.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Measurement of D-lactic acid</title><p id="Par28">D-Lactic acid was measured using a commercially available D-Lactic Acid Content Assay Kit (AKAC014M, Beijing Boxbio Science &amp; Technology Co., Ltd.). All reagents were provided with the kit, and the experimental steps were performed in accordance with the manufacturer’s manual.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Western blot</title><p id="Par29">The proteins extracted from brain tissue and bEnd.3 cells using RIPA lysis buffer and then electrophoresed and transferred to PVDF membranes. After the membranes were blocked with protein-free rapid blocking buffer (PS108P, Epizyme Biotech) at 37℃ for 10 min, they were incubated overnight at 4 °C with primary antibodies. The primary antibodies used were as follows: anti-gasdermin D (E9S1X) rabbit mAb (1:1000, #39754, Cell Signaling Technology), anti-cleaved gasdermin D (Asp276) rabbit mAb (1:1000, #10137, Cell Signaling Technology), anti-IL-1β rabbit mAb (1:1000, #12507, Cell Signaling Technology), anti-cleaved-IL-1β (Asp117) rabbit mAb (1:1000, #63124, Cell Signaling Technology), anti-caspase-1 rabbit mAb (1:1000, #24232, Cell Signaling Technology), anti-cleaved caspase-1 (Asp296) rabbit mAb (1:1000, #89332, Cell Signaling Technology), anti-ASC rabbit mAb (1:1000, #67824, Cell Signaling Technology), anti-HMGB1 rabbit mAb (1:1000, #6893, Cell Signaling Technology), recombinant anti-IL-18 antibody (1:1000, ab207323, Abcam), anti-NLRP3 antibody (1:1000, DF7438, Affinity Biosciences), anti-beta actin antibody (1:10000, AF7018, Affinity Biosciences), and anti-GAPDH polyclonal antibody (1:10000, AP0063, Bioworld Technology, Inc). The membrane was subsequently incubated with a secondary antibody (anti-rabbit IgG, HRP-linked antibody, #7074; Cell Signaling Technology) at room temperature for 1 h. Immunoreactivity was then detected using SuperSignal West Pico PLUS Chemiluminescent Substrate (#34577; Thermo Scientific). Imaging was performed using the eBLOT (e-BLOT Life Science) imaging system, and quantification was conducted using FIJI software (NIH, Bethesda, MD, USA).</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Quantitative real-time PCR (RT‒qPCR)</title><p id="Par30">Total RNA was extracted using an RNeasy™ RNA Isolation Kit (R0027, Beyotime Biotechnology) and reverse transcribed into cDNA using qRT‒PCR Master Mix (QPR-200, TOROIVD). RT‒qPCR was performed using qPCR Master Mix (QST-100P, TOROIVD) on a real-time PCR system (Thermo Fisher Scientific). Bacterial 16 S rRNA served as the internal control for the <italic toggle="yes">cylA</italic> gene, while <italic toggle="yes">Gapdh</italic> mRNA was used as the normalization control in mice. The relative expression level was calculated using the ΔΔCT method. Each real-time PCR was performed three times. The sequences of primers used for RT‒qPCR (Sangon Biotech) are shown in Supplementary Table 2.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Determination of intestinal permeability</title><p id="Par31">After fasting for 8 h, each mouse was orally administered FITC-dextran (MW 4000, GC18871, GLPBIO) at a dose of 600 mg/kg per mouse in the dark. After 2 h, the mice were anesthetized with 1% sodium pentobarbital and euthanized by cervical dislocation, and whole blood was collected and centrifuged in an anticoagulant tube at 3000 rpm for 10 min at 4 °C, after which the upper plasma layer was retained. One hundred microliters of plasma was used to measure the absorbance (Ex = 495 nm; Em = 525 nm).</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Data analysis and statistics</title><p id="Par32">Normality was assessed with the Kolmogorov–Smirnov test. Nonparametric data are reported as medians (IQRs) and compared using the Mann–Whitney U test or the Kruskal–Wallis test with Dunn’s post hoc test. Parametric data are presented as means ± SD and analyzed with Student’s t test or one-way ANOVA followed by Tukey’s post hoc test. Univariate analysis of candidate variables was performed using univariate logistic regression analysis and univariate Cox regression analysis. Variables with a two-sided p value of &lt; 0.2 were entered into the multivariate logistic regression to construct the prediction model. The predictive performance for death was assessed by comparing receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curves, and the results are reported as areas under the curves (AUCs). R version 4.4.1 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.r-project.org/">https://www.r-project.org/</ext-link>) and GraphPad Prism 9 software were used for statistical analysis and figure generation. Two-tailed <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> values &lt; 0.05 were considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec24"><title>Elevated levels of cytolysin-positive <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> in patients with ischemic stroke can predict adverse outcomes after stroke</title><p id="Par33">We performed 16 S rRNA gene sequencing to investigate whether adverse outcomes in patients with stroke are associated with alterations in the fecal microbiota composition. One-hundred acute ischemic stroke patients were recruited from January 2021 to September 2023 at the Stroke Centre of the First Affiliated Hospital of Wenzhou Medical University; the inclusion and exclusion processes are detailed in Supplementary Fig. 1. Rectal swab samples were collected from each patient within 48 h of stroke onset. Among the patients, 14 (14.0%) died within 30 days, 20 (20.0%) died within 90 days, 25 (25.0%) died within 180 days, and 33 (33.0%) died within 360 days (Supplementary Table 3). We conducted 16 S rRNA gene sequencing and <italic toggle="yes">cylA</italic> gene qPCR using 100 rectal swab samples collected within 48 h of stroke onset to investigate whether patient mortality and survival are linked to alterations in the composition of cytolysin-positive <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic>. The relative abundance of the genus <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> was significantly greater in 360-day mortality patients (median 13.0%, IQR 3.5%−42.5%) than in 360-day survival patients (median 3.0%, IQR 1.0%−19.0%) (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0239, Mann‒Whitney U test) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A). The relative expression of the cytolysin exotoxin gene <italic toggle="yes">cylA</italic> determined by qPCR was significantly greater in 360-day mortality patients (median 6.105, IQR 1.230–19.98) than in 360-day survival patients (median 1.502, IQR 0.3353–5.856) (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.002, Mann‒Whitney U test) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>B). ROC analysis revealed the high diagnostic value of the <italic toggle="yes">cylA</italic> level for mortality (AUC = 0.688, 95% CI: 0.574–0.802, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.002) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>C). An improved mortality prediction model combining the level of <italic toggle="yes">cylA</italic> with age and sex yielded an AUC of 0.787 (AUC = 0.787, 95% CI: 0.689–0.884, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> ≤ 0.001) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>C). When the cohort was divided into two groups, i.e., low levels of <italic toggle="yes">cylA</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">cylA</italic> &lt; median, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 50) and high levels of <italic toggle="yes">cylA</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">cylA</italic> &gt; median, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 50), there was a significant intergroup difference in 360-day mortality (log rank <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0244, hazard ratio (HR) = 0.4480, 95% CI: 0.1543–1.055) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>D). The same trend was also observed between 30-day mortality and 30-day survival, 90-day mortality and 90-day survival, and 180-day mortality and 180-day survival (Supplementary Fig. 2). Logistic regression analyses were performed to investigate the association between cytolysin and mortality (Supplementary Table 4). The relative expression of the <italic toggle="yes">cylA</italic> gene was significantly associated with 360-day mortality (OR 1.038, 95% CI: 1.008 − 1.068, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.012), and this association remained significant after adjusting for age and sex (OR 1.040, 95% CI: 1.009 − 1.073, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.012). Furthermore, univariate Cox regression analysis indicated that <italic toggle="yes">cylA</italic> was independently associated with 360-day mortality, a finding that persisted in the multivariate Cox regression model adjusted for age and sex (HR 1.016, 95% CI: 1.004 − 1.027, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.006) (Supplementary Table 5). These results suggest that elevated levels of gut cytolysin-positive <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> in ischemic stroke patients may serve as a potential predictor of poor post-stroke outcomes.<fig id="Fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Elevated levels of cytolysin-positive <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> predict poor prognosis in ischemic stroke patients. <bold>A</bold> Comparison of the relative abundance of the genus <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> between the 360-day mortality and survival groups, presented as medians (IQRs); 360-day mortality, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 33; 360-day survival, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 67; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> values are determined by Mann-Whitney U test. <bold>B</bold> Relative quantification of the cytolysin exotoxin gene <italic toggle="yes">cylA</italic> by qPCR, presented as medians (IQRs); 360-day mortality, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 33; 360-day survival, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 67; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> values are determined by Mann-Whitney U test. <bold>C</bold> Receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curves evaluating the predictive value of <italic toggle="yes">cylA</italic> alone or in combination with age and NIHSS score for stroke mortality. <bold>D</bold> Kaplan–Meier survival curves over 360 days for patients with low (<italic toggle="yes">cylA</italic> &lt; median) and high (<italic toggle="yes">cylA</italic> &gt; median) <italic toggle="yes">cylA</italic> levels. Sample size: <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 100, * <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, ** <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e650" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12974_2025_3590_Fig1_HTML.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec25"><title>Cytolysin-positive <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> can exacerbate ischemic stroke</title><p id="Par34">We performed 16 S rRNA gene sequencing to determine whether PT model mice have an altered fecal microbiota composition. The fecal microbiota composition was significantly different among PT model mice, Sham mice, and control mice, as indicated by the α diversity, Shannon index (Kruskal‒Wallis <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.031) and Pielou_e index (Kruskal‒Wallis <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.019, Sham vs. Con Dunn’s test <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.04, PT vs. Con Dunn’s test <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.033) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>A). β diversity analysis revealed significant differences in the microbiota composition among the PT, Sham and control groups (Jaccard-based Adonis test, R<sup>2</sup> = 0.233, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001; PT vs. Sham, Adonis test, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.001; Sham vs. Con, Adonis test, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.002; PT vs. Con, Adonis test, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.004) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>B). The <italic toggle="yes">E. faecalis</italic> content was notably greater in the PT group than in the sham and control groups (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>C-E). We then identified the cytolysin-positive <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> strains using PCR gel electrophoresis (Supplementary Fig. 3). To determine whether cytolysin contributes to brain damage mediated by <italic toggle="yes">E. faecalis</italic>, we gavaged mice with CylPE.f, CylNE.f or PBS. The 16 S sequencing results indicated a marked increase in the abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> within the fecal samples of the mice subjected to <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> gavage (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>F, Supplementary Fig. 4A-C). Moreover, compared with the CylNE.f-gavaged group, mice gavaged with CylPE.f had significantly higher relative <italic toggle="yes">cylA</italic> mRNA expression in fecal samples, indicating successful colonization of CylPE.f (Supplementary Fig. 4D). The mice were then grouped and treated with PT or sham according to their assigned groups. The balance beam test results and Longa scores for the PT + CylPE.f group were significantly greater than those for the PT + PBS and PT + CylNE.f groups (all <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>G). In the assessment of CBF, PT + CylPE.f mice presented a significantly greater reduction in blood flow within the infarct area than PT + CylNE.f mice did (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>H-I). However, TTC staining revealed only a mild increase in the PT + CylPE.f group compared with the PT + PBS or PT + CylNE.f groups, which did not reach statistical significance (Supplementary Fig. 5A-B). Apoptotic TUNEL staining was conducted using brain sections from mice. Compared with those in the infarct area of brains from mice in the PT + PBS and PT + CylNE.f groups, the number of apoptotic cells in the infarct area of brains from mice in the PT + CylPE.f groups was greater (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>J-K). There were no significant differences among the sham + PBS, sham + CylNE.f, and sham + CylPE.f groups (Supplementary Fig. 5C-D). These results suggest that cytolysin significantly exacerbates ischemic brain injury by aggravating neurological deficits and promoting cell apoptosis in the infarcted region.</p><p id="Par35">
<fig id="Fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Cytolysin-positive <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> exacerbates ischemic stroke in mice. <bold>A</bold> α-diversity indices (Shannon index and Pielou_e index) in the control, Sham, and photothrombotic (PT) groups, performed by Kruskal-Wallis test with Dunn’s post-hoc test, *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05; <bold>B</bold> Principal coordinate analysis (PCoA) based on the Jaccard distance showing β diversity among the groups, with statistical significance assessed by the Adonis test (R² = 0.233, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001); <bold>C</bold> Bar plot showing the average relative abundances of dominant bacterial taxa at the genus level in the control, sham, and PT groups, with <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> highlighted in red; <bold>D</bold> Heatmap illustrating elevated abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> in the PT group; <bold>E</bold> LEfSe analysis (LDA score &gt; 3.7) identifying significantly discriminative taxa among groups, with <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> significantly enriched in the PT group; <bold>F</bold> Heatmap of the top 20 most differentially abundant genera in mice after oral gavage with <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic>, showing a significant increase in <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> in the treated group; <bold>G</bold> Neurological function scores (beam balance test and Longa score) were significantly higher in the PT + CylPE.f group than in the PT + CylNE.f and PT + PBS groups, presented as the means ± standard deviations; * <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, ** <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01, performed by one-way ANOVA with Tukey’s post-hoc test; <bold>H</bold>,<bold> I</bold> Representative laser speckle contrast images and quantification of cerebral blood flow (CBF) in the infarct region, presented as the means ± standard deviations; *** <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001, **** <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001, performed by one-way ANOVA with Tukey’s post-hoc test; <bold>J</bold>,<bold> K</bold> Representative TUNEL staining images and quantification of apoptotic cells in mouse brain tissue (scale bar = 100 μm), presented as the means ± standard deviations; **** <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001, performed by one-way ANOVA with Tukey’s post-hoc test</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e815" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12974_2025_3590_Fig2_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par36">We further examined astrocyte and microglial activation to assess the neuroinflammation. Immunofluorescence staining showed increased activation of microglia (IBA1) and astrocytes (GFAP) in the peri-infarct regions of mice in the PT + CylPE.f group compared with the PT + PBS and PT + CylNE.f groups. Quantitative analysis of fluorescence intensity further confirmed elevated IBA1 and GFAP signals, indicating enhanced glial activation in response to cytolysin exposure (Supplementary Fig. 5E–H).</p></sec><sec id="Sec26"><title>Cytolysin-positive <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> can exacerbate brain barrier damage</title><p id="Par37">To assess BBB disruption caused by cytolysin, we conducted both in vitro and in vivo studies. Firstly, we examined albumin extravasation in vivo, a critical indicator of BBB disruption, and found markedly higher leakage in the PT + CylPE.f group compared with the PT + PBS and PT + CylNE.f groups (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>A–B). In contrast, Sham + CylNE.f showed a modest but significant increase versus Sham + PBS (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05), while Sham + CylPE.f displayed a non-significant trend toward increased extravasation versus Sham + PBS group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt;0.05) (Supplementary Fig. 6A-B). ZO-1 and Claudin-5 are two representative protein indicators of tight junctions, and CD31 is a marker protein for blood vessels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. The immunofluorescence images of ZO-1 and Claudin-5 revealed that the tight junctions of the cerebral blood vessels in the Sham group were continuous and intact (Supplementary Fig. 6C-F). The tight junctions of cerebral blood vessels showed partial disruption in the PT + PBS and PT + CylNE.f groups, whereas the PT + CylPE.f group exhibited markedly greater discontinuity of tight junction structures, as confirmed by Pearson’s correlation coefficient analysis of colocalization between CD31 and ZO-1 or Claudin-5 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>C-F). Permeability assays using Evan’s Blue extravasation and BWC measurements corroborated these findings. Evan’s blue permeability was significantly greater in mice in the PT + CylPE.f group than in mice in the PT + PBS and PT + CylNE.f groups, while no significant changes were observed in the Sham group (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>G). Consistently, BWC analysis revealed a significant increase in mice in the PT + CylPE.f group compared with the PT + PBS and PT + CylNE.f groups, with no notable differences in the Sham group (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>H). Collectively, these findings suggest that cytolysin markedly enhances BBB permeability, thereby compromising BBB integrity during ischemic stroke.</p><p id="Par38">
<fig id="Fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Cytolysin-positive <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> exacerbates blood-brain barrier (BBB) disruption. <bold>A</bold>,<bold> B</bold> Representative whole-brain and magnified images of albumin immunofluorescence staining in mouse brain tissue (scale bar = 100 μm), with quantification bar graphs. <bold>C-F </bold>Immunofluorescence images showing DAPI (blue) for nuclei, CD31 (red) for vasculature, and ZO-1 or claudin-5 (green) for tight junction proteins of the BBB (scale bar = 100 μm), with quantification bar graphs (<bold>D</bold>, <bold>F</bold>). <bold>G </bold>Quantification of Evan’s blue extravasation across the BBB. <bold>H</bold> Quantification of BWC, indicating the extent of brain edema. <bold>I</bold> Bar graph showing FITC-dextran permeability in bEnd.3 cells following stimulation with medium, CylNE.f or CylPE.f. <bold>J–N</bold> ELISA results for proinflammatory chemokines (CCL2, CXCL10, CXCL1, and CCL5) in brain endothelial cells, presented as heatmaps and box plots. All the data are expressed as means ± standard deviations. The experiments were independently repeated three times with <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3; for all panels, * <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, ** <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01, *** <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001, and **** <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001, performed by one-way ANOVA with Tukey’s post-hoc test</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e905" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12974_2025_3590_Fig3_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par39">In vitro, we cultured brain microvascular endothelial cells in Transwell chambers and stimulated them with the sonicated supernatant of either CylPE.f or CylNE.f, with culture medium used as the control. The FITC-dextran permeability assay results revealed significantly greater FITC-dextran permeability in the CylPE.f group than in the CylNE.f and medium groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05), indicating a compromised endothelial barrier (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>I). We subsequently used ELISAs to quantify the levels of the pro-inflammatory chemokines CXCL1, CCL2, CCL5, and CXCL10 in the culture supernatant of bEnd.3 cells. After 3 h of exposure to CylPE.f supernatant, concentrations of these chemokines were significantly elevated compared with cells treated with medium or CylNE.f (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>J–N).</p><p id="Par40">In summary, the cytolysin produced by <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus faecalis</italic> can significantly damage the BBB and damage endothelial cells.</p></sec><sec id="Sec27"><title>Cytolysin activates the NLRP3 inflammasome to mediate the classical pyroptosis pathway in cerebral vascular endothelial cells, damaging the BBB</title><p id="Par41">To further explore the mechanism by which cytolysin damages the BBB, we conducted RNA-seq analysis using the damaged cortices of PT model mice and sham mice that were administered CylNE.f or CylPE.f via gavage. Distinct differences in gene expression were observed within the damaged cortex of mice in the sham group treated with CylNE.f or CylPE.f, with these differences becoming even more pronounced in mice in the PT + CylNE.f and PT + CylPE.f groups (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>A). GO enrichment analysis revealed a significantly greater number of genes enriched in the biological processes ‘response to external stimulus’ and ‘response to toxic substance’ in the PT + CylPE.f group than in the CylNE.f group (all <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>B). These findings indicate that the damaged cortex of mice in the PT + CylPE.f group indeed experienced increased exposure to external stimuli and toxic substances, thus verifying the impact of cytolysin at the genetic level. KEGG enrichment analysis revealed a significantly greater number of differentially expressed genes in the NOD-like receptor signaling pathway in the PT + CylPE.f group than in the PT + CylNE.f group (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>C). Therefore, NLRP3 and the pyroptosis pathway may play a role in cytolysin-induced damage to the BBB during ischemic stroke.</p><p id="Par42">
<fig id="Fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Cytolysin activates the NLRP3 inflammasome-mediated classical pyroptosis pathway in the infarct region of mice and in cerebrovascular endothelial cells. <bold>A</bold> Principal component analysis (PCA) plot showing transcriptomic differences among treatment groups in mouse brain tissue. <bold>B</bold>,<bold> C</bold> GO enrichment analysis (<bold>B</bold>) and KEGG pathway enrichment analysis (<bold>C</bold>) of differentially expressed genes in the PT + CylPE.f group compared with those in the PT + CylNE.f group. <bold>D</bold>,<bold> E </bold>Protein levels of IL-18 and IL-1β in serum measured using ELISA. <bold>F</bold>,<bold> G</bold> Western blot and quantification of the protein expression levels of NLRP3, GSDMD, cleaved GSDMD (C-GSDMD), IL-18, and IL-1β in mouse brain tissue. <bold>H</bold> qPCR analysis of the mRNA expression levels of <italic toggle="yes">Nlrp3</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Gsdmd</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Il18</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Il1b</italic> in mouse brain tissue. <bold>I</bold>,<bold> J</bold> Western blot and quantification of the protein levels of NLRP3, GSDMD, C-GSDMD, IL-18, and IL-1β in bEnd.3 cells. <bold>K</bold> qPCR analysis of the mRNA expression levels of <italic toggle="yes">Nlrp3</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Gsdmd</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Il18</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Il1b</italic> in bEnd.3 cells. All the data are presented as means ± standard deviations. The experiments were independently repeated three times with <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3; for all panels, * <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, ** <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01, *** <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001, and **** <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001, performed by one-way ANOVA analysis followed by Tukey’s test post hoc test</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1030" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12974_2025_3590_Fig4_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par43">To verify whether NLRP3 and the pyroptosis pathway are involved in the damage to the BBB caused by cytolysin in ischemic stroke, we collected blood samples from mice for ELISAs. We found that the levels of IL-18 and IL-1β were significantly increased in mice in the PT + CylPE.f group (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>D-E). These two cytokines are the main inflammatory factors released during pyroptosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>], consistent with the trend of the RNA-seq analysis results.</p><p id="Par44">We selected representative proteins (NLRP3, GSDMD, IL-18, and IL-1β) that mediate the classical pyroptosis pathway through the NLRP3 inflammasome. Western blotting was conducted using the damaged cortex of mice, and the results revealed a significant increase in the protein levels of NLRP3, C-GSDMD, IL-18, and IL-1β in mice in the PT + CylPE.f group (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>F-G). The mRNA levels of <italic toggle="yes">Nlrp3</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Gsdmd</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Il18</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Il1b</italic> were also significantly greater in the PT + CylPE.f group than in the PT + CylNE.f group (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>H). To exclude the influence of other factors in the brain, the same protein and mRNA analyses were conducted using bEnd.3 cells treated with sonicated solutions of medium, CylNE.f, or CylPE.f. The CylPE.f group had significantly elevated protein levels of NLRP3, C-GSDMD, IL-1β and IL-18, as determined by Western blotting (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>I-J). Similarly, the relative quantification of the mRNA levels detected by qPCR revealed that the levels of <italic toggle="yes">Nlrp3</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Gsdmd</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Il1b</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Il18</italic> significantly increased after stimulation with CylPE.f (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>K). Therefore, it can be inferred that NLRP3 and the pyroptosis pathway are involved in the process by which cytolysin damages the BBB in ischemic stroke and play a critical role.</p></sec><sec id="Sec28"><title>Cytolysin damages the intestinal barrier</title><p id="Par45">We speculate that the damaging effects of cytolysin on the BBB originate from its initial disruption of the intestinal barrier, subsequently allowing cytolysin to enter the bloodstream and reach the cerebral circulation. To test this hypothesis, naïve mice were divided into three groups and administered PBS, CylNE.f, or CylPE.f via oral gavage. The results revealed that the plasma D-lactate level, an indicator of intestinal integrity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>], was significantly higher in mice in the CylPE.f group than in mice in the CylNE.f and PBS groups (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>A). Additionally, FITC-dextran permeability assays revealed a markedly higher plasma FITC-dextran concentration in the CylPE.f group than in the CylNE.f and PBS groups (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>B). To more clearly demonstrate the impact of cytolysin on the intestinal barrier, immunofluorescence staining and quantification of the tight junction proteins ZO-1 and Occludin were performed. In the PBS group, ZO-1 staining appeared continuous and intact, whereas both the CylNE.f and CylPE.f groups showed disrupted and discontinuous ZO-1 patterns, with the reduction in fluorescence intensity observed in the CylPE.f group (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>C, D). Similarly, Occludin staining was continuous in the PBS and CylNE.f groups but decreased and fragmented in the CylPE.f group, consistent with the quantification results (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>E, F). These findings indicate that cytolysin significantly compromises the integrity of the intestinal epithelial barrier, leading to increased intestinal permeability. This disruption may serve as an early event in the broader pathological effects of cytolysin, including its impact on the BBB.</p><p id="Par46">
<fig id="Fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Cytolysin disrupts the intestinal barrier. <bold>A</bold> Bar graph showing the serum concentration of D-lactic acid, a biomarker of intestinal barrier damage. <bold>B</bold> Quantification of FITC-dextran permeability into plasma following oral gavage, indicating increased intestinal permeability. <bold>C-F</bold> Representative immunofluorescence images of mouse intestine tissue of the tight junction proteins ZO-1 (<bold>C</bold>) and Occludin (<bold>E</bold>) (green) and nuclei stained with DAPI (blue) (scale bar = 100 μm), with quantification bar graphs (<bold>D</bold>, <bold>F</bold>). All the data are presented as means ± standard deviations. The experiments were independently repeated three times, with <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3; for all panels, ** <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01, and **** <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001 by one-way ANOVA analysis followed by Tukey’s test post hoc test</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1139" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12974_2025_3590_Fig5_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec29"><title>Inhibition of NLRP3 can reverse the brain damage caused by Cytolysin and exert neuroprotective effects</title><p id="Par47">To verify the critical role of NLRP3 and its associated pyroptosis pathway in the exacerbation of ischemic stroke damage by cytolysin, we used MCC950, a specific inhibitor of NLRP3 that effectively suppresses pyroptosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. First, mice were divided into four groups: PT + PBS, PT + PBS + MCC950, PT + CylPE.f, and PT + CylPE.f + MCC950. Before sacrifice, we evaluated the neurological deficits of the mice using the balance beam test and Longa score and found that, compared with that in mice in the PT + CylPE.f group, the degree of neurological deficits in the mice in PT + CylPE.f + MCC950 group was significantly lower (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 for balance beam test; and <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01 for Longa score) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>A), indicating that inhibiting NLRP3 can significantly reduce the stroke damage caused by cytolysin. To verify the effect of inhibiting NLRP3 on brain cell apoptosis, we performed TUNEL staining. Compared with that in the PT + CylPE.f group, the number of apoptotic brain cells in the PT + CylPE.f + MCC950 group was significantly lower (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>B-C). In the assessment of CBF, PT + CylPE.f + MCC950 mice exhibited a significantly greater restoration of blood flow in the infarct area compared with PT + CylPE.f mice (Supplementary Fig. 7A–B). In contrast, TTC staining showed only a slight reduction in infarct volume in the PT + CylPE.f + MCC950 group relative to the PT + CylPE.f group, which did not reach statistical significance (Supplementary Fig. 7C-D). Subsequently, the degree of albumin permeability was determined to test BBB function. Compared with those in mice in the PT + CylPE.f group, albumin permeability (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>D-E) in mice in the groups treated with MCC950 was significantly lower, indicating that inhibiting NLRP3 can reverse the damage caused by cytolysin to the BBB. The BWC (Supplementary Fig. 7E) and Evan’s blue pass rate (Supplementary Fig. 7 F) in mice treated with MCC950 were significantly reduced, indicating that inhibiting NLRP3 can reverse the damage caused by cytolysin to the BBB. The tight junction proteins ZO-1 and Claudin-5 were subsequently analyzed by immunofluorescence staining and quantitative fluorescence analysis (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>F-I). The results showed a significant reduction in ZO-1 and Claudin-5 expression after CylPE.f gavage, which was partially restored following MCC950 treatment. These results indicate that inhibiting NLRP3 can reverse the brain damage caused by cytolysin and exert neuroprotective effects.</p><p id="Par48">
<fig id="Fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Inhibition of NLRP3 reverses cytolysin-induced blood-brain barrier (BBB) disruption and confers neuroprotection. <bold>A</bold> Neurological function scores, including the beam balance test and Longa score, were compared among the PT + PBS, PT + PBS + MCC950, PT + CylPE.f and PT + CylPE.f + MCC950 groups. <bold>B</bold>,<bold> C</bold> Representative fluorescence images of mouse brain tissue stained with DAPI (blue) and TUNEL (green), along with the quantification of apoptotic cells (scale bar = 100 μm). <bold>D</bold>,<bold> E</bold> Representative immunofluorescence images and quantification of albumin (green) and DAPI (blue) in whole-brain and magnified brain regions, indicating that MCC950 treatment alleviated the BBB leakage induced by CylPE.f (scale bar = 100 μm). <bold>F-I</bold> Immunofluorescence images showing DAPI (blue) for nuclei, CD31 (red) for vasculature, and ZO-1 or claudin-5 (green) for tight junction proteins of the BBB (scale bar = 100 μm), with quantification bar graphs (<bold>G</bold>, <bold>I</bold>). <bold>J-N</bold> Heatmap and box plots showing the ELISA results for proinflammatory chemokines (CCL2, CXCL10, CXCL1, and CCL5) secreted by endothelial cells. The experiments were independently repeated three times with <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3; for all panels, * <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, ** <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01, *** <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001, **** <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001, performed by one-way-ANOVA analysis followed by post-hoc Tukey’s test</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="d33e1220" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="12974_2025_3590_Fig6_HTML.jpg"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par49">We subsequently established an in vitro cell model using bEnd.3 cells, and the cells were divided into four groups: (1) bEnd.3 + medium, (2) bEnd.3 + medium + MCC950, (3) bEnd.3 + CylPE.f, and (4) bEnd.3 + CylPE.f + MCC950. The permeability of bEnd.3 cells was measured using the Transwell method with FITC-dextran. FITC-dextran absorbance was significantly lower in the CylPE.f + MCC950 group than in the CylPE.f group (Supplementary Fig. 7G), indicating that NLRP3 inhibition alleviates cytolysin-induced endothelial barrier damage. We subsequently used ELISAs to measure the protein concentrations of the endothelial pro-inflammatory chemokines CXCL1, CCL2, CCL5, and CXCL10 in the culture supernatant of bEnd.3 cells. Compared with those in the CylPE.f group, the protein levels of these chemokines were significantly lower in the CylPE.f + MCC950 group (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>J-N).</p><p id="Par50">These results suggest that inhibiting NLRP3 can effectively mitigate cytolysin-induced endothelial cell damage.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec30"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par51">Given the increasing recognition of the importance of the gut–brain axis in stroke pathology, the aim of this study was to investigate the role of cytolysin-producing <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> in ischemic stroke progression and its underlying mechanisms, with the goal of identifying potential therapeutic targets. In this study, a clinical cohort was established to investigate the correlation between the prognosis of ischemic stroke patients and the presence of cytolytic <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic>. Additionally, an ischemic stroke mouse model characterized by the enrichment of cytolytic <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> was developed to explore the underlying mechanism. The results demonstrated that following ischemic stroke, the enrichment of cytolytic <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> in the intestinal lumen exacerbated neurological deficits, increased neuronal apoptosis, disrupted the intestinal and blood‒brain barriers, and activated the NLRP3 inflammasome-mediated pyroptosis pathway. Notably, these pathological phenotypes were reversed by NLRP3 inhibitors. These findings provide a novel perspective on the interaction between the cytolysin-mediated gut microbiota and ischemic stroke, laying a theoretical foundation for future precision therapeutic strategies targeting the gut microbiota in ischemic stroke.</p><p id="Par52">There is a close association between the gut microbiota and stroke, and its critical role in regulating brain function has garnered increasing attention in recent years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. A prospective observational clinical study demonstrated that a combination of viable <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> tablets promote neurological recovery in stroke patients by modulating the levels of NF-κB, IL-1β, and TNF-α [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Another prospective case‒control study reported an increased abundance of anaerobic bacteria, including <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Peptostreptococcus</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Ezakiella</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia</italic> species, in the gut microbiota of patients with cerebral infarction and cerebral hemorrhage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Consistent with previous findings, our clinical cohort exhibited dysbiosis of the gut microbiota, characterized by a significant increase in <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> levels. Notably, a study by Duan et al. published in Nature revealed that cytolysin-positive <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> was markedly enriched in patients with alcoholic hepatitis and was strongly associated with disease severity and increased mortality [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Similarly, in our clinical cohort, cytolysin, a major virulence factor of <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic>, was an independent risk factor for 360-day mortality in ischemic stroke patients. Based on these findings, we hypothesize that <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic>, particularly its secretion of cytolysin, plays a pathogenic role in exacerbating the disease process. The subsequent animal experiments further substantiated this hypothesis. Ischemic stroke mice gavaged with cytolysin-positive <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> exhibited exacerbated neurological deficits, marked reductions in cerebral blood flow within the infarct area, and significantly increased numbers of apoptotic cells in the infarcted region. These results suggest a neurotoxic effect of cytolysin. Similarly, a previous study reported that fecal microbiota transplantation from patients with ST-elevation myocardial infarction worsened post-injury cardiac function in germ-free mice, highlighting the potential harm of specific gut microbiota to the cardiovascular and cerebrovascular systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>].</p><p id="Par53">The BBB is a vital physiological barrier that preserves central nervous system homeostasis and consists of epithelial cells interconnected by TJs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Disruption of the BBB has been implicated in the pathogenesis of various vascular and neurodegenerative disorders, including Alzheimer’s disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>], vascular cognitive impairment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>], and ischemic stroke [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Both broad-spectrum antibiotic treatment and germ-free conditions lead to the significant dysregulation of endothelial TJs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Furthermore, variations in the gut microbiota composition have been associated with differences in BBB integrity and FITC-dextran permeability in mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. These findings suggest that both the presence and specific composition of the gut microbiota play crucial roles in maintaining BBB integrity. In our study, within the pathophysiological context of an ischemic stroke mouse model, gavage with cytolysin-positive <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> led to a significant increase in the BWC and albumin extravasation and increased permeability to Evan’s blue dye, indicating that cytolysin contributes to BBB disruption. Moreover, cytolysin stimulation of brain endothelial cells resulted in increased FITC-dextran permeability, suggesting compromised endothelial barrier integrity. Previous studies have demonstrated that the enrichment of opportunistic pathogens in the gut can lead to lipopolysaccharide (LPS) accumulation, which, through TLR4 activation in microglia, induces endotoxemia and neuroinflammation, ultimately disrupting endothelial TJs and increasing BBB permeability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Additionally, gut microbiota-derived short-chain fatty acids (SCFAs) have been shown to modulate BBB permeability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>] and influence the integrity of BBB TJs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. These findings suggest that the gut microbiota may compromise BBB function by targeting TJs through metabolic products or endotoxins. Consistent with these findings, our experiments demonstrated that ischemic stroke model mice gavaged with cytolysin-positive <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> showed marked brain TJ disruption, suggesting that the <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> exotoxin cytolysin plays a critical role in BBB endothelial dysfunction. Moreover, in an in vitro brain microvascular endothelial cell model, cytolysin stimulation led to the marked upregulation of pro-inflammatory chemokine expression, further supporting the role of cytolysin in endothelial barrier impairment. Collectively, these in vivo and in vitro findings provide compelling evidence that cytolysin-positive <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> directly interacts with brain microvascular endothelial cells, compromising endothelial TJs and disrupting BBB integrity. Based on our results, we propose that following ischemic stroke, the enrichment of <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> strains, particularly cytolysin-positive strains, may exacerbate brain injury through cytolysin-mediated BBB dysfunction.</p><p id="Par54">To investigate the underlying mechanism of cytolysin-mediated BBB dysfunction, we performed RNA-seq analysis on the infarcted brain region. The RNA-seq results indicated that, within the pathophysiological context of ischemic stroke, cytolysin significantly upregulates the expression of genes associated with the “NOD-like receptor signaling pathway” in brain tissue. NLRP3, a cytosolic pattern recognition receptor (PRR) belonging to the NOD-like receptor (NLR) family, plays a crucial role in innate immune responses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. NLRP3 inflammasome pathway activation is a key signaling mechanism that contributes to excessive inflammation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Previous studies have demonstrated that NLRP3 inflammasome activation in neurons drives neuroinflammation in acute ischemic stroke [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>] and that the inhibition of NLRP3 activation mitigates hypoxic-ischemic brain injury in neonatal male rats [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. These findings highlight the critical role of NLRP3 in exacerbating ischemic stroke outcomes. In our study, the cytolysin-positive <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> intervention group exhibited a significant increase in key mRNA transcripts associated with the NLRP3 pathway in brain tissue, along with increased protein expression of key pyroptosis-related markers, including NLRP3, caspase-1, GSDMD, IL-1β, and IL-18. These findings suggest that cytolysin, as a pore-forming toxin, activates the NLRP3 pathway, which is likely a critical mechanism underlying the cytolysin-induced disruption of BBB permeability and exacerbation of ischemic stroke. NLRP3-associated proteins are typically expressed in endothelial cells and microglia, and NLRP3 inflammasome activation can further suppress TJ protein expression, exacerbating BBB damage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. In vitro studies have shown that NLRP3 inhibition stabilizes endothelial cell integrity and reduces endothelial cell death under oxygen‒glucose deprivation (OGD) conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>], further supporting a close relationship between NLRP3 inflammasome activation and BBB disruption in ischemic stroke. Our in vivo findings demonstrated that the pathological phenotypes observed in ischemic stroke mice gavaged with cytolysin-positive <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic>—including exacerbated neurological deficits, elevated apoptotic cell counts, and increased BBB permeability—were effectively reversed by NLRP3 inhibition. Consistently, in vitro experiments further demonstrated that NLRP3 inhibition significantly alleviated endothelial barrier disruption and inflammatory responses inducted by the sonicated supernatant of cytolysin-positive <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic>. These findings highlight the pivotal role of NLRP3 activation in mediating cytolysin-driven ischemic brain injury. Collectively, our results, in conjunction with those of previous studies, suggest that the NLRP3 inflammasome acts as a critical mediator linking cytolysin-induced BBB dysfunction, endothelial inflammation, and the progression of ischemic stroke pathology.</p><p id="Par55">Disruption of intestinal barrier function is a common consequence of brain injury [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>] and is typically characterized by increased intestinal permeability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. Studies have shown that middle cerebral artery occlusion (MCAO) in a rat model results in a widespread reduction in the number of TJs between intestinal epithelial cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. Similarly, murine models of ischemic stroke exhibit elevated levels of inflammatory proteins in the small intestine, reduced TJ protein expression in ileal epithelial cells, and significantly increased intestinal permeability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. Our findings revealed that cytolysin disrupts intestinal TJs and increases intestinal permeability, highlighting its detrimental effect on intestinal barrier integrity. The impact of <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> on intestinal barrier function remains controversial. A study suggested that the metalloproteinase GelE, produced by <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic>, compromises intestinal epithelial barrier integrity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>], which aligns with our results. Conversely, other studies have indicated that <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> can reduce oxidative stress in porcine intestinal epithelial cells and decrease intercellular permeability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. Additionally, <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> has been reported to maintain intestinal integrity in Ross roosters by regulating <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> O78 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>], findings that contradict our results. We propose that these discrepancies may stem from multiple factors, including genotypic and phenotypic variations among <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> strains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>], differences in experimental conditions (e.g., animal models and culture conditions) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>], the complexity of the gut microbiota [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>], and variations in host genetic background and immune status [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. Furthermore, it is conceivable that certain metabolites produced by <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> could exert concentration-dependent dual effects, potentially supporting barrier function at low concentrations via immunomodulatory or antioxidative pathways while impairing barrier integrity at relatively high concentrations. Therefore, the impact of <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> on the intestinal barrier is likely multifactorial, warranting further investigation to elucidate the specific mechanisms and conditions governing these effects. Despite these conflicting findings, our study provides evidence that <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> disrupts intestinal barrier function through cytolysin secretion. Furthermore, disruptions in intestinal function can further disturb immune homeostasis, establishing a bidirectional feedback loop along the gut‒brain axis that sustains and exacerbates neurological dysfunction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]. For example, <italic toggle="yes">Akkermansia muciniphila</italic> has been shown to modulate the gut‒brain axis by maintaining the intestinal mucosal barrier [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>], whereas probiotic diets can restore intestinal barrier function and alleviate migraines via gut‒brain axis modulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]. Integrating our findings with those of previous studies, we propose that ischemic stroke leads to an enrichment of <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> in the intestinal lumen and a corresponding increase in cytolysin levels, initiating a top-down influence along the gut‒brain axis. In turn, elevated cytolysin exacerbates intestinal barrier dysfunction, facilitating the translocation of bacterial exotoxins into the bloodstream and further compromising the BBB. This establishes a bottom-up feedback loop that amplifies neurological damage and worsens ischemic stroke pathology.</p><p id="Par56">The present study has several strengths and unique aspects. First, in this study, we innovatively investigated the role of <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> and its exotoxin cytolysin in ischemic stroke. We elucidated the bridging role of the exotoxin cytolysin between gut dysbiosis and neurological damage, providing a novel perspective for microbiota-related research. Second, through this study, we clarified the mechanism by which cytolysin induces brain injury, revealing its involvement in pyroptosis via the NLRP3 signaling pathway. This study deepens the understanding of the toxic effects of cytolysin and provides new insights into microbiota-targeted interventions, such as bacteriophage or biological antibody therapies, laying a theoretical foundation for precision treatment. Third, we optimized an animal model to increase the clinical translational value of the results. The widely used MCAO model often results in high mortality and extensive infarcts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>], which do not accurately reflect the prevalence of minor and moderate strokes in clinical settings. By employing a PT stroke model to induce small infarcts, we achieved a closer alignment with clinical reality, notably improving the translational potential of our findings.</p><p id="Par57">However, several limitations should be considered when interpreting the findings of the present study. First, the conclusions have not yet been validated in large-scale clinical cohorts, and future research will aim to enhance clinical applicability by increasing the sample size or conducting multicenter studies. Second, the synthesis and purification of cytolysin, a small peptide exotoxin, present considerable technical challenges. Owing to these constraints, we were unable to obtain purified cytolysin for in vitro stimulation experiments. Additionally, the lack of specific anti-cytolysin antibodies precluded both antagonistic validation experiments and the measurement of cytolysin levels in serum or cerebral spinal fluid. To overcome these challenges, future efforts will prioritize optimizing cytolysin synthesis, purification, and antibody development, potentially through collaboration with Professor Duan Yi or specialized biological laboratories. Third, while this study revealed that cytolysin induces brain injury via the NLRP3 pathway, the precise molecular mechanisms underlying its effect on NLRP3 remain unclear. Future investigations will employ in vitro models alongside advanced proteomic and epigenetic analyses, such as the phosphorylation and acetylation profiling of NLRP3, to provide deeper molecular insights. Despite these limitations, this study offers a strong foundation for further research and contributes to a more comprehensive understanding of the mechanisms linking gut microbiota-derived cytolysin to ischemic brain injury.</p><p id="Par58">In conclusion, the role of <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> and its exotoxin cytolysin in ischemic stroke were investigated in this study. The findings reveal that cytolysin exacerbates ischemic brain injury by disrupting TJs in brain microvascular endothelial cells, which increases BBB permeability. Animal experiments revealed that cytolysin activates the NLRP3 inflammasome, further impairing BBB integrity and worsening brain damage, and in vitro studies confirmed its direct endothelial toxicity and pro-inflammatory effects via NLRP3 activation. Additionally, cytolysin compromised intestinal barrier function by disrupting intestinal epithelial TJs. Notably, NLRP3 inhibition effectively mitigated cytolysin-induced stroke exacerbation, highlighting its therapeutic potential. This study is the first to establish the bridging role of cytolysin in post-stroke outcomes using both in vivo and in vitro models, providing critical insights into gut microbiota‒stroke interactions and offering new avenues for drug discovery and targeted interventions. Future studies should explore the therapeutic potential of targeting cytolysin and the gut–brain axis, which may inform precision strategies for stroke treatment.</p></sec><sec id="Sec32" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="12974_2025_3590_MOESM1_ESM.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher’s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn><p>Jia-ni Huang and Wei-hao Zhuang contributed equally to this work.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors thank all of the study participants and the clinical and research staff from the First Affiliated Hospital of Wenzhou Medical University for their contributions to this study.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors’ contributions</title><p>HJN performed the majority of the in vivo and in vitro experiments and drafted the manuscript. ZWH provided assistance with the animal experiments. LYS, ZYL, LJ, and HM participated in patient cohort recruitment and data analysis. XCL supported the manuscript revision. XRT contributed to the experimental design, manuscript writing, and revision. All authors reviewed and critically evaluated the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by the Wenzhou Municipal Science and Technology Bureau (Y20210170), the Projects of Natural Science Foundation of Zhejiang Province (LQ23H090005) and the Basic Research Funds of Wenzhou Medical University (KYYW202325).</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>Inquiries regarding the original data can be directed to the corresponding author, Ruoting Xu.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par59">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feigin</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Global and regional burden of stroke during 1990–2010: findings from the global burden of disease study 2010</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2014</year><volume>383</volume><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(13)61953-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24449944</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4181600</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Feigin VL, et al. Global and regional burden of stroke during 1990–2010: findings from the global burden of disease study 2010. Lancet. 2014;383:245–54.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24449944</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0140-6736(13)61953-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4181600</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Collaborators GBDSRF</collab></person-group><article-title>Global, regional, and national burden of stroke and its risk factors, 1990–2021: a systematic analysis for the global burden of disease study 2021</article-title><source>Lancet Neurol</source><year>2024</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>973</fpage><lpage>1003</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1474-4422(24)00369-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39304265</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12254192</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Collaborators GBDSRF. Global, regional, and national burden of stroke and its risk factors, 1990–2021: a systematic analysis for the global burden of disease study 2021. Lancet Neurol. 2024;23:973–1003.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39304265</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S1474-4422(24)00369-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12254192</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>2018 Guidelines for the Early Management of Patients With Acute Ischemic Stroke: A Guideline for Healthcare Professionals From the American Heart Association/American Stroke Association</article-title><source>STROKE</source><year>2018</year><volume>49</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>e46</fpage><lpage>e110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/STR.0000000000000158</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29367334</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Powers WJ, et al. 2018 Guidelines for the Early Management of Patients With Acute Ischemic Stroke: A Guideline for Healthcare Professionals From the American Heart Association/American Stroke Association. STROKE. 2018;49:e46-e110.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29367334</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1161/STR.0000000000000158</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Guidelines for the early management of patients with acute ischemic stroke: 2019 update to the 2018 guidelines for the early management of acute ischemic stroke: a guideline for healthcare professionals from the American Heart Association/American Stroke Association</article-title><source>Stroke</source><year>2019</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>e344</fpage><lpage>e418</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/STR.0000000000000211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31662037</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Powers WJ, et al. Guidelines for the early management of patients with acute ischemic stroke: 2019 update to the 2018 guidelines for the early management of acute ischemic stroke: a guideline for healthcare professionals from the American Heart Association/American Stroke Association. Stroke. 2019;50:e344–418.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31662037</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1161/STR.0000000000000211</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>New insight into gut microbiota and their metabolites in ischemic stroke: a promising therapeutic target</article-title><source>Biomed Pharmacother</source><year>2023</year><volume>162</volume><fpage>114559</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopha.2023.114559</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36989717</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Zhang S, et al. New insight into gut microbiota and their metabolites in ischemic stroke: a promising therapeutic target. Biomed Pharmacother. 2023;162:114559.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36989717</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.biopha.2023.114559</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanscom</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loane</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shea-Donohue</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Brain-gut axis dysfunction in the pathogenesis of traumatic brain injury</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>2021</year><volume>131</volume><fpage>e143777</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI143777</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34128471</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8203445</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Hanscom M, Loane DJ, Shea-Donohue T. Brain-gut axis dysfunction in the pathogenesis of traumatic brain injury. J Clin Invest. 2021;131:e143777.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34128471</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1172/JCI143777</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8203445</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR7" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>QQ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Patchouli alcohol attenuates the cognitive deficits in a Transgenic mouse model of alzheimer’s disease via modulating neuropathology and gut microbiota through suppressing C/EBPbeta/AEP pathway</article-title><source>J Neuroinflammation</source><year>2023</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>19</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12974-023-02704-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36717922</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9887791</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR7" publication-type="journal">Xu QQ, et al. Patchouli alcohol attenuates the cognitive deficits in a Transgenic mouse model of alzheimer’s disease via modulating neuropathology and gut microbiota through suppressing C/EBPbeta/AEP pathway. J Neuroinflammation. 2023;20:19.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36717922</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12974-023-02704-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9887791</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haak</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Disruptions of anaerobic gut bacteria are associated with stroke and post-stroke infection: a prospective case-control study</article-title><source>Transl Stroke Res</source><year>2021</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>581</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12975-020-00863-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33052545</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8213601</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Haak BW, et al. Disruptions of anaerobic gut bacteria are associated with stroke and post-stroke infection: a prospective case-control study. Transl Stroke Res. 2021;12:581–92.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33052545</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s12975-020-00863-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8213601</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gut microbiota composition reflects disease progression, severity and outcome, and dysfunctional immune responses in patients with hypertensive intracerebral hemorrhage</article-title><source>Front Immunol</source><year>2022</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>869846</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2022.869846</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36439158</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9699794</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Luo J, et al. Gut microbiota composition reflects disease progression, severity and outcome, and dysfunctional immune responses in patients with hypertensive intracerebral hemorrhage. Front Immunol. 2022;13:869846.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36439158</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fimmu.2022.869846</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9699794</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Tyne</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilmore</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure, function, and biology of the Enterococcus faecalis Cytolysin</article-title><source>Toxins (Basel)</source><year>2013</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>895</fpage><lpage>911</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/toxins5050895</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23628786</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3709268</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Van Tyne D, Martin MJ, Gilmore MS. Structure, function, and biology of the Enterococcus faecalis Cytolysin. Toxins (Basel). 2013;5:895–911.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23628786</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/toxins5050895</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3709268</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gurcel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abrami</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Girardin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tschopp</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van der Goot</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Caspase-1 activation of lipid metabolic pathways in response to bacterial pore-forming toxins promotes cell survival</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2006</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>1135</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2006.07.033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16990137</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Gurcel L, Abrami L, Girardin S, Tschopp J, van der Goot FG. Caspase-1 activation of lipid metabolic pathways in response to bacterial pore-forming toxins promotes cell survival. Cell. 2006;126:1135–45.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16990137</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cell.2006.07.033</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Munoz-Planillo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>K(+) efflux is the common trigger of NLRP3 inflammasome activation by bacterial toxins and particulate matter</article-title><source>Immunity</source><year>2013</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>1142</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2013.05.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23809161</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3730833</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Munoz-Planillo R, et al. K(+) efflux is the common trigger of NLRP3 inflammasome activation by bacterial toxins and particulate matter. Immunity. 2013;38:1142–53.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23809161</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.immuni.2013.05.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3730833</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural mechanisms of NLRP3 inflammasome assembly and activation</article-title><source>Annu Rev Immunol</source><year>2023</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>301</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-immunol-081022-021207</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36750315</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10159982</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Fu J, Wu H. Structural mechanisms of NLRP3 inflammasome assembly and activation. Annu Rev Immunol. 2023;41:301–16.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36750315</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1146/annurev-immunol-081022-021207</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10159982</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baroja-Mazo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The NLRP3 inflammasome is released as a particulate danger signal that amplifies the inflammatory response</article-title><source>Nat Immunol</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>738</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ni.2919</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24952504</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Baroja-Mazo A, et al. The NLRP3 inflammasome is released as a particulate danger signal that amplifies the inflammatory response. Nat Immunol. 2014;15:738–48.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24952504</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/ni.2919</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Broz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pelegrin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The gasdermins, a protein family executing cell death and inflammation</article-title><source>Nat Rev Immunol</source><year>2020</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41577-019-0228-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31690840</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Broz P, Pelegrin P, Shao F. The gasdermins, a protein family executing cell death and inflammation. Nat Rev Immunol. 2020;20:143–57.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31690840</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41577-019-0228-2</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Research progress on pyroptosis-mediated immune-inflammatory response in ischemic stroke and the role of natural plant components as regulator of pyroptosis: a review</article-title><source>Biomed Pharmacother</source><year>2023</year><volume>157</volume><fpage>113999</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopha.2022.113999</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36455455</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Yang K, et al. Research progress on pyroptosis-mediated immune-inflammatory response in ischemic stroke and the role of natural plant components as regulator of pyroptosis: a review. Biomed Pharmacother. 2023;157:113999.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36455455</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.biopha.2022.113999</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mechanism of inflammatory response and therapeutic effects of stem cells in ischemic stroke: current evidence and future perspectives</article-title><source>Neural Regen Res</source><year>2025</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/1673-5374.393104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38767477</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11246135</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Wang Y, et al. Mechanism of inflammatory response and therapeutic effects of stem cells in ischemic stroke: current evidence and future perspectives. Neural Regen Res. 2025;20:67–81.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38767477</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4103/1673-5374.393104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11246135</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Expression of Interleukin-1beta and matrix Metalloproteinase-8 in cytolytic and noncytolytic Enterococcus faecalis-induced persistent apical periodontitis: A comparative study in the rat</article-title><source>J Endod</source><year>2015</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>1288</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joen.2015.04.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26055433</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Lu B, et al. Expression of Interleukin-1beta and matrix Metalloproteinase-8 in cytolytic and noncytolytic Enterococcus faecalis-induced persistent apical periodontitis: A comparative study in the rat. J Endod. 2015;41:1288–93.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26055433</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.joen.2015.04.019</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>NOGOB receptor deficiency increases cerebrovascular permeability and hemorrhage via impairing histone acetylation-mediated CCM1/2 expression</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>2022</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>e151382</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI151382</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35316220</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9057619</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Fang Z, et al. NOGOB receptor deficiency increases cerebrovascular permeability and hemorrhage via impairing histone acetylation-mediated CCM1/2 expression. J Clin Invest. 2022;132:e151382.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35316220</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1172/JCI151382</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9057619</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kikuchi</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Poldip2 mediates blood-brain barrier disruption in a model of sepsis-associated encephalopathy</article-title><source>J Neuroinflammation</source><year>2019</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>241</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12974-019-1575-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31779628</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6883676</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Kikuchi DS, et al. Poldip2 mediates blood-brain barrier disruption in a model of sepsis-associated encephalopathy. J Neuroinflammation. 2019;16:241.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31779628</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12974-019-1575-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6883676</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tight junction proteins related to blood-brain barrier and their regulatory signaling pathways in ischemic stroke</article-title><source>Biomed Pharmacother</source><year>2023</year><volume>165</volume><fpage>115272</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopha.2023.115272</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37544283</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Zheng X, Ren B, Gao Y. Tight junction proteins related to blood-brain barrier and their regulatory signaling pathways in ischemic stroke. Biomed Pharmacother. 2023;165:115272.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37544283</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.biopha.2023.115272</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shui</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of pyroptosis in inflammatory diseases</article-title><source>Front Cell Dev Biol</source><year>2023</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1173235</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fcell.2023.1173235</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37250902</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10213465</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Chai R, Li Y, Shui L, Ni L, Zhang A. The role of pyroptosis in inflammatory diseases. Front Cell Dev Biol. 2023;11:1173235.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37250902</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fcell.2023.1173235</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10213465</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Camara-Lemarroy</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Biomarkers of intestinal barrier function in multiple sclerosis are associated with disease activity</article-title><source>Mult Scler</source><year>2020</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>1340</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1352458519863133</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31317818</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Camara-Lemarroy CR, et al. Biomarkers of intestinal barrier function in multiple sclerosis are associated with disease activity. Mult Scler. 2020;26:1340–50.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31317818</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/1352458519863133</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohto</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structural basis for the oligomerization-mediated regulation of NLRP3 inflammasome activation</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2022</year><volume>119</volume><fpage>e2121353119</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.2121353119</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35254907</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8931350</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Ohto U, et al. Structural basis for the oligomerization-mediated regulation of NLRP3 inflammasome activation. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2022;119:e2121353119.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35254907</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.2121353119</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8931350</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Winek</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Depletion of cultivatable gut microbiota by broad-spectrum antibiotic pretreatment worsens outcome after murine stroke</article-title><source>Stroke</source><year>2016</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>1354</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/STROKEAHA.115.011800</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27056982</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4839545</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Winek K, et al. Depletion of cultivatable gut microbiota by broad-spectrum antibiotic pretreatment worsens outcome after murine stroke. Stroke. 2016;47:1354–63.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27056982</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1161/STROKEAHA.115.011800</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4839545</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of combined live <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus cereus</italic> tablets on post-stroke depression and serum inflammatory factorse</article-title><source>Discov Med</source><year>2023</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>312</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.24976/Discov.Med.202335176.32</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37272098</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Wang Y, et al. Effects of combined live <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus cereus</italic> tablets on post-stroke depression and serum inflammatory factorse. Discov Med. 2023;35:312–20.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37272098</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.24976/Discov.Med.202335176.32</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Bacteriophage targeting of gut bacterium attenuates alcoholic liver disease</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2019</year><volume>575</volume><fpage>505</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-019-1742-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31723265</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6872939</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Duan Y, et al. Bacteriophage targeting of gut bacterium attenuates alcoholic liver disease. Nature. 2019;575:505–11.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31723265</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41586-019-1742-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6872939</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gut butyrate-producers confer post-infarction cardiac protection</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2023</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>7249</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-023-43167-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37945565</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10636175</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Chen HC, et al. Gut butyrate-producers confer post-infarction cardiac protection. Nat Commun. 2023;14:7249.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37945565</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41467-023-43167-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10636175</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Persidsky</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haorah</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kanmogne</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Blood-brain barrier: structural components and function under physiologic and pathologic conditions</article-title><source>J Neuroimmune Pharmacol</source><year>2006</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11481-006-9025-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18040800</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Persidsky Y, Ramirez SH, Haorah J, Kanmogne GD. Blood-brain barrier: structural components and function under physiologic and pathologic conditions. J Neuroimmune Pharmacol. 2006;1:223–36.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18040800</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11481-006-9025-3</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR30" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Novel</surname></name></person-group><article-title>MRI techniques identifying vascular leak and paravascular flow reduction in early alzheimer disease</article-title><source>Biomedicines</source><year>2020</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>228</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/biomedicines8070228</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32698354</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7400582</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR30" publication-type="journal">Joseph CR, Novel. MRI techniques identifying vascular leak and paravascular flow reduction in early alzheimer disease. Biomedicines. 2020;8:228.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32698354</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/biomedicines8070228</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7400582</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR31" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vinciguerra</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Update on the neurobiology of vascular cognitive impairment: from lab to clinic</article-title><source>Int J Mol Sci</source><year>2020</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>2977</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms21082977</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32340195</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7215552</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR31" publication-type="journal">Vinciguerra L, et al. Update on the neurobiology of vascular cognitive impairment: from lab to clinic. Int J Mol Sci. 2020;21:2977.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32340195</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijms21082977</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7215552</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kahles</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>NADPH oxidase plays a central role in blood-brain barrier damage in experimental stroke</article-title><source>Stroke</source><year>2007</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>3000</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/STROKEAHA.107.489765</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17916764</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Kahles T, et al. NADPH oxidase plays a central role in blood-brain barrier damage in experimental stroke. Stroke. 2007;38:3000–6.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17916764</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1161/STROKEAHA.107.489765</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Braniste</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The gut microbiota influences blood-brain barrier permeability in mice</article-title><source>Sci Transl Med</source><year>2014</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>263ra158</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/scitranslmed.3009759</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25411471</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4396848</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Braniste V, et al. The gut microbiota influences blood-brain barrier permeability in mice. Sci Transl Med. 2014;6:263ra158.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25411471</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/scitranslmed.3009759</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4396848</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR34" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frohlich</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cognitive impairment by antibiotic-induced gut dysbiosis: analysis of gut microbiota-brain communication</article-title><source>Brain Behav Immun</source><year>2016</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>140</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbi.2016.02.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26923630</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5014122</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR34" publication-type="journal">Frohlich EE, et al. Cognitive impairment by antibiotic-induced gut dysbiosis: analysis of gut microbiota-brain communication. Brain Behav Immun. 2016;56:140–55.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26923630</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bbi.2016.02.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5014122</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR35" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gut microbiota regulates blood-cerebrospinal fluid barrier function and Abeta pathology</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>2023</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>e111515</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15252/embj.2022111515</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37427561</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10476279</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR35" publication-type="journal">Xie J, et al. Gut microbiota regulates blood-cerebrospinal fluid barrier function and Abeta pathology. EMBO J. 2023;42:e111515.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37427561</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.15252/embj.2022111515</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10476279</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zhou F, et al. Electroacupuncture Attenuated Anxiety and Depression-Like Behavior via Inhibition of Hippocampal Inflammatory Response and Metabolic Disorders in TNBS-Induced IBD Rats. Oxid Med Cell Longev. 2022:8295580.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1155/2022/8295580</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8789424</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35087621</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR37" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vojdani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vojdani</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herbert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kharrazian</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Correlation between antibodies to bacterial lipopolysaccharides and barrier proteins in sera positive for ASCA and ANCA</article-title><source>Int J Mol Sci</source><year>2020</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>1381</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms21041381</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32085663</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7073094</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37" publication-type="journal">Vojdani A, Vojdani E, Herbert M, Kharrazian D. Correlation between antibodies to bacterial lipopolysaccharides and barrier proteins in sera positive for ASCA and ANCA. Int J Mol Sci. 2020;21:1381.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32085663</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijms21041381</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7073094</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR38" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vanhoutte</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woo</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Akkermansia muciniphila</italic> protects against atherosclerosis by preventing metabolic endotoxemia-induced inflammation in <italic toggle="yes">Apoe</italic>-/- mice</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>2016</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>2434</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.115.019645</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27143680</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR38" publication-type="journal">Li J, Lin S, Vanhoutte PM, Woo CW, Xu A. <italic toggle="yes">Akkermansia muciniphila</italic> protects against atherosclerosis by preventing metabolic endotoxemia-induced inflammation in <italic toggle="yes">Apoe</italic>-/- mice. Circulation. 2016;133:2434–46.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27143680</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.115.019645</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR39" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Breaking down the barriers: the gut microbiome, intestinal permeability and stress-related psychiatric disorders</article-title><source>Front Cell Neurosci</source><year>2015</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>392</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fncel.2015.00392</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26528128</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4604320</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR39" publication-type="journal">Kelly JR, et al. Breaking down the barriers: the gut microbiome, intestinal permeability and stress-related psychiatric disorders. Front Cell Neurosci. 2015;9:392.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26528128</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fncel.2015.00392</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4604320</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR40" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ting</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The NLRP3 inflammasome: molecular activation and regulation to therapeutics</article-title><source>Nat Rev Immunol</source><year>2019</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>477</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41577-019-0165-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31036962</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7807242</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR40" publication-type="journal">Swanson KV, Deng M, Ting JP. The NLRP3 inflammasome: molecular activation and regulation to therapeutics. Nat Rev Immunol. 2019;19:477–89.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31036962</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41577-019-0165-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7807242</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR41" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gugliandolo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Involvement of TLR4 and PPAR-alpha receptors in host response and NLRP3 inflammasome Activation, against pulmonary infection with Pseudomonas aeruginosa</article-title><source>SHOCK</source><year>2019</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/SHK.0000000000001137</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29547450</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41" publication-type="journal">Gugliandolo E, et al. Involvement of TLR4 and PPAR-alpha receptors in host response and NLRP3 inflammasome Activation, against pulmonary infection with Pseudomonas aeruginosa. SHOCK. 2019;51:221–7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29547450</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/SHK.0000000000001137</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR42" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borg</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The multifaceted roles of NLRP3-modulating proteins in virus infection</article-title><source>Front Immunol</source><year>2022</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>987453</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2022.987453</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36110852</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9468583</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR42" publication-type="journal">Harris J, Borg NA. The multifaceted roles of NLRP3-modulating proteins in virus infection. Front Immunol. 2022;13:987453.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36110852</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fimmu.2022.987453</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9468583</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR43" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Franke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The NLRP3 inflammasome drives inflammation in ischemia/reperfusion injury after transient middle cerebral artery occlusion in mice</article-title><source>Brain Behav Immun</source><year>2021</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbi.2020.12.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33307174</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR43" publication-type="journal">Franke M, et al. The NLRP3 inflammasome drives inflammation in ischemia/reperfusion injury after transient middle cerebral artery occlusion in mice. Brain Behav Immun. 2021;92:223–33.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33307174</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bbi.2020.12.009</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yang Z, Shi X, Gao Z, Chu L. miR-155-5p in Extracellular Vesicles Derived from Choroid Plexus Epithelial Cells Promotes Autophagy and Inflammation to Aggravate Ischemic Brain Injury in Mice. Oxid Med Cell Longev. 2022;8603427.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1155/2022/8603427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8865969</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35222806</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR45" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nlrp3 deficiency ameliorates neurovascular damage in experimental ischemic stroke</article-title><source>J Cereb Blood Flow Metab</source><year>2014</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>660</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/jcbfm.2013.242</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24424382</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3982086</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR45" publication-type="journal">Yang F, et al. Nlrp3 deficiency ameliorates neurovascular damage in experimental ischemic stroke. J Cereb Blood Flow Metab. 2014;34:660–7.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24424382</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/jcbfm.2013.242</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3982086</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR46" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bellut</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nlrp3 inhibition reduces rt-PA induced endothelial dysfunction under ischemic conditions</article-title><source>Biomedicines</source><year>2022</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>762</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/biomedicines10040762</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35453512</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9028140</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR46" publication-type="journal">Bellut M, et al. Nlrp3 inhibition reduces rt-PA induced endothelial dysfunction under ischemic conditions. Biomedicines. 2022;10:762.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35453512</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/biomedicines10040762</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9028140</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR47" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bellut</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>NLPR3 inflammasome inhibition alleviates hypoxic endothelial cell death in vitro and protects blood-brain barrier integrity in murine stroke</article-title><source>Cell Death Dis</source><year>2021</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>20</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41419-021-04379-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34930895</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8688414</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR47" publication-type="journal">Bellut M, et al. NLPR3 inflammasome inhibition alleviates hypoxic endothelial cell death in vitro and protects blood-brain barrier integrity in murine stroke. Cell Death Dis. 2021;13:20.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34930895</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41419-021-04379-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8688414</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR48" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kharrazian</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traumatic brain injury and the effect on the brain-Gut axis</article-title><source>Altern Ther Health Med</source><year>2015</year><volume>21</volume><issue>Suppl 3</issue><fpage>28</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26348611</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR48" publication-type="journal">Kharrazian D. Traumatic brain injury and the effect on the brain-Gut axis. Altern Ther Health Med. 2015;21(Suppl 3):28–32.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26348611</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR49" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bansal</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Traumatic brain injury and intestinal dysfunction: uncovering the neuro-enteric axis</article-title><source>J Neurotrauma</source><year>2009</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>1353</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/neu.2008.0858</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19344293</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2989839</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR49" publication-type="journal">Bansal V, et al. Traumatic brain injury and intestinal dysfunction: uncovering the neuro-enteric axis. J Neurotrauma. 2009;26:1353–9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19344293</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1089/neu.2008.0858</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2989839</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR50" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Intestinal barrier dysfunction following traumatic brain injury</article-title><source>Neurol Sci</source><year>2019</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>1105</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10072-019-03739-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30771023</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR50" publication-type="journal">Pan P, et al. Intestinal barrier dysfunction following traumatic brain injury. Neurol Sci. 2019;40:1105–10.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30771023</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10072-019-03739-0</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR51" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Shengui sansheng pulvis maintains blood-brain barrier integrity by vasoactive intestinal peptide after ischemic stroke</article-title><source>Phytomedicine</source><year>2020</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>153158</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phymed.2019.153158</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31999981</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR51" publication-type="journal">Xia ZY, et al. Shengui sansheng pulvis maintains blood-brain barrier integrity by vasoactive intestinal peptide after ischemic stroke. Phytomedicine. 2020;67:153158.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31999981</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.phymed.2019.153158</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Oyama N, et al. Exploratory investigation of intestinal function and bacterial translocation after focal cerebral ischemia in the mouse. Front Neurol. 2018;9:937.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fneur.2018.00937</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6254134</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30510535</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ye D, et al. Exploratory Investigation of Intestinal Structure and Function after Stroke in Mice. Mediators Inflamm. 2021:1315797.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1155/2021/1315797</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7902147</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33642941</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR54" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Steck</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus faecalis</italic> metalloprotease compromises epithelial barrier and contributes to intestinal inflammation</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><year>2011</year><volume>141</volume><fpage>959</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2011.05.035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21699778</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR54" publication-type="journal">Steck N, et al. <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus faecalis</italic> metalloprotease compromises epithelial barrier and contributes to intestinal inflammation. Gastroenterology. 2011;141:959–71.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21699778</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1053/j.gastro.2011.05.035</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR55" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Palkovicsne Pezsa</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kovacs</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galfi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Racz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farkas</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus faecium</italic> NCIMB 10415 on gut barrier function, internal redox state, proinflammatory response and pathogen inhibition properties in Porcine intestinal epithelial cells</article-title><source>Nutrients</source><year>2022</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1486</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nu14071486</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35406099</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9002907</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR55" publication-type="journal">Palkovicsne Pezsa N, Kovacs D, Galfi P, Racz B, Farkas O. Effect of <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus faecium</italic> NCIMB 10415 on gut barrier function, internal redox state, proinflammatory response and pathogen inhibition properties in Porcine intestinal epithelial cells. Nutrients. 2022;14:1486.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35406099</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/nu14071486</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9002907</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Luo M, et al. Protective effect of Enterococcus faecium and its extracellular vesiclesagainst Ethanol-Induced intestinal injury. Foodborne Pathog Dis. 2025;22:585–93.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1089/fpd.2024.0061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39474696</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR57" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of the dietary probiotic, <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus faecium</italic> NCIMB11181, on the intestinal barrier and system immune status in <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> O78-challenged broiler chickens</article-title><source>Probiotics Antimicrob Proteins</source><year>2019</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>946</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12602-018-9434-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29948799</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6695369</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR57" publication-type="journal">Huang L, Luo L, Zhang Y, Wang Z, Xia Z. Effects of the dietary probiotic, <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus faecium</italic> NCIMB11181, on the intestinal barrier and system immune status in <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> O78-challenged broiler chickens. Probiotics Antimicrob Proteins. 2019;11:946–56.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29948799</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s12602-018-9434-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6695369</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR58" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Solheim</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aakra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Snipen</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brede</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nes</surname><given-names>IF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative genomics of <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus faecalis</italic> from healthy Norwegian infants</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2009</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>194</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-10-194</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19393078</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2680900</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR58" publication-type="journal">Solheim M, Aakra A, Snipen LG, Brede DA, Nes IF. Comparative genomics of <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus faecalis</italic> from healthy Norwegian infants. BMC Genomics. 2009;10:194.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19393078</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-2164-10-194</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2680900</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR59" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Albeke</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gigley</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbiome composition in both wild-type and disease model mice is heavily influenced by mouse facility</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1598</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2018.01598</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30079054</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6062620</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR59" publication-type="journal">Parker KD, Albeke SE, Gigley JP, Goldstein AM, Ward NL. Microbiome composition in both wild-type and disease model mice is heavily influenced by mouse facility. Front Microbiol. 2018;9:1598.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30079054</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fmicb.2018.01598</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6062620</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR60" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Swann</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Considerations for the design and conduct of human gut microbiota intervention studies relating to foods</article-title><source>Eur J Nutr</source><year>2020</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>3347</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00394-020-02232-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32246263</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7669793</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR60" publication-type="journal">Swann JR, et al. Considerations for the design and conduct of human gut microbiota intervention studies relating to foods. Eur J Nutr. 2020;59:3347–68.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32246263</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00394-020-02232-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7669793</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR61" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ecological dynamics of the gut microbiome in response to dietary fiber</article-title><source>ISME J</source><year>2022</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>2040</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41396-022-01253-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35597888</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9296629</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR61" publication-type="journal">Liu H, et al. Ecological dynamics of the gut microbiome in response to dietary fiber. ISME J. 2022;16:2040–55.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35597888</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41396-022-01253-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9296629</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR62" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Manos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The human microbiome in disease and pathology</article-title><source>APMIS</source><year>2022</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>690</fpage><lpage>705</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/apm.13225</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35393656</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9790345</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR62" publication-type="journal">Manos J. The human microbiome in disease and pathology. APMIS. 2022;130:690–705.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35393656</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/apm.13225</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9790345</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR63" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The interactions between host genome and gut microbiome increase the risk of psychiatric disorders: Mendelian randomization and biological annotation</article-title><source>Brain Behav Immun</source><year>2023</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>400</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbi.2023.08.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37557965</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11258998</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR63" publication-type="journal">Xiao L, et al. The interactions between host genome and gut microbiome increase the risk of psychiatric disorders: Mendelian randomization and biological annotation. Brain Behav Immun. 2023;113:389–400.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37557965</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bbi.2023.08.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11258998</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR64" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Montiel-Castro</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez-Cervantes</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bravo-Ruiseco</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pacheco-Lopez</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The microbiota-gut-brain axis: neurobehavioral correlates, health and sociality</article-title><source>Front Integr Neurosci</source><year>2013</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>70</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnint.2013.00070</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24109440</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3791857</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR64" publication-type="journal">Montiel-Castro AJ, Gonzalez-Cervantes RM, Bravo-Ruiseco G, Pacheco-Lopez G. The microbiota-gut-brain axis: neurobehavioral correlates, health and sociality. Front Integr Neurosci. 2013;7:70.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24109440</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fnint.2013.00070</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3791857</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR65" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dao</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Akkermansia muciniphila</italic> and improved metabolic health during a dietary intervention in obesity: relationship with gut microbiome richness and ecology</article-title><source>Gut</source><year>2016</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>426</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/gutjnl-2014-308778</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26100928</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR65" publication-type="journal">Dao MC, et al. <italic toggle="yes">Akkermansia muciniphila</italic> and improved metabolic health during a dietary intervention in obesity: relationship with gut microbiome richness and ecology. Gut. 2016;65:426–36.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26100928</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/gutjnl-2014-308778</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Xie Y, et al. Effects of diet based on IgG elimination combined with probiotics on migraine plus irritable bowel syndrome. Pain Res Manag. 2019:7890461.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1155/2019/7890461</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6721378</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31531150</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR67" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Animal models of stroke</article-title><source>Anim Models Exp Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>204</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ame2.12179</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8446711</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34557647</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR67" publication-type="journal">Li Y, Zhang J. Animal models of stroke. Anim Models Exp Med. 2021;4:204–19.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/ame2.12179</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8446711</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34557647</pub-id></mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>